<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Endoxa, or, Some probable inquiries into truth, both divine and humane: together with a stone to the altar: or, short disquisitions on a few difficult places of Scripture; as also, a calm ventilation of Pseudo-doxia epidemica. / By John Robinson, Dr. of Physick. Translated and augmented by the author.</title>
            <title>Endoxa. English</title>
            <author>Robinson, John, M.D.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1658</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 215 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 80 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A91895</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R1700</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1821_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R203377</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863347</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863347</idno>
            <idno type="VID">115542</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A91895)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 115542)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 227:E1821[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Endoxa, or, Some probable inquiries into truth, both divine and humane: together with a stone to the altar: or, short disquisitions on a few difficult places of Scripture; as also, a calm ventilation of Pseudo-doxia epidemica. / By John Robinson, Dr. of Physick. Translated and augmented by the author.</title>
                  <title>Endoxa. English</title>
                  <author>Robinson, John, M.D.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 151, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J. Streater, for Francis Tyton,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1658.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Translated from Latin.</note>
                  <note>"Pseudodoxia epidemica" is by Sir Thomas Browne.</note>
                  <note>With a preliminary errata leaf.</note>
                  <note>"A stone to the altar" and "A calm ventilation of Pseudodoxia epidemica" each have separate dated title page; pagination and register are continuous.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aprill".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Browne, Thomas, --  Sir, 1605-1682. --  Pseudodoxia epidemica --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Bible --  Commentaries --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Truthfulness and falsehood --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:115542:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>ENDOXA, <hi>OR,</hi> Some probable <hi>Inquiries</hi> INTO TRUTH, BOTH <hi>Divine</hi> and <hi>Humane:</hi> Together with <hi>A STONE to the ALTAR:</hi> OR, Short Diſquiſitions on a few difficult places of <hi>SCRIPTURE;</hi> AS ALSO, <hi>A CALM VENTILATION</hi> OF <hi>PSEUDO-DOXIA EPIDEMICA.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>By <hi>John Robinſon,</hi> Dr. of Phyſick.</p>
                  <p>Tranſlated and augmented by the Author.</p>
                  <figure/>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Though divers Heads, Faces averſe you ſee;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Yet for Truth's ſake, they all in Heart agree.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>
                     <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. Streater,</hi> for <hi>Francis Tyton,</hi> 1658.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="table_of_contents">
                  <pb facs="tcp:115542:2"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:115542:2"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>The Contents of the</hi> Endoxa.</head>
                  <list>
                     <item>Chap. 1. Of a Church. Pag. 1</item>
                     <item>Chap. 2. Of Miniſters. Pag. 20</item>
                     <item>Chap. 3. Of Sacraments. Pag. 25</item>
                     <item>Chap. 4. Of <hi>Adam.</hi> Pag. 28</item>
                     <item>Chap. 5. Of Marriage. Pag. 33</item>
                     <item>Chap. 6. Of Sympathy. Pag. 39</item>
                     <item>Chap. 7. Of an Egge. Pag. 43</item>
                     <item>Chap. 8. Of Floating or Swimming. Pag. 45</item>
                     <item>Chap. 9. Of Remedies. Pag. 48</item>
                     <item>Chap. 10. Of Teleſmes. Pag. 52</item>
                  </list>
               </div>
               <div type="key">
                  <pb facs="tcp:115542:3"/>
                  <head>A Key to the <hi>Work.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THe Pillars of this Univerſe are the</hi> Church, <hi>to which for guidance</hi> Miniſters <hi>are ſent, for ſolace</hi> Sacraments: <hi>It conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth man either innocent as was</hi> Adam; <hi>or fallen, as his Poſterity: The due propagation whereof is by</hi> Matriage: <hi>This uſhereth in love and</hi> Sympathy, <hi>being part of the Parents; The truth whereof is examined in an</hi> Egge, <hi>whence diſſimilar parts ariſing, are beſt diſtinguiſhed by</hi> Floating: <hi>Theſe, in a right order, are preſerved, in diſorder rectified by lawful</hi> Remedies, <hi>not by</hi> Teleſmes: <hi>Or thus, Man may he conſidered as a Subject of Morality, which taketh up the firſt four Chapters; or as a Political Subject, which is handled in the two middle ones; or as a Body Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſical; which finiſheth the rest of the Treatiſe.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="preface">
                  <pb facs="tcp:115542:3"/>
                  <head>The Preface, <hi>To the candid Reader.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>TRuth, both divine and naturall, hath two adverſaries; one reall, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in a mask. The real is all ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique, though not diametrically op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite, Error, The other, when, by our miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtruction, Verity ſeemeth combating with it ſelf; as ſeverall places in Holy Writ. Now, to reconcile that which hath a ſemblance of repugnancy, and to reſcue truth ſurrounded with falſhood, is a badge, both of charity and valour; and to an ingenuous mind its own ſufficient recompence.</p>
                  <p>Some upon a ſupine deſpondency procraſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate their ſearching into truth, becauſe at our neerer union with God, which we ſhall enjoy at our ſolemn change, we ſhal know all things more perfectly: yet is it a more heroick ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, to antedate heaven, to aſſay to add ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing unto eternity <hi>à priori,</hi> cauſing it to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin the ſooner: That eternall beatitude con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting in knowledge and holineſſe, which dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer from theſe our commenced and initiated firſt fruits, onely in degree. He that hath not had a primitiall caſt and prelibation of them
<pb facs="tcp:115542:4"/>
here below, is like never to be ſatiated with a full harveſt of them above.</p>
                  <p>Here therefore you have a handfull of ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt <note place="margin">Nec ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men ſine calce a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rena.</note> conceptions, or rather, abortions of mine; their birth at firſt, for ſome reaſon, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing precipitated; there hanging then over our heads the fear of a great cataract, ſwiftly running down, from the top of the higheſt Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate; by which the ſoil of ſuperſtition was not ſo much likely to be rinced off; as the tender ſprouting graſs of ſincere godlines was in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to be choaked. Beſides, neither my <hi>Genius,</hi> nor calling, will allow me a ſequeſtred time, to dwell long upon any ſubject: Afterward, at more leiſure, and, I hope, without being te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious, I have, in ſome meaſure, endeavoured their augmentation.</p>
                  <p>It was with me, as with them that dwell near the coaſt, who, upon a Sea-breach, will caſt in any thing that is next at hand; though but looſely compacted; which, the ſpringtide being over, and waves calmed, they can more orderly diſpoſe againſt a future inundation: Neither, in a publick flame, would I have my bucket, though of a leſſer ſize, to be wanting.</p>
                  <p>The ſtyle and method is neither accurate, nor altogether neglected: yet one thing I muſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertiſe the Reader, concerning the tranſlation; that though I was conſcious to my own weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, in the Engliſh Tongue, becanſe of my long aboad out of my native Country; yet, becauſe the drift of the Authour is beſt known to my ſelf, that would make ſome recompenſe for the
<pb facs="tcp:115542:4"/>
barbarous andhobnail phraſes, wherein are ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral worde, for neceſſity more then affectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which, in a vulgar ear, would ſooner beget a wonder then ſatisfaction.</p>
                  <p>If any thing be falſe, [for we are but men] do not carp at it; but teach better. I ſhall promiſe my ſelf, though here and there be gray haires, a willing and thankfull diſciple: If there be doubts, [as in untract paths it is hard to find the neareſt way] let them be exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined by the ſcales of the Sanctuary, and beam of right reaſon: What is true, embrace and lodge it. Let neither the meanneſſe of the <hi>Superficies,</hi> nor dwarſneſſe of the Bulk, prepoſſeſſe your, otherwiſe unbiaſed, expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. <hi>Among the ruſhes you may stumble up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Exod. 2. Eſa. 65.</note> 
                     <hi>a</hi> Moſes, <hi>and there may be a Bleſſing, even in a Cluſter of Grapes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>You may meet with two obſtacles retard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your conſent: Firſt, that I take many <hi>Poſtulata</hi> for granted; which, becauſe they are by others ſufficiently proved, I doe on purpoſe paſs over: And then, that the names of the Authors are not ſet down; to which I anſwer, that ſome are <hi>Anonymi,</hi> though not to me: Beſides, I have no quarrell with any man; but rather diſcuſs the queſtions which many defend.</p>
                  <p>My intention is not to enter into the field of controverſy, with all the ſtrength, and main body of a <hi>Battalie;</hi> but rather by excurſions, in a velitary way, to skirmiſh with ſome, whom (all due love and reſpect unviolated) I diſſent from.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:115542:5"/>
My wiſhed end is, by gentle concuſſion, the emulſion of truth, and ſo reduce the fruit of theſe exercitations into practiſe; that, by e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melioration of Judgment, they may, in their proportion, be uſefull to the generation wherein we live: which if I find to anſwer my deſires, I will acknowledge as an ample reward of theſe few unfiled lines.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <salute>Farewell.</salute>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:115542:5"/>
                  <head>ENDOXA. OR, <hi>Some profitable Inquiries into Truth, both</hi> Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine <hi>and</hi> Humane.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. I.</head>
                     <argument>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Of a Church.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </argument>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen by a figurative denomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, an Error, or, which is of affinity unto it, Confuſion and Ambiguity is either be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten or foſtered; then I think it ſafeſt, to reduce it to its primitive ſimplicity. Our <hi>Saviour</hi> citeth corrupt manners, to the Tribunal of <hi>firſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution: Mat.</hi> 19. 8. Words are more flexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; When I call <hi>Tueſday</hi> the third day of the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:115542:6"/>
week, to a <hi>Jew</hi> or <hi>Turk,</hi> [its well, if not to many <hi>Engliſh,]</hi> I ſhall be a <hi>Barbarian. Mars-Hill, Castor</hi> and <hi>Pollux,</hi> were no idolatrous titles, in the mouth of the holy Scribe. An appellation of a brother, to a beleiver, is moſt rationall, where there can fall no miſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction: In religious actions, I commend it; but not in civill converſation; For then muſt I, except I infringe the rule of <hi>Jam.</hi> 2. call and write my Father, Son, and Servant, <hi>Brother;</hi> which is a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founding of Relations. Here would have been a ſpecious excuſe for <hi>Abraham's</hi> ſimula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: <hi>Gen.</hi> 12. <hi>&amp;</hi> 20. So in this ſubject, the attributes belonging to the body of Chriſt, <hi>i. e.</hi> his Church, are conferred upon the place; as glory, holineſſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Theſe titles did in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed in ſome meaſure, and for a certain time befit the <hi>Temple</hi> at <hi>Jeruſalem:</hi> becauſe this ſole place God had aſſigned for his ſolemn Worſhip: But, the Vaile being rent, <hi>any place</hi> of ſervice, <hi>ſo it were in truth and ſpirit,</hi> was agreeable unto him, <hi>John</hi> 4. which hath of late made a juſt diſtinction between a meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <note place="margin">Templum quod teneat populum.</note> people and houſe. But to the thing.</p>
                     <p>There being ſeveral opinions concerning a Church, both ancient and modern; I will endeavour, what may be, to build upon ſuch general <hi>conceſſa,</hi> drawn from Sacred page or reaſon, as whereby the truth may be moſt manifeſt.</p>
                     <p>That God had a Church, that is, a ſelected company out of the World, from <hi>Cain's</hi> time &amp;
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:115542:6"/>
ſhall have unto the end, is undeniable among all profeſſing Chriſtianity: Firſt in <hi>Families,</hi> as in <hi>Noah, Melchizedeck, Abraham;</hi> after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in the <hi>Nation</hi> of the <hi>Iews;</hi> and now un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Goſpel, diſperſed throughout the <hi>face of the earth.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>This <hi>Church,</hi> as it is taken for an Univerſall <hi>Congregatum,</hi> or Collective, are all the belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, paſt, preſent, and, in ſome ſenſe, to come. The <hi>Jews,</hi> Gods elder daughter, did not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain, to call the Church of the <hi>Gentiles, their younger Siſter;</hi> though <hi>without breaſts,</hi> i. e. the ſincere milk of the Word: yea, yet unborn, <hi>Cant.</hi> 8. 8. This may be called, as vulgarly it is, the <hi>Univerſall</hi> or <hi>Catholick Church,</hi> out of <note place="margin">For which who pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth for the dead.</note> which there is no ſalvation: And of this ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny have been and are amongſt the <hi>Pagaus, Turks,</hi> and remoteſt <hi>Hereticks:</hi> ſaved by a way unknown to us: as <hi>little Children</hi> are ſaid to <hi>believe: Math.</hi> 18. 6. i. e. onely paſſively; having the root, though not the form. Theſe hidden things are beyond the reach of any Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical Conſiſtory.</p>
                     <p>But that there are <hi>particular Churches,</hi> and joyned into bodyes, is paſt all contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie.</p>
                     <p>Now, that the way of gathering of them, as well as ruling, is in a determinate manner unalterably ſet down, either in the heart of man, [which none can averre,] or in the holy word by God himſelf, [let them eſpecially look to this who urge an uniforme diſcipline upon all Churches,] might be gathered thus.
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:115542:7"/>
A Prince demanding obedience of his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, muſt needs ſet down poſitive Laws, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alterable, but by himſelf; and not leave it to their prudentiall change, <hi>Where, When,</hi> and <hi>How</hi> to obey: This is a clear dictate of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon which God doth not ordinarily contradict. Thus did <hi>Adam, Noah, Abraham,</hi> before the written-Scripture, teach their Families, by the primmer of divine Traditions: Not that every one by <hi>Enthuſiaſm</hi> was immediately inſpired; the teaching of their Children elſe had been fruſtraneous, which God and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture abhorreth. Afterward, God himſelf gave <hi>Moſes</hi> a perfect pattern of every particular thing in the Tabernacle, even unto the ſmall<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt <hi>bagatello's,</hi> from the which he might not warp an Inch; which did bind the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> immutably unto the time of <hi>Salomon;</hi> who likewiſe did not in the leaſt deviate from the expreſſe command of God in the meaneſt <hi>punctillo:</hi> Hereunto were the <hi>Iews</hi> obliged untill Chriſt's time. And what <hi>the Phariſees did</hi> in the worſhip of God, either <hi>omit, adde, or alter,</hi> was liſted among the <hi>traditions of men;</hi> and ſo rejected as ſpurious. And is it reaſon, that after Chriſts comming, it ſhould be left to prudence of man, either Prince or Church, to vary any way of worſhip of God, according to the mutability of their own diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion?</p>
                     <p>The whole ſtream of both Teſtaments run irreſiſtably this way: God menaceth judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to the <hi>Iews, becauſe their fear towards
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:115542:7"/>
him, was taught by the precepts of men,</hi> Iſa. 29. 13. And the <hi>Temple</hi> [ſpeaking of Chriſtian Churches] is <hi>exactly meaſured by</hi> John, <hi>Revel.</hi> 11. which is far wide from any prudentiall way, or [which prudence importeth] any al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration upon occurrences.</p>
                     <p>Moreover, the <hi>Author</hi> to the <hi>Hebrews</hi> doth expreſly teach the <hi>faithfulneſſe of Chriſt as a Son; above Moſes as a Servant;</hi> in ſetting down every particular concerning the ordering of his <hi>Houſe,</hi> which is the <hi>Church:</hi> which no earthly power can or ought to change, or ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence the publiſhing of it: but every one is bound faithfully to ſubmit unto, and in his place to divulge: He is bound, I mean in <hi>foro divino.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>That God did at any time change the exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall garbe of his Church, was no mark of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adviſedneſſe in the Guardian; but of weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in his Ward. He would, in the twi-light and morning of the Goſpel, have his orphane put on her night-attire, that the Sun being ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen, ſhe might wear her Nuptiall Garment; untill it, [with all outward ſervices] do ſet for ever.</p>
                     <p>What <hi>Politicians</hi> diſtinguiſh between <hi>Law</hi> and <hi>Counſell,</hi> is granted between man and man; but the introduction of this diſtinction into divinity, doth look with the face of an encroachment. For to deſpiſe either of theſe, is <hi>ſin,</hi> and that is the <hi>breach of the Law:</hi> The reaſon is clear; becauſe all his Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments aime at our good; and all his counſels,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:115542:8"/>
are, unqueſtionably, profitable for us; none of which quadrateth with thoſe of men. That <hi>Chriſt,</hi> Mark 10. <hi>doth bid the young man ſell all,</hi> muſt not be taken in an abſolute ſenſe, for a poſitive command, or ſtanding rule to him, or any others; but by way of probation: If theſe things be true, give a Teſtimony, the ſelling of all thy goods.</p>
                     <p>To wade a little further; the cauſes of a <hi>Church,</hi> [as being known] I do but men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
                     <p>The <hi>Efficient;</hi> God, out of his love, through the word and ſpirit, perſwading mens hearts to believe in his Son.</p>
                     <p>The <hi>Materiall;</hi> are all the Saints, and mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of his myſticall body.</p>
                     <p>The <hi>Pormal,</hi> Union with him, and one with another.</p>
                     <p>The <hi>Final,</hi> his own honour; their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſting themſelves into the formet, or rather, better image of Himſelf; the edifying one another, and their mutuall eternall bliſſe.</p>
                     <p>Now the way of gathering, and rule of go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verning is the ſame; namely the preaching of <note place="margin">Ex quibus conſtamus, iiſdem nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimur.</note> the word of God.</p>
                     <p>But becauſe the manner of divulging the Goſpel, is by ſome of our age controverted; and they would have nothing to be the word of God, but the very text of the Old and New Teſtament; becauſe, ſay they, <hi>a concionatory way is not wholly, intrinſecally, undoubtedly, and meerly true;</hi> driving rather to content them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:115542:8"/>
with a private conclave worſhip; by reading of the ſole Scripture, as it is and lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth; than to be preſent at, an aſſembly pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly ſerving God.</p>
                     <p>In a body Politick, it is no wiſe to be tol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerated, much leſſe in any Eccleſiaſticall cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poration; that without mutuall help, whilſt every one ſets up for himſelf, the externall invaſion of publick adverſaries, or the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſtick pruning of rotten branches, ſhould be neglected.</p>
                     <p>Of theſe, I deſire firſt to ask one queſtiou: <hi>Whether the Word in its original, not being under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, be able to convert ſouls?</hi> Or, <hi>Whether all to be converted, must be maſters of the Hebrew and Greek Languages?</hi> Which both ſeem ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurdities: Or, which neceſſarily muſt follow; they muſt be converted by the word tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; which, beſides the various readings of the Originals, <hi>is not wholly, intrinſecally, undoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedly, and meerly true.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>I ſhall point at a few reaſons.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. God in writing his holy Will, would not give us bare husks of words; but by them the ſolid kernel of his intended minde: <hi>Neh.</hi> 8. 8. doth teach, that what by right reaſon can be concluded from authority of Scripture, is Scripture, though no text: we being endued with reaſon, as well as the <hi>Beroeaus,</hi> who for <hi>examining</hi> the truth, in its ſelf authentick, were honoured with the Title of <hi>Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="2">
                        <pb n="8" facs="tcp:115542:9"/>
2. The Holy Ghoſt frequently varieth the Text, in quoting the Septuagint, only keeping to the meaning of the Spirit.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. If private meetings be ſatisfactory, then are all admonitions, cenſures, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> fruſtrated, <hi>Mat.</hi> 24. 26.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. <hi>Every firſt day of the week, when ye are met together, lay aſide for the poor.</hi> The ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection which the <hi>Antiſynuſians</hi> make, that this precept was but tranſient, to laſt but for a while, Chriſt meeteth withall; <hi>Iohn</hi> 12. 8. That <hi>the poor,</hi> therefore Deacons, <hi>will be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuated.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="5">5. <hi>We may not withdraw from publick aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies,</hi> Heb. 10. 25.</p>
                     <p n="6">6. <hi>Faith cometh by hearing.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>By Hearing, is meant, any way of attaining knowledge and ſo is Reading.</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Object.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>If by hearing here be underſtood reading, <note place="margin">Anſw.</note> I marvel what conſtruction they will make of the ſubſequent words, <hi>they muſt be ſent:</hi> and how this ſending is competent unto books, I cannot underſtand. Reading, I grant, is an informing and perfecting of the underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding; but that the will and affections, [the main wheels in faith] are thereby, as well as by a lively voice drawn into conſent, I ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly deny: And becauſe the clock of our love, by the weight of our terreſtrialls, run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth down from God continually, we need every day, by the cords of our affections, a new winding up of former truths.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="9" facs="tcp:115542:9"/>
Againſt theſe premiſed things, there is a <note place="margin">Object.</note> great and general Objection. <hi>That the externall form of words in preaching, praying; the dayes and places inſtituted for fasting and thanksgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, with other circumstances, are not diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctly ſet down in holy Scripture; but may in a prudentiall way, according to the exigence of oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions or perſons, be changed.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>In the Worſhip of God two things are to <note place="margin">Anſw.</note> be conſidered; The Subſtance, and the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary intervening Adjuncts: That the word of God muſt be preached, the Sacraments ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred, in time of danger Gods help muſt be implored, after deliverances praiſes muſt be returned; is an inſtitution of God, and ſo a law unalterable: The intermixed adjuncts, crowding into all our actions, are naturall and no part of Gods worſhip: The manner of expreſſion, the time is no more then the place; nor the publick either time or place, more than a private, whiles I am with God in my cloſet-approaches, or Family-duties: they being ſuch Circumſtances, without which nothing can be done; A naturall neceſſity of adjuncts will follow, without the ſpurre of a command; nor need any curb of reſtraint: If there be any holineſs in them, it is for the works ſake, and ſo but Relative.</p>
                     <p>The difference is worth obſerving, when the work is done for the dayes ſake, or the day is uſed for the works ſake: If the Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance be determined by God, it becommeth <note place="margin">☜</note> a neceſſary part of his worſhip; which no
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:115542:10"/>
man can extort out of his hand; it being a Prerogative Royall, belonging only to him, to make any time, place, or perſon ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</p>
                     <p>Beſides, becauſe theſe circumſtances are fortuitous, they do overturn and interrupt the Celebration of anniverſary-dayes: ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times, to our long-prefixed humiliation, a ſuddain victory will run counter; and unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected calamities will quench the feudejoy of a long-fore-ſet gratulation: But theſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents being various, we muſt from a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral rule, draw forth the particulars.</p>
                     <p>All God's diſpenſations are books of his appointment, which we may and muſt read; though in them there be many hard leſſons: But to erect and keep any thing for a holy uſe, upon the authority of our own compla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency, is to build too near the banks of Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition.</p>
                     <p>Neither do I mean by holineſſe, a ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed uſe, as many cavil; for ſo is meat and drink; but ſeparated unto an holy end. The <hi>Sabbath</hi> is excepted, which [give leave to a ſmall digreſſion] being firſt inſtituted <hi>in rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to Chriſt, Pſal.</hi> 118. 22, 23, 24. was an ordinance of grace, and not of nature; nor competent to <hi>Adam</hi> in innocency; and is <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Geo. Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker,</hi> of the Sabbath.</note> holy for it ſelf ſake, though no body in the world ſhould keep it. Let it be no hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance to the truth of theſe words, that but little mention was made of it, before the Law written in ſtones, either in <hi>Marah</hi> or
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:115542:10"/>
                        <hi>Aluſh;</hi> No more there is of other long-lived Laws, as that <hi>a man ſhould marry his Brothers widdow,</hi> or, <hi>that whoredome ſhould be puniſhed with death,</hi> and the like; which eaſily might be proved to be in force before; I ſpeak of a civil Law, under which rank theſe fore-men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned do march: not of the moral Law, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graven in the heart of all mankinde.</p>
                     <p>They object further; <hi>Many things are adi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aphorous</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Object.</note> 
                        <hi>and indifferent, the choice whereof is within the command of our will.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>By what is ſaid may be concluded, that in <note place="margin">Anſw.</note> Gods worſhip there is nothing indifferent: In natural things moſt actions do contemn the voice of our command. To ſpeak with the Schools, I adde more preſly; Though in <hi>actu ſignato,</hi> there may be; yet that there is no indifferency in <hi>actu exercito,</hi> I remember to have read with full ſatisfaction.</p>
                     <p>But to cloſe more near: Beſides the <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall Church</hi> diſperſed here on earth, God hath appointed ſome particular Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to joyn into bodies, for their mutuall edification; which challenge right to all the ordinances, left by Chriſt, and his Apoſtles: as is, the receiving in, building up, caſting out; which actions, not being competent to the <hi>Univerſall,</hi> do juſtly deſcend to the <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteriall</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Univerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libus non competunt perſonalia.</note> 
                        <hi>or Oeconomicall Churches;</hi> whoſe duty it is, to ſee their inheritance not to lay waſte.</p>
                     <p>The <hi>Antiſynagogians</hi> do object; <hi>that there</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Object.</note>
                        <pb n="12" facs="tcp:115542:11"/>
                        <hi>is no crime in the Church, which the Chriſtian Magistrate is not to take notice of.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>This title I underſtand in diviſion, not in a <note place="margin">Anſw.</note> conjunction; Nor a Chriſtian Phyſician, or Mathemematician, to preſcribe pious rules of Health, or Angels: Morality, not faith, is requiſite in a Prince; <hi>Caeſar</hi> was as eſſentiall, and integrall an Emperour, as was <hi>Joſhua.</hi> But what if he fall into ſcandalous errors, or practiſes? by what meanes ſhall he be mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, or removed, not as a Magiſtrate, but as a commenſall and fellow-commoner with the faithfull? what if he neglect his duty? ſhall all run to wrack? Were there not in the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles and latter times, Churches, for their piety and purity, as famous as ever? But power being granted, abilities for diſcerning hereſies, accompliſhments for publick and private duties, are neither allotted nor requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, in a civil power, <hi>quà talis.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>That ſentence, which goeth cheek by jowle with Scripture; that <hi>Moſes,</hi> and thence all Magiſtrates, <hi>are the preſervers of both tables,</hi> will hardly go down with me? By <hi>keepers</hi> they muſt underſtand [impertinency attends others interpretations] <hi>overſeers,</hi> to look to the outward execution of the Ten commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; which if it were granted unto <hi>Moſes,</hi> it would prove but a lame argumentation, to derive it unto Princes under the Goſpel; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe their Church and Common-weale, were the ſame ſubjects. We are to pray and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:115542:11"/>
for the converſion of the <hi>Jews,</hi> which can hardly be conceived without converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: But, upon their co-habitation with us, to compell them, againſt conſcience, to a poſitive Celebration of our <hi>Lords day,</hi> were <note place="margin">Duci non trahi vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lunt.</note> a prepoſterous way to gain them to the true faith. The <hi>interdiction of publick labour,</hi> for the not diſturbance of the reſt, is ſufficient, <hi>Neh.</hi> 13. 19. The <hi>Sabbath</hi> being a leſſon of grace, cannot be read by the letters of reaſon, as was mentioned before.</p>
                     <p>But, as the injunction of all Divine wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip upon an unbeliever hath little equity in it; ſo neither is it poſſible for the <hi>Supreme Power</hi> to take cognizance of the breach of every Commandement: For the laſt precept, <hi>Thou ſhalt not covet,</hi> &amp;c. the new conceived motions, and infant-affections of the deſire of <hi>our Neighbour's goods</hi> are forbidden; which becauſe not apparent, they are as if they were not; [I ſpeak <hi>ad hominem]</hi> according to that Maxim, <hi>Non entis &amp; non apparentis eadem eſt ratio.</hi> When theſe concupiſcences break forth into actions, they are to be ranked un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the heads of <hi>Adultery</hi> or <hi>Theft;</hi> And the <hi>Dealogue</hi> doth not admit of Tautology: This <hi>concupiſence</hi> if it be <hi>hidden to ones own ſelf,</hi> Rom. 7. 7. How ſhall it be manifeſt unto others? Thus God ſecurerh both tables with a lock, which no key of reaſon can open.</p>
                     <p>That place <hi>Eſa.</hi> 65. <hi>I will create new Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, and new Earth,</hi> with the like conſonant places, are meant of new-moulding the <hi>State;</hi>
                        <pb n="14" facs="tcp:115542:12"/>
both in Church and Common-wealth, under the Goſpel; when they ſhall be more remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably diſtinguiſhed: But theſe men labour for a monſtrous <hi>prothuſteron,</hi> that the Heavens ſhould be ruled by the Earth, the Higher go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned <note place="margin">Gen ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keerde weerld.</note> by the Lower; and the greater by the leſſer orbes. Let every Sphere enjoy its pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Intelligence.</p>
                     <p>Neither can I ſo readily aſſent to thoſe, who affirme, that <hi>two or three gathered together into a ſociety, riſe up to an Organicall Church:</hi> For that, <hi>Mat.</hi> 18. ſpeaking of ſuch a Church, preſuppoſeth more perſons: For <hi>if thy brother offend thee,</hi> there are two perſons; <hi>and after reproof will not hear thee, take one or two with thee,</hi> there are four perfons, and thoſe males, whereas experience daily teacheth the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, <hi>Acts</hi> 16. 13. beſides the Church: yet how ſmall the <hi>embryo</hi> of a particular Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation may be, is hard to depoſe defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively.</p>
                     <p>As in all ſenſitive bodies, theſe three facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties are required; to attract, to nouriſh, and to expell; the ſame may be ſaid of every Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregationall body: It muſt have power within it ſelf, to admit and receive in, to nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh and foſter thoſe received, and to expell or decline that which is noxious.</p>
                     <p>But the grand Quere will be, <hi>Whence this Power is derived?</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Doubt.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>They of the See of <hi>Rome</hi> lay claim of inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance to it, by ſucceſſion from Chriſt and <note place="margin">Exam.</note> his Apoſtles; and ſo exclude, as Hereticks,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:115542:12"/>
all thoſe that uſurpe the title of a true Church or Miniſtry, without ſucceſſion or ordination from them.</p>
                     <p>Others, even of our brethren, in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Churches, do deny this to belong to a <hi>Church,</hi> without ſome ſucceſſion or depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency on other Churches: Of whom I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſire the ſolution of theſe two Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Whether a company of godly people, being by</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Queſt. 1.</note> 
                        <hi>ſhipwrack caſt into the a barbarous or empty Iland, where they are like to live out their dayes, may not joyn into a ſpiritual body; and ſo raiſe up unto themſelves, the exerciſes of all Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces revealed in Gods word?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>If any one think, that, by ſtating the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <note place="margin">Sol.</note> out of the <hi>Church,</hi> it is a begging of the queſtion: he muſt have recourſe unto the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer diſtinction, that they are indeed diſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed parts of the <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſall Church:</hi> but not organized by union unto Eccleſiaſticall du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; A multitude but no people. <hi>Paul, when he aſſayed to joyn himſelf unto the Church of</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>Acts</hi> 9. 26. was, as a private man, no actuall member of any determinate Church: but, as an Apoſtle, vertually, of all, confined to no particular place; rather a Father then a Nurſe to moſt of the Churches of the Gentiles.</p>
                     <p>Leſt any ſhould deny this Demand, theſe things are tendred to their conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="16" facs="tcp:115542:13"/>
Whatſoever is Spiritually a living body, is Spiritually <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, perfecting it ſelf: An Axiom grounded upon Reaſon: <hi>Aristotle</hi> applyeth it to the Soul of Man: But all Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers are Spiritually living Bodies, and have an inward principle, <hi>to build up themſelves and others, in their holy faith.</hi> So 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5. they are commanded to <hi>edifie one another,</hi> and 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. the <hi>Faithful</hi> are called <hi>living ſtones.</hi> Now preſuppoſe, that a company of living ſtones, (it is lawful to diſpute upon a falſe <hi>Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potheſis)</hi> meet and joyn together, who will doubt, but they may, and ought, to rear up from themſelves a perfect Edifice? <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2. 21.</p>
                     <p>From this ground ariſe all Politick Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, Common-Weals, and Kingdoms: ſince a man, for his well-being, hath need of ſeveral things; and one alone is not laid in with all kind of Handicraft, or Art; for a mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual good, there is a coaleſcency: So in the <hi>Church,</hi> every one is nor an <hi>eye</hi> or <hi>hand;</hi> ſome muſt act the <hi>ear,</hi> others the <hi>foot.</hi> Semblable is that of <hi>Solomon,</hi> Eccleſ. 4. <hi>Wo to him that is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone; for if he fall who ſhall raiſe him up?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Again, I ask, <hi>In time of Reformation from</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Queſt. 2.</note> 
                        <hi>Idolatry or profaneneſs to an Orthodox Holineſs; Whether there be not the ſame neceſſity, which there was in the caſe ſtated before?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>How ſhall they be reduced, where there is <note place="margin">Exam.</note> no Church, will be the queſtion. The Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of the <hi>Diſciples,</hi> that were ſent out by <hi>Couples,</hi> will teach that: Theſe Hewers of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:115542:13"/>
Stone and Timber did, by converting many, fit and ſquare them for a Spiritual Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice.</p>
                     <p>If it be anſwered affirmatively, then they may unite together into a <hi>Church,</hi> without ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion or dependency on other Churches. If not, either they muſt procure ſome Superlti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous or profane Miniſter, to receive-in Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, to ordain Officers in a true <hi>Church,</hi> which is abſurd; or elſe they muſt ſtay, till they meet with another true <hi>Church,</hi> or Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry; which, beſides the difficulty, favoureth of a Prelatical Juriſdiction of one <hi>Church</hi> over another; of which, ſomething in the ſubſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Chapter; where the difference of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority and benefit of one <hi>Church</hi> towards another, is more copiouſly examined.</p>
                     <p>Some that meekly, yet earneſtly, contend againſt this way, object two main Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: The firſt is, <hi>It is unlawful to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw, or ſeparate from a true Church.</hi> The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond is, <hi>concerning readd Prayer:</hi> A word to each.</p>
                     <p>Firſt, Caſes might be ſtated, in which it is lawful to <hi>forſake a true Church;</hi> and ſo the Propoſition ſhaketh: But I deny the aſſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that there is, or hath been, ſince the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vorce of the <hi>Jews</hi> (their <hi>Church</hi> and State be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſame) any National Miniſterial <hi>Church,</hi> in which none might abide, alien from their Religion, as far as concerneth the Moral Law; <note place="margin">Proſelytus aut domu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, aut Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae.</note> though ſome were exempted from the Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monial Obedience: As were the <hi>Gideonites,</hi>
                        <pb n="18" facs="tcp:115542:14"/>
and <hi>Nethinims;</hi> and ſo it is the begging of the queſtion.</p>
                     <p>To the ſecond, I anſwer, That there is a great difference of <hi>reading of a Prayer,</hi> and committing Heads thereof to memory: [the caſe is the ſame in Preaching] the latter be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a means ſanctified, and a gift required in every Miniſter: The former, there being no Example, or Rule for it; nor any Paſtoral gift eminent in it.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>The Miniſters Prayer is a stinting of the Spirit, and ſo of my Prayer.</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Ob.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>The Miniſters Prayer is not my particular <note place="margin">Sol.</note> prayer, nor properly his, but the Churches; and he, therein, the mouth onely of the Church unto God: And if his Prayer be by the Spirit, [as it ought] mine, as a member, is no other; neither is mine more ſtinted then his. In Preaching, the caſe is inverted; for there he is the mouth of God unto the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. The Bleſſing is a mixt action: as he doth apprecate unto us God's favours, is his Vice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerent, Unto which <hi>Amen</hi> following, is the Peoples aſſent. No man properly can bleſs himſelf, but the <hi>leſſer is bleſſed of the greater, Heb.</hi> 7. 7.</p>
                     <p>To conclude this point, It ſeemeth more then probable, that a company of faithful, (the heart no man knoweth) uniting into a body, become a true Oeconomical <hi>Church,</hi> and, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving <hi>Christ</hi> for their ſole Head, may, with a pleniporent <hi>Octroy</hi> or Conceſſion, claim pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge to all the Ordinances inſtituted in the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:115542:14"/>
Goſpel, as by a Charter belonging to them; by virtue of their Pact and Covenant with the Lord their King; without any dependency upon any Forrein Authority, either Secular, or Eccleſiaſtical. The ſame caſe is of a <hi>Church</hi> releaſed from Babyloniſh Bondage; who, by Writ of Recovery, may challenge her Priſtine Inheritance.</p>
                     <p>I muſt clear up one Objection; <hi>There are</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Ob.</note> 
                        <hi>Hypocrites in the Church; and Christ communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated with</hi> Judas.</p>
                     <p>For Hypocrites, there is no Law againſt <note place="margin">Sol.</note> them: Not Divine, becauſe they are the worſt of Atheiſts; Nor Humane, becauſe they have the face or vizard of devout Penitents: The <hi>Church,</hi> therefore, taketh no cognizance of them: and what an encaſed or diſcovered Hypocrite is, I could never apprehend. <hi>Christ</hi> indeed, by His Theanthropy, ſearching the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, knew <hi>Judas</hi> to be one; but, becauſe he himſelf was beyond reach of Contagion, and <hi>Judas</hi>'s diſſimulation in ſecret, was not yet broken out into open profaneneſs, <hi>every one of the Diſciples queſtioning, Who ſhould be the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil their Maſter ſpake of, Chriſt</hi> did not refuſe him: which is the miſtake of many Learned men in our days; making his ſecure Example, a pattern of their perilous practiſe.</p>
                     <p>Appoſitely do others obſerve, that Chriſt would not be both Witneſs and Judge, which no Court of Equity doth admit of.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="20" facs="tcp:115542:15"/>
                     <head>CHAP. II.</head>
                     <argument>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Of Miniſters.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </argument>
                     <p>THere is a vulgar errour, even among the beſt, concerning the Name; which if they mean, as they ſpeak, is an open door unto Anarchy. They call their <hi>Pastors,</hi> as alſo their <hi>Magiſtrates,</hi> yea, <hi>Angels, Their, or, the Churches Miniſters,</hi> which is falſe; eſpecially, thoſe whom they furniſh with things neceſſary for this preſent life: Whereas it is grounded up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a triple Foundation. <hi>Natural, Thou ſhalt not muzzle the mouth of the Oxe, that treadeth out the corn: Levitical,</hi> By the Law of <hi>Deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation: Evangelical,</hi> 1 Cor. 9. <hi>If we have ſown unto you ſpiritual things, is it a great mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, if we reap your carnal things?</hi> Paying a Debt, doth induce no obligation. They are indeed <hi>God's Miniſters,</hi> and to they are ſtyled, 2 <hi>Cor. 6. 4. Rom. 13. 8. Pſal.</hi> 104. 4. not mans: That 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 5. is a ſtrain of holy courte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie.</p>
                     <p>Not to ſpeak here, of four things requiſite to the conſtitution of a Paſtor, 1. A faculty of adminiſtring the Sacraments and Keyes, which is called <hi>Mandate.</hi> II. The applying of this Mandat to a certain perſon, named <hi>Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Grotius.</note> 3. The adjoyning of the perſon to a certain company, and that is <hi>Election.</hi> 4. When the ſame exerciſeth his Miniſtry by publick
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:115542:15"/>
Authority, which is with them <hi>Confirmation:</hi> The diſcuſſing the truth whereof, would take up time, and ſwell the Bulk, beyond my inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Let the firſt queſtion be,</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Whether a Miniſter may celebrate the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Queſt.</note> 
                        <hi>out of his own Church?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>There may be conſidered in a Miniſter's <note place="margin">Exam.</note> Office two things; his <hi>Power</hi> over his own, and his <hi>Duty of Benefit</hi> towards others. Now no act of <hi>power</hi> can he exerciſe out of his Church; but any grace of <hi>benefit</hi> he may; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided always, that by feeding of others, his own be not pinched.</p>
                     <p>But, becauſe his <hi>duty of benefit</hi> doth extend to all, whether of the ſame Profeſſion, or not, that therefore his power ſhould do the like, is no neceſſary conſequence: This Key well turned, will unlock moſt of our Diſſenters Arguments: The Sacraments, therefore, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no act of power, ſeem to may be, by him, adminiſtred out of his own Church; theſe conſiderations being ballanced.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. <hi>The Levites,</hi> this way <hi>were tyed,</hi> though to a Nation; yet <hi>not to any particular Tribe, Jud.</hi> 17. 9.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. If he may not adminiſter the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments out of his own Church, then none up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a juſt abſence from their own, might either themſelves, or their children, be partakers of the Siſter-Churches Sacraments; which is againſt the practiſe of the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and now beſt Reformed Churches: The reaſon of the conſequence is this; If he admit a ſtranger,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:115542:16"/>
either, by that act, he becometh one of them, or no: If not, then he adminiſtreth to ſome out of his Church; and why not then unto moſt, or unto all? Who ſhall ſet a certain bound or number? If he become one of that Society, then may he be a member of two or more Churches at once: which though in Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Corporations, it may be admitted, is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiſting with Eccleſiaſtical Conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. <hi>Deacons might, and ought ſometime to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſter out of their own Church,</hi> 2 Corinth. 8.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. It would redound unto the greater comfort to the Neighbour-Churches, in their building up, and Spiritual Hoſpitality, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any fear of ataxy.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>The Adminiſtration of the Sacraments is an</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Object.</note> 
                        <hi>act of Power and Authority.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>I confeſs it is an act of Place or Office, not <note place="margin">Anſw.</note> common to every one: So was the <hi>carrying out of the Aſhes under the Altar,</hi> yet without any power; yea, all the Sacrifices, which went onely through the <hi>Levites</hi> hands, uſhered in no Authority with them: But if the giving of the Sacraments be an act of power, then, by the Rule of Relates, is the receiving of them an act of ſubjection: But none will ſay, that, by receiving the Sacrament, they become ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to that Church or Power, or have the priviledge of chuſing Officers, or a ſuffrage in cenſures.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="23" facs="tcp:115542:16"/>
                        <hi>The Mayor is not, to exerciſe any power of his</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Inſtance.</note> 
                        <hi>Office, neither ſet the City Seal, to any perſon or thing, out of his Juriſdiction.</hi> So <hi>neither,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                     <p>The Argumentation is from a Similitude, <note place="margin">Anſw. 1.</note> therefore not Apodictick, or of evident De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration.</p>
                     <p>He may give advice, yea, as a Deputy, be <note place="margin">2.</note> helpful out of his own Corporation, for ſome neighbour, or publick good.</p>
                     <p>The <hi>Simile</hi> differeth in the main; becauſe every Corporation hath its ſeveral Seal: But <note place="margin">3.</note> all the Churches throughout the World do make uſe of the ſame; which pleadeth, not weakly, for the queſtion in hand; and withall reſolveth, by a juſt Analogy, that Controverſie perplexing many; <hi>Whether Baptiſm be an obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation to a particular Church?</hi> Thoſe in <hi>Jor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dan</hi> were not Baptized into an individual So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety, <hi>Math.</hi> 3. Neither the <hi>Goaler, Act.</hi> 16. Nor the <hi>Eunuch, Act.</hi> 8. I know it was the Office of Apoſtle-ſhip, to continue till Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches were eſtabliſhed; but that doth not enervate altogether our Argument. Neither doth it preſently follow, that Sacraments may be adminiſtred out of the Church, either by wandring Itineraries, or fixed Fathers of Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies to their Houſhold; which controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie being handled by others, I paſs over.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Whether if a Popiſh Priest, reforming unto</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Queſt. 2.</note> 
                        <hi>Proteſtantiſm; by vertue of his former Order, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main a Miniſter in a Reformed Church?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="24" facs="tcp:115542:17"/>
The Negative is moſt likely, theſe Reaſons conſidered: <note place="margin">Anſw.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>He muſt be choſen from among the Godly;</hi> yea, <hi>among his own Flock.</hi> Now <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, <note place="margin">1.</note> [after the conveighing of gifts by Miracles, which like the <hi>Therapeutick Chriſm,</hi> died with, or ſoon after the Apoſtles] is but the <note place="margin">Denomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio viſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis.</note> demonſtration or confirmation of his choice; the word being attributed to <hi>God</hi> Himſelf <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, <hi>Act.</hi> 10. 4. This hath been proved by others <note n="*" place="margin">Grotiusde <hi>Imp: circa ſacra, Lib. 10.</hi> Selden <hi>de Synod. Lib. 1. Cap. 14.</hi>
                        </note>, See <hi>Num.</hi> 8. 9. The Impoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Names in Baptiſm is of the like nature, without which, ſome think that lavacre defe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive; but unadviſedly: It is not probable, that <hi>John</hi> did ſuperadde any new names to his Diſciples: neither was there an impoſition of names, in the long differred Circumciſion, <hi>Joſ.</hi> 5. Of old, all Women ſhould have been nameleſs; Perſonal forgotten; Patricious, if married, ſwallowed. Neither did conferring of gifts accompany always the laying on of Apoſtolical hands, <hi>Act.</hi> 6. 6. for, <hi>they were full of the Holy Ghoſt before,</hi> ver. 3. Sometime this Ceremony was repeated; as may be demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated, by comparing <hi>Act.</hi> 9. 17. with <hi>Act.</hi> 13. 3.</p>
                     <p>He ſhall have an Office of Paſtorſhip before <note place="margin">2.</note> he have a Flock, whereas the nature of <hi>Relates</hi> is, to live and die together: nay, perhaps before he be a member of a true Oeconomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Church, which is difficult to imagine.</p>
                     <p>Concerning the difference of reteining Baptiſm, and not Ordination, I remit you to
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:115542:17"/>
the ſatisfactory Treatiſes, of our worthy Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſours.</p>
                     <p>Other things might be added, and doubts cleared; but becauſe I ſtudy brevity, and am loath to plume my ſelf with other birds fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, or to ſurfet my Reader with twice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warmed cabbadge, I proceed to another con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverted ſubject.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. III.</head>
                     <argument>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Of Sacraments.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </argument>
                     <p>SAcraments are ſo near allyed unto Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, that they might well have lodged under one roof; but, for breathing ſake they are ſevered.</p>
                     <p>Sacraments are viſible words, differing from the audible, in that the latter ſerveth not only for food, but alſo for ſeed; the former only for nouriſhment: To tender nutri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to not yet generated, is prepoſterous. But to the Problems.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Whether Baptiſm received unworthily, that is,</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Queſt. 1.</note> 
                        <hi>either on the exhibents or receivers part, ſo it be done to a religious uſe, the element and word al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies concurring, may be reiterated?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>It being on Gods part a <hi>Seal of a</hi> federal <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant,</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Exam.</note> 
                        <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. 11. [not of a civil one, as many urge; except juſtifying faith be recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned among civil affairs] It is truth-like, that
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:115542:18"/>
once adminiſtred, I afterward by faith apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſign to my ſelf, may have fruit and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit thereby.</p>
                     <p>Though in order the Covenant be before the Seal annexed; yet God, in mercy, doth of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten vary that courſe, which man may not, till he have proved the Sacraments to be a ſeed of faith: But he finding his Seal truly ſet to a blanck, though unworthily, doth, of grace, ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuperſcribe his Covenant to it; though not for it. God alwaies knowing and owing his <hi>veſſels,</hi> though in Uſurpers hands: which <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhazar abuſing, did wofully rue, Dan.</hi> 5.</p>
                     <p>So if at any times [alas too often] we ſin, by rumination on the foregoing ſigns, we may draw freſh ſolace; without reiteration of the element. We have, for example, ſeveral of our <hi>Saviour's Diſciples,</hi> recollecting the words after his death; which, in his life time, they had negligently, either overflipt or overſlepr. The Spirit ecchoing over former either Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts or Promiſes: Which practically apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, might turn to the great ſupport of thoſe who have miſspent many ordinances fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe: ſo alſo in the Lords ſupper; the ſtrength and <hi>ſignatum</hi> thereof, may, upon neceſſity, be oftner extracted by meditation and applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, then it is elementally exhibited.</p>
                     <p>This, for fear of miſtake, I write, ſomewhat to inform the diſſenting Chriſtians, for rebap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizing themſelves: What if they be baptized under the hood of hypocriſie being unmasked ſhall they renew their mark? As alſo, for
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:115542:18"/>
the reforming of thoſe, who, without the Lords Supper in their death-bed, [a <hi>viaticum</hi> in their journey] cannot die quietly: bread and wine denying nouriſhment; which is next to communicating without elements.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Whether is the immerſion of the whole body ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary?</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Queſt. 2.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>Where an opportunity is, and no danger to <note place="margin">Exam.</note> the party by cold, I ſhould think it fitting: But in ſeverer weather or region, as it was with the <hi>Jaylor in the night,</hi> here taketh place that compaſſionate rule, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 6. <hi>I had rather have mercy then ſacrifice:</hi> And I ſee not but the hand, or other convenient part, might ſtand ſynecdochically for the whole; becauſe by its immerſion, and emerſion, is better ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified the <hi>burying and reſurrection of Chriſt,</hi> as indeed it ought: See <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. 4. <hi>Col.</hi> 2. 12. which in the front-aſperſion is more obſcure.</p>
                     <p>They who preferre this part, in regard of religious ſignification, before any other, are, at leaſt, within the confines and ſuburbs of ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition.</p>
                     <p>In the Lords Supper, the elements muſt ſomewhat be regulated in quantity, according unto the meaſure of the appetite: a morſel will ſuffice a weaker ſtomack; when to the ſtronger a more liberal draught is agreeable: although ſpirituall nouriſhment dependeth not upon the proportion of the ſign, but of faith.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="28" facs="tcp:115542:19"/>
                     <head>CHAP. IIII.</head>
                     <argument>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Of</hi> Adam.</p>
                     </argument>
                     <p>I Am not purpoſed to digeſt this Treatiſe into common-places; but rather trace polemick and eriſtick diſcourſe, and that in unbeaten paths.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>How was</hi> Adam <hi>made after God's Image,</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Queſt. 1.</note> 
                        <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. 26.</p>
                     <p>Every <hi>ens,</hi> in oppoſition to privation, is an <note place="margin">Sol.</note> image of the Deity: every living thing is an expreſſion of his life: Old age is a print of his eternity: Strength, riches, beauty, ſculptures of his excellency: yea, every thing [ſin and its fruit excepted] is an impreſs of its Creator: But it could not be as he was living; [for now there was a new thing a working] for ſo were other Creatures before him: Neither becauſe of his righteouſneſs, or immortality <hi>à posterio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re;</hi> nor as the three faculties of the ſoul Intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect, Memory, and Will, reſembling the Trinity; for ſo were the Angels.</p>
                     <p>I rather think it was, to <hi>rule</hi> and <hi>govern,</hi> as Gods deputy, all the Creatures below: which Imperial power was wanting to the Creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. This expoſition ſeemeth moſt genuine, as having <hi>Moſes</hi> in the ſame verſe, <hi>totident verbis,</hi> for an Expoſitor.</p>
                     <p>That the <hi>Image of God</hi> is expreſt in ſuperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ority, is further manifeſt from 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. where
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:115542:19"/>
the <hi>man,</hi> in an <hi>antitheſis</hi> to the woman, is ſaid <hi>to be the Image of God:</hi> If it had been in righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, their portion was equilibrous, both in a compleat degree.</p>
                     <p>The difference is alſo not to be neglected, between <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, the image of ſuperiority, and <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, the ſimilitude of qualities; though I read them confounded; <hi>Col.</hi> 3. 10.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Gen.</hi> 3. 6. <hi>We may eat:</hi> Ergo, <hi>the woman, as</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Object.</note> 
                        <hi>being coloeir by joynt-iſſue, had power.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>All is hers for participation and uſe, not for <note place="margin">Anſw.</note> diſpoſing: a prime token of the latter hath of old been a power of denomination. Thus <hi>Adam</hi> nominated his wife and the creatures: <hi>Joſeph</hi> and <hi>Daniel,</hi> being captives, had their names changed, by their conquerours or ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners: All the tenure the woman had, was <hi>in capite.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Note here two things by the way. Firſt, that <hi>meum</hi> and <hi>tuum,</hi> as they were natural relatives, were before the Creation: Before time was, was the Son the Fathers Image; but Poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſives came in ſince. Priority and cauſality is from eternity, and from thence being derived, may not be given away: I may paſſe away my right among my equals; not to my inferiors: becauſe it is the <hi>Image of God:</hi> Ergo, <hi>Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, Parents, Firſt-born</hi> may not reſign their power, becauſe it is Gods inheritance: And this was the ſin of <hi>Eſau.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Secondly, That there was no ſubjection, <hi>i. e. ejuſdem ſpeciei,</hi> before ſin; no not among the Angels: What the Scripture holdeth forth of
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:115542:20"/>
an <hi>Arch-Angel,</hi> a <hi>Michael, &amp;c.</hi> doth very fitly ſuit with the Angel of <hi>the Covenant, Christ.</hi> Where there is no fear of enormity, there may be a ſecure ſeriation of ſupremacy. In <hi>Adam,</hi> yet intire, there was a priority and a preſtancy, but no ſoveraignty; for that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came afterward a part of the womans curſe; ſhe being the firſt in the tranſgreſſion: If the leader fall into the pit, he beareth his own, and the followers burden.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Whether matter of propagation were concrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Queſt. 2.</note> 
                        <hi>with</hi> Adam?</p>
                     <p>Upon this queſtion affirmed, ſeemeth to <note place="margin">Exam.</note> depend <hi>Cain's</hi> exemption from Original ſin: For every thing in innocency, executing, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out let, the grand <hi>Fiat</hi> of his Maker, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing being unfruitful; it ſhould ſeem, that <hi>Cain</hi> was priviledged from that contagion; or elſe, that it is contracted by imitation, which ſome defend.</p>
                     <p>Beſides, why ſhould not Man, maſter of multiplying creatures, enjoy the materiall principle of Generation, at his Creation; ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing inferiour ſervants were entruſted with ſo noble a treaſure, every thing being created in his fulleſt eſtate? For the forbidden fruit, with the reſt, [and therefore the kernel] was certainly ripe: elſe neither would it have been ſo lovely, nor deſirable to eat: eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by thoſe, who, before the fall, could ſee fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then paring deep.</p>
                     <p>Not only the plaſtick vertue, but matter, though in <hi>potentia remota,</hi> was, as with all
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:115542:20"/>
creatures ſo connate with <hi>Adam:</hi> his whole poſterity elſe had been defective in one rib.</p>
                     <p>Yet the contrary opinion hath its weight. <hi>Creſcite et multiplicate</hi> was the firſt bleſſing that God delivered to our Primogenitours. Now the latter in nature being impoſſible without the former, [for propagation before adoleſcency, according to the Decrees of Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy, is imperfect] the former was not to be obtained without eating; yea, the extrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſt digeſtion: It being, as Phyſicians teach, the excrement of the laſt concoction.</p>
                     <p>To the queſtion then I anſwer, That the firſt conception is not properly man, nor the ſubject of ſin; but a plant, in order unto man; whoſe conception is at the quickning: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto witneſſeth the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>Moſes Exod.</hi> 21. If it be expounded as do the <hi>Septuagint:</hi> and, <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>.</note> that innocency continued ſo long, is not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable.</p>
                     <p>As is the Seed, ſo is the Field, a <hi>Plant-ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal,</hi> or rather an inmate, and, <hi>[mirandum]</hi> as that which is ſown doth increaſe, ſo doth the field extend, not only in circumference, but alſo in thickneſs; For better diſtinction, let me inſert a ſhort <hi>Synopſis</hi> of excretions.</p>
                     <list>
                        <pb n="32" facs="tcp:115542:21"/>
                        <item>
                           <label>Of excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions ſome are</label>
                           <list>
                              <item>Mere &amp; pure as
<list>
                                    <item>Ordure,</item>
                                    <item>Sweat,
<list>
                                          <item>and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come by a new
<list>
                                                <item>Putre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction
<list>
                                                      <item>Worms,</item>
                                                      <item>Lice.</item>
                                                   </list>
                                                </item>
                                                <item>Petrification, Stone</item>
                                             </list>
                                          </item>
                                       </list>
                                    </item>
                                 </list>
                              </item>
                              <item>Urine,</item>
                              <item>Mixt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>their end for
<list>
                                    <item>Lubrification, as phleghm in ſeveral parts of the body.</item>
                                    <item>Covering, or Ornament, as hair, nails, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>Excluſion or irritation, as
<list>
                                          <item>Choller,</item>
                                          <item>Melancholy</item>
                                       </list>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>Part of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and either
<list>
                                          <item>Artificial, as Veneſection.</item>
                                          <item>Critical, ſeveral waies.</item>
                                          <item>Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for
<list>
                                                <item>Generation, as ſeed in both ſexes.</item>
                                                <item>Preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<list>
                                                      <item>within, <hi>Menſes.</hi>
                                                      </item>
                                                      <item>without, Milk.</item>
                                                   </list>
                                                </item>
                                             </list>
                                          </item>
                                       </list>
                                    </item>
                                 </list>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="33" facs="tcp:115542:21"/>
Of the firſt ſort, I think, none were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>created; the reſt, ſave <hi>Phlebotomy,</hi> and <hi>Criſes,</hi> were coexiſting with their firſt Being; or, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the leaſt Wink of Opportunity, preſt to be drawn forth. Sweat, and Thiſtles, came in Twins into the World together.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. V.</head>
                     <argument>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Of Marriage.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </argument>
                     <p>A <hi>Dam</hi> had the liberty of all Trees, but one; A man is forbidden all Women, but one: both, for preſervation of Mankind. If in Food, he had been confined to one ſtanding diſh, it might have bred a nauſeouſneſs: If man were not limited within the Bounds of one Woman, his exhauſted Spirits would pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce but a weak Progeny. <hi>Marriage,</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, doth not owe Homage of its being, ſole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the Civil Law; there is ſome Ingredient of Nature in it. Among ſeveral Birds, one may read a conjugal love, and ſee Foot-ſteps of a Nuptial-Bed, which maketh them <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>. In the <hi>Ark,</hi> the Nurſery of the future World, there was an undoubted Teſtimony of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bination: and what if I ſhould fetch it as farre as the Creation? But in Mankind, I ſhall enquire into two Queſtions.</p>
                     <pb n="34" facs="tcp:115542:22"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>By whom the Parties are to be joyned?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Marriage</hi> is the firſt Foundation of a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, <note place="margin">Queſt. 1. Sol. <hi>Mr.</hi> Hobs</note> out of a principle of love; not of mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all fear, as ſome, too narrowly, derive all Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties from: For the end of the firſt Society, is rather the preſervation of the Univerſe, then a defence of ſome Individuals; and therefore no pact equipollent to the Conjugal contract: the perpetuation of the Creation is a more noble end, than the continuation of others, or himſelf: ſo that if man were alone, as was <hi>Adam,</hi> the firſt companion he could in Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom wiſh, would be a Woman.</p>
                     <p>Out of the conjunction of Families, ariſing a Political Body, which being common to the whole Earth, Matrimony, its ground, may ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be rancked under a <hi>Civil,</hi> than any <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious,</hi> or <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> Conſtitution: the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration whereof, we never read in <hi>Holy Scripture,</hi> was done by any in <hi>Priestly</hi> Office; but by <hi>Judges,</hi> and that in places of Civil Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicature. That Duty did, of old, belong to the <hi>Father of the Family,</hi> by the Example of <hi>Laban, Gen. 29. 19 quoting their Municipall Statutes,</hi> ver. 26. Neither is there any Precept or Precedent, directly, or analogically, either in the Old or New Teſtament, tying it to the Office of a <hi>Prieſt,</hi> or <hi>Miniſter:</hi> yea, the <hi>Jewes</hi> would not ſuffer it to be celebrated on a Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath, or Feſtival Day.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="35" facs="tcp:115542:22"/>
It might be queſtioned, <hi>whether marriage were inſtituted in innocency;</hi> ſeeing the end of marriage is to flee fornication, which they were uncapable of. Propagation is the proper end of the conjunction of male and female, which is naturall; and to make a naturall end of a civill cauſe, ſeemeth to me diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult.</p>
                     <p>But thoſe that would make an <hi>Evangelicall Sacrament</hi> of it, or a <hi>Sacramentall ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> at leaſt, and yet to be <hi>inſtituted in para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe,</hi> ſhoot wider: becauſe, as there was no need, ſo there was no thought of <hi>Chriſt.</hi> That which the modern have borrowed from the Ancient <hi>Fathers,</hi> as they ſtyle them, that <hi>the tree of life was a Sacrament before the Fall;</hi> muſt not be taken in a ſtrict, but Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phorical ſenſe.</p>
                     <p>Further, as far as my proſpective of enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry could reach, among the Heathen, out of a principle, of nature, [not corrupted by per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted reaſon; for then <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, they <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come ſottiſh,</hi> Rom. 11. 2. but regulated by its own light, <hi>they do by nature, thoſe things con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the Law]</hi> the King joyneth them to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and not the Prieſt, where the offices are diſtinct. The <hi>confarreation,</hi> where the <hi>High-Prieſt</hi> and <hi>Flamen</hi> were preſident, was, becauſe of its incongruity, but-ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lived.</p>
                     <p>Mal. 2. 14. <hi>A wife of thy Covenant, where the Lord hath been witneſſe.</hi> Ergo, <hi>the Covenant is religious.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="36" facs="tcp:115542:23"/>
Diſtinction muſt be made between an act, and the confirmation of it: The one may be civil, the other religious. Abraham's <hi>ſending his ſervant,</hi> Gen. 24. <hi>for a wife to his Son,</hi> was no ſpirituall tranſaction, though obſigned with a Religious Oath: Nor can the bargain between <hi>Ioſhua</hi> and the <hi>Gibeonites,</hi> though ſtrengthened by an Oath, be marſhalled in the band of ſacred proceedings; <hi>Pauls ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies did bind their unwarrantable determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, with a ſolemn curſe,</hi> Act. 23.</p>
                     <p>Prayers for a bleſſing on matrimony, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth it no more a ſpiritual thing; then appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation to peace, warre, bodily labour, make them holy and of a religious na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Whether Inceſt be a ſin againſt the morall Law?</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Queſt. 1.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>Matrimony among conſanguinity, doth <note place="margin">Exam.</note> hinder the extenſion of affinity and ſociety: which man, being a ſociable Creature, is bound to enlarge: But, as we take inceſt, <hi>a pollution of them, that are allyed by birth,</hi> it ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth doubtfull; except it be between <hi>Parents</hi> and <hi>Children; Uncle</hi> and <hi>Neece; Grand-father</hi> and <hi>Grand-childe,</hi> in which are the footſteps of deſcent; but we ſpeak of <hi>Homotimous</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, level in the ſame degree of honour; where a former tye of reverence doth not prevent it, by the Law of Nature. Firſt, God would never have put ſuch a Law in the heart of <hi>Adam,</hi> the executing whereof in the two ſucceding generations, He was neceſſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:115542:23"/>
to diſpenſe withall: For <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Abel</hi> were Husbands to their <hi>Siſters,</hi> [though not to their twins, according to the <hi>Rabbins]</hi> and, among their Children, marriage was recipro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call; there being no naturall obligation or tye, of reverence, before; except God had created another ſtock, which is more likely, then to bring them to that indigency, and that without their own delinquency, that, without this ſin, the whole <hi>ſpecies</hi> of mankind muſt have periſhed.</p>
                     <p>Further, it did conſiſt neither with the wiſdome nor juſtice of God, to command any thing in the <hi>Judicial</hi> or <hi>Ceremonial law</hi> of the <hi>Jews,</hi> that ſhould be diametrically counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded in the <hi>Moral Law:</hi> But, <hi>not to take his Brothers wife, after his deceaſe, was ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time puniſhed with death: alwayes with publick ſhame, by pulling off the ſhoe, and ſpitting in the face;</hi> Deut. 25. 9. or rather in his preſence; for ſo <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> is generally elſe where expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; and afterward the ſame phraſe did de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend into a Greciſme, <hi>Luke</hi> 9. 52. Yea this law may be fetched from before <hi>Moſes</hi> time, <hi>Gen.</hi> 38.</p>
                     <p>That Theft had a remiſſer puniſhment among the <hi>Jews,</hi> was, becauſe they enjoyed a kind of community, both in Religion and Politicks: That Adultery had ſo ſevere a pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment annexed unto it, was to keep their tribes unmixed, to verifie the <hi>ſtremme of Christ:</hi> Semblable to which was the <hi>examen of pucellage,</hi> the <hi>waters of jealouſly,</hi> &amp;c. very
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:115542:24"/>
ſtrict; and, to the ſame end, munici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall.</p>
                     <p>Levit. 18. 24. <hi>For in all theſe the Nations</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Obj.</note> 
                        <hi>were defiled, that I caſt out before you.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Theſe Nations had, beſides <hi>Noah's precepts,</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Sol.</note> the law of nature, which prohibiteth a conju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall familiarity, where there is a naturall ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation to ſuperiority; as ſeverall of the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going precepts do forbid. It may alſo have a reſpect unto the three immediate prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding verſes, where ſins are mentioned worſe then beſtiall.</p>
                     <p>Leſt any hereby ſhould be encouraged unto <note place="margin">He that diggeth a pit muſt cover it</note> licentiouſneſſe, I adde; Where conjunction of conſanguinity, and how farre it is for bidden, by the <hi>ſupreme ſeigniory,</hi> there the commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of it, is formally, as well as materially, againſt the Morall Law; both againſt the <hi>fifth</hi> and <hi>ſeventh Commandement:</hi> Though, in a ſtrict ſenſe, ſin hath no matter, being void of entity, but <hi>modus entis,</hi> an obliquity from the right line: But not finding a word more ſuitable to it's object, I begge it a paſſe.</p>
                     <p>Beſides, that the <hi>Soveraign Authority</hi> may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large contract, or alter theſe bounds, &amp; their puniſhments, according to variety of occur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences, I ſec no enormity in it; Since the deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, and ſo the alteration of whatſoever is <hi>meum</hi> and <hi>tuum,</hi> reſteth in the breaſt of the <hi>Legiſ-lative Power,</hi> whether <hi>Perſon</hi> or <hi>Senate.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>That the paternall relation is civil, I do incline to believe, till the markes of the iſſue of blinde born women do envince the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:115542:24"/>
contrary: yet if gratitude be within the tables of reaſon, the obligation is moral.</p>
                     <p>Theſe, and the like truths, are to be pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered by thoſe, who would make the <hi>Laws</hi> of this Land run parallel with the <hi>Judiciall</hi> of the <hi>Jews.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. VI.</head>
                     <argument>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Of Sympathy.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </argument>
                     <p>
                        <hi>SYmpathy</hi> is a hidden love; Love a deſire of Union: but, being ſcanted in words, we take the effect for the affect.</p>
                     <p>To referre moſt of the ſtrange events to <hi>Sympathy,</hi> without ſtudying of the cauſes, is a mark of ſupine oſcitancy. The <hi>Lawyers,</hi> when they are at a ſtand, take their refuge to a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall caſe, or verdict: The <hi>Divines</hi> to a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular warrant: The <hi>Philoſophers</hi> to the hidden quality. But rational men, upon narrower ſcrutiny, will often finde out a manifeſt rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, which former predeceſſours, or preſent yonger-heads take for an occult cauſe: and herein conſiſteth not the ſmalleſt part of an induſtrious minde.</p>
                     <p>There is an error on both hands; either, when every new-diſcovered truth, is laid upon the aſſes pack-ſaddle the occult <hi>Syneraſy;</hi> or, when impertinent and ridiculous reaſons are derived from the Elements to produce an effect, tranſcending their nature. For theſe
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:115542:25"/>
properties are a myſtery to modeſt mindes; and to the curious, an impoſture. The mean is the ſafeſt.</p>
                     <p>So in <hi>Scripture,</hi> an allowable reaſon may be given excuſing <hi>Abraham</hi> from <hi>Pilicide;</hi> The <hi>Egyptian Jews</hi> from <hi>theft,</hi> and <hi>Sampſon</hi> from <hi>Suicide;</hi> the two latter whereof, here be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, are vindicated from crime, and prove acquitted.</p>
                     <p>If there be an hoſtile exerciſe between two Creatures, for the conſervation either of its <hi>ſpecies,</hi> or individual, <hi>i. e.</hi> for propagation, as between <hi>Cocks;</hi> or lively-hood, as <hi>Kite</hi> and <hi>Chicken;</hi> the laſt whereof is more dura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, the former more violent: [in the latter kinde, to ſpeak juſtly, there is no hatred; but a love unto, and a neceſſity of its own preſervation: Rats, though friends at their ſetting out; put into a great viall, a ſpectacle worthy of a <hi>ſecond Nero,</hi> will make a banck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet one of another; yea to kill a home-bred beaſt, to furniſh a diſh, will cauſe a <hi>regret.]</hi> This latter I can hardly call an <hi>Antipathy,</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept I involve man into an Antipathy with almoſt the whole nether-world, whoſe beaſts, fouls, fiſhes, he doth deſtroy, and they him again: yea the ſame <hi>ſpecies,</hi> as ſo many <hi>Cad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mean teeth,</hi> will ſtand in Antipathy to its own kind. But to ſurvey two untoucht exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>That a man helpeth a woman to breed;</hi> that <note place="margin">Doubt. 1.</note> is, is ſick in the time of her geſtation, is a currant opinion with many; and among our
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:115542:25"/>
                        <hi>Commeres</hi> applauded, as an infallible token of kindneſſe.</p>
                     <p>That ſickneſſe, unto both, at the ſame time, <note place="margin">Exam.</note> may often concurre, caſually, though not cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſally, I confeſſe. But that an excretion, or part of man, being ſeparated, ſhould affect, at a diſtance its former remainder, cannot to me be made out, either by digitall experience, or ſolid reaſon: though much of late hath been written, both learnedly and largely, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning ſuch ſubjects.</p>
                     <p>But touching this point: That the reten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Lunary evacuations, may, [as it doth the woman] by a diaphoreticall way, cloud and ſtaine the ſpirits of an accompany<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing man, which ſoon will produce a <hi>dyſcraſy</hi> in natural actions, I can, without difficulty, conceive. As alſo, that a ſtrict continence [which ſome other-wiſe, after their wives known impregnation, do ſcrupulouſly and unadviſedly vow to themſelvs] where uſe hath met with fit temperature to the contrary, may often ſenſibly annoy the male, our daily experience teacheth.</p>
                     <p>Some indeed, are like the <hi>Hebrew women,</hi> who can paſſe it over with a groan or two; which the Husband tender and puſillanimous hearing, falleth into pangs of fears and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triſtation: But, that this ſhould be an abate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the wife, were, to <hi>invert the curſe layd upon the woman;</hi> as my unmatched fellow-Practitioner ſheweth in another caſe of the <hi>Viper.</hi> But if it were true, it would, with the <note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Browni</hi>
                        </note>
                        <pb n="42" facs="tcp:115542:26"/>
ſpurious Father, of the doubtfull iſſue, bewray the diſloyalty of ſuſpected women.</p>
                     <p>There are Writers that ſpeak concerning <note place="margin">Doubt. 2.</note> 
                        <hi>Sympathy of a woman newly engravidated and a Bear: and, for experimtnt, remitt us into</hi> England; which yet I could never ſee, nor fully be ſatisfied in.</p>
                     <p>But upon ſuppoſition of its truth, it is <note place="margin">Exam.</note> worth the inquiry, whether it be out of luſt towards the woman, through ſalaciouſneſſe; which would produce a ſtrange <hi>Paradox.</hi> A Serpentine malice in the Beare, to ſuperaddde ſuch an inmate unto the fruit, deſpoiling it of its allotted aliment: Or, whether by a cruel and immature mid-wiving of the <hi>embryon,</hi> to ſatiate the immenſity of its hunger, which would betray a dainty tooth in the Beares head.</p>
                     <p>Howſoever, if it were certainly true, one might, without danger, uſe it in diſcovery of impregnation; and, by that meanes, often ſave the lives of two at once.</p>
                     <p>It is the moſt provident husbandry of man, to turn the ſtream of impetuous enormities, in brute Beaſts, into the Channell of humane accommodation.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="43" facs="tcp:115542:26"/>
                     <head>CHAP. VII.</head>
                     <argument>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Of an Egge.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </argument>
                     <p>SEveral Creatures continue the Linage of their Deſcent, by Eggs; as <hi>Fowls, Fiſhes, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſects.</hi> The <hi>Tortoiſe</hi> I take for a mixt kind of the two latter: But here I ſpeak of our ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Eggs; which, if not addle, are in <hi>proximâ potentiâ,</hi> but once removed from fleſh; and being eaten, become the lighteſt, pureſt, and fulleſt nutriment, and ſooneſt converted into our ſubſtance, becauſe we ſee a moderate heat, either Natural, or Artificial, will produce In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnation.</p>
                     <p>Now though the yoalk ſeemeth the nobler part, according unto Analogie of other natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Situations; for it is ſeated in the inner-Room and Abditory, for its defence envello<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped with the white, which rather were in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to the food of man, <hi>(Adam,</hi> in Innocency, eating Milk and Eggs; becauſe all things were exempted from Death, and nothing fruſtrane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous) than for propagation: Seeing a Hen, without the inition of a Cock, will not leſſen her daily task, and that almoſt the whole year through: For even yet, (Sin having impaired Fertility) more Eggs are excluded, than the Hen, (yea, adde the Cock into the bargain, for in coupled Fowls that is not unuſual) is able to ſet: yet that the tread of the Cock cannot
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:115542:27"/>
reach the yoalk; but that the White is nouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed by it, as having its <hi>Menſtruum</hi> within it ſelf, is both wonderful, and by daily <hi>Autopſie</hi> uncontrolable.</p>
                     <p>But here layeth the knot, which is not ſo <note place="margin">Doubt.</note> eaſily diſſolved. <hi>By what Veſſels the nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is attracted, and where they are inſert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>I know, after two or three days incubation, <note place="margin">Exam.</note> that there is a Sanguine-like ſtring, from the treading or Cock-ſperm; but that that ſhould be the <hi>Umbilicality</hi> of the Chicken, is not by ſight demonſtrable; neither is there any Mark, or leaſt <hi>Vestigium</hi> thereof remaining, in a new-hatched deplumed Chicken. Neither is it like, it ſhould be inſerted at the Bill; for then the Bill, as the deferring Organ, ſhould be formed firſt: Nor doth any perfect creature attract nouriſhment mouth-wiſe, before its eruption into the World: though <hi>Hippocrates</hi> 
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, be very plain for it; affirming, <hi>That both Breath and Nutriment within the Wombe, are ſuckt in by the Lips:</hi> but this place is ſuſpected to be ſpurious.</p>
                     <p>And if aliment ſhould be conveyed by the vent, beſides the prepoſterouſneſs in Nature, the Entrals muſt ſuffer a great perturbation, before the turning of the wonred periſtaltick motion: then is there likewiſe no place aſſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to the Exrements: or, to ſpeak <hi>ad amuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſim,</hi> rather remainders of the thickeſt and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pureſt blood, then the ſuperfluous dregs of the firſt concoction.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="45" facs="tcp:115542:27"/>
Or if by a <hi>Diaphoreſis,</hi> or Tranſpiration; it would encourage us, to adminiſter ſuch Ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments topically, as might afford ſolid nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and ſo become the eaſieſt and ſafeſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy, in many deplorable Diſeaſes.</p>
                     <p>At laſt, upon ſecond review, (neither is it a ſhame to recant an errour) I found the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel with ſome part of the yoalk, adhering to the belly.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="8" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. VIII.</head>
                     <argument>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Of Swimming.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </argument>
                     <p>HEre give me leave to write an ocular Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periment of mine own.</p>
                     <p>Being in the <hi>Canicular dayes,</hi> with ſome friends, about Noon-tide, in a high Chamber, at <hi>Catwick up Zee,</hi> near to the <hi>Arx-Britannica,</hi> (founded, as ſome ſay, by <hi>Julius Caeſar)</hi> we eſpy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a young man going to bathe himſelf in the main; and falling into a hole, which a ſhip, newly lanched, by the in-coming Flood, had made, being unexpert in ſwimming, was drowned. Two or three hours after, we alſo run down into Sea, and found this imprudent man floating, the <hi>Nucha,</hi> with the hair of his Neck, was all we could diſcern; we brought him to ſhore, but without either hope or trial of recovery.</p>
                     <p>That this ſuddain <hi>Fluctuation</hi> doth not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fall all men, is certain. But upon this Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:115542:28"/>
the truth whereof, I hope, is beyond the reach of ſuſpition, a more ſedulous encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement may be taken, for the enquiring of the cauſes, which are ſomewhat abſtruſe.</p>
                     <p>In Man there be divers parts to be exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, in relation to gravity of Water: There are <hi>Bones, Fleſh, Brain, Liver,</hi> and other <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trails</hi> heavier; ſome of which, the Water, if fully impregnated with Salt, ſhall contend with for Victory in weight. There are the <hi>Lungs</hi> and <hi>Fat</hi> lighter, beſides many concavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, where, upon <hi>Anatomy,</hi> we can ſee no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but the empty Cells of the newly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved Spirits.</p>
                     <p>Now the body of man, as in its ſeveral parts, it differeth in gravity; ſo doth alſo one body, in its <hi>totum,</hi> from another: that in ſome, there need but a ſmall moment to make them equilibrous with the Water.</p>
                     <p>Some ridiculouſly aſcribe it to <hi>the breaking of the Gall,</hi> which, as in reality, ſo in reaſon, is falſe. The bilious veſicle remaineth intire and full: Choller, though it produce an inca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſcency in the Spirits, and by it an agility in the members; yet doth it afford no levity to the body. I doubt not, though I never tryed it, but <hi>icteritions</hi> bodies, which they give out to proceed from the Gall, being ſuffocated, will ſink.</p>
                     <p>The ſupine reſting on Water, without mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, onely by retention of Air within the Spungie Lungs, doth digitate a reaſon.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="47" facs="tcp:115542:28"/>
A culinary Experiment hath in ſome part given me ſatisfaction: the boyling of Lights in a Pot, it is worth our obſervation to ſee, what a weight it will bear up. So, if there can be conceived, (as I know nothing to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary) an allien heat, which the Lungs may ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, either while all the warmth, at the point of death, doth retreat to the Heart; or its heat, (the refrigerating motion of the Lungs ceaſing) is derived into their cavernous Veſſels, and ſo rarifie the contained Air; the reaſon may, without difficulty, be conjectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</p>
                     <p>Finally beſides that the Sea, by all probabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, is ſalter, and ſo more apt to bear up any body, at the flowing, then at the ebbe; becauſe every Ebbe the River-Waters do more freely intermixe themſelves with the ſaltneſs of the Sea; and the middle <hi>Ocean,</hi> becauſe of its gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity moveth ſloweſt; I ſpeak in relation to this individual inſtance; ſome mens bodies, ſometimes of the year, are proner to a ſuddai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner put refaction; which being a new fermen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, is accompanied with a further dilating expanſe, and ſo advanceth their Fluctuati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="9" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="48" facs="tcp:115542:29"/>
                     <head>CHAP. IX.</head>
                     <argument>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Of Remedies.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </argument>
                     <p>IN the diſquiſition of <hi>Therapeuticks,</hi> I would look firſt into the home-born ſhop of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; the ſedulous culture whereof, would abridge the number of exotick ſimples: moſt of which are either adulterared, by the avarice of the Merchant, or come to our hands corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, by the long and torrid ſpace of the Voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age.</p>
                     <p>In <hi>Prophylacticks</hi> we ſee, where the pinch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingeſt cold is, there the wiſe <hi>Creator</hi> hath ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red up abundance of Furre and Fuel, either Wood, Turf, or Coal. Where an <hi>Endemicall</hi> Diſeaſe doth tyrannize, look there for an adequate <hi>Alexiterium:</hi> as the <hi>Guajacum,</hi> where the <hi>Venereous ſcourge</hi> had its Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mencement: The <hi>Iriſh Slat</hi> giveth ſuccour to their particular <hi>Flux:</hi> So we ſhall find <hi>Scorbutical</hi> Plants to luxuriate, where the <hi>Scurvie</hi> is predominant. The <hi>Sedum Minus</hi> in <hi>Sweden:</hi> The <hi>Chamerubus</hi> in <hi>Norway:</hi> The <hi>Cochlearia</hi> in <hi>Germany</hi> and <hi>England,</hi> and will not abide the <hi>French</hi> Air, (which is immune from it,) either by Seed or Plant; as the Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick Profeſſours there did credibly relate unto me. Nature is the beſt Druggiſt.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="49" facs="tcp:115542:29"/>
She ſeemeth alſo to obſerve Seaſons and Times; For when <hi>Feavers</hi> and <hi>Pluriſies</hi> are moſt rife, which is about the <hi>Summer-Solſtice,</hi> then are <hi>Papaver, Rheas, Lettice, Purſlain,</hi> with other proper Herbs, in their fulleſt vigour: yea, as ſome make it out, every Moneth produceth <note place="margin">Merſennus.</note> its ſeaſonable Fruit, reſpondent to the various diſpoſition of the Body.</p>
                     <p>The like might, by induſtry, be elaborated, in Domeſtick Purgative, and Sudorifick Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines; the uſe of the former, with Phleboro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, ſome <hi>Renegadoes of Philoſophy,</hi> which I read <hi>a regret,</hi> have given a Bill of defiance unto, and endeavoured, with weak Engines, to demoliſh: ſubſtituting, inſtead of them no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but their own frothy Fame; a thing of as eminent a conſequence, as abſurdity.</p>
                     <p>Art is a Servant, or Ape of Nature, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in internal Diſeaſes: (Chirurgery, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, ſtandeth more in want of the help of Man: Bones broken, or diſlocated, being left to the ſole hand of Nature, will never be right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reſtored:) and where it ſeeth Nature to cure by ſuch means, there Art muſt imitate it. Thus, in little ones, where natural counſel doth work a Cure by vomiting, there a cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpect Phyſitian may, upon due conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſupply the place, and be Lievtenant to its Leader.</p>
                     <p>Neither doth the <hi>Purging Medicine corrupt good Humours,</hi> as they pretend; moſt of the Purges being bitter, and ſo Preſervatives againſt Putrefaction. This appeareth in the
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:115542:30"/>
Embalming of Dead Bodies, which preſerveth them entire, unto many Generations.</p>
                     <p>Behold the <hi>Dogs</hi> and <hi>Rats,</hi> exhibiting unto themſelves a doſe of <hi>Spear-graſs,</hi> for their eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuation, either by Vomit, or Siege, <hi>which they never learned from the corruption of Pagan Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſities;</hi> which, as a Bone to knaw on, thefe <hi>Miſ-academicks</hi> do, upon every occaſion, caſt unto us: which graſs, (I note by the way) doth it rather by its external form, with its prick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing irritating the Stomack, then by any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward offenſive quality: The ſame effect, not being common to them, that have their <hi>dentes molares,</hi> and uſe rumination.</p>
                     <p>Daily experience doth teach beſides that warm Water, which in ſo ſhort a time, cannot be conceived to corrupt, doth, as an <hi>emetick vehicle,</hi> often educe ſuperfluous and putrid hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, ſalt or acide Phlegme, yellow or black Choller, &amp;c. with a great alleviation of the Patient. As well they may imagine, that a Gli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of Milk, doth, in ſo quick a ſpace, breed thoſe Worms, which are allured to it, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded with it.</p>
                     <p>Moreover, we ſee in moſt acute Diſeaſes, that by ſpontaneous Bleeding, and that ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral ways, either in Man or Woman, ſometime alſo in Children, there is, by the ſole help of Nature a critical Solution: Several of <hi>Hippo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates Aphoriſms,</hi> which alone are left in cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit with theſe men, do aſtipulate the ſame.</p>
                     <p>But, becauſe in Living Bodies, we cannot ſo well demonſtrate the induſtry of Nature with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in;
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:115542:30"/>
while, by its Natural Heat, it ſeparateth, digeſteth, and, by its unſearchable paths, doth baniſh to its utmoſt Borders, whatſoever it findeth refractory to its Laws; let us examine a contuſion without; where the Blood, being provoked out of its proper Veſſels, is of all hands neceſſarily granted to be corrupted: yet we ſee, that by unperceptible Pores, Nature doth evacuate this; Firſt, in blew, then green: Laſt, a yellow colour, till ſhe hath expelled whatſoever is noxious, and reſtored the part to its former <hi>Craſis.</hi> Doubtleſs, Natures ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration within, though of leſſe ſenſe, yet is of greater ſubtilty: Whence may be concluded, that, though <hi>nature never entreth into league with any thing corrupted,</hi> (which they urge con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually upon us, that never denied it) yet af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the exile of her Enemy, reneweth amity with its reſcued remainer.</p>
                     <p>Finally, the long Experiment of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording <hi>Practitioners,</hi> with the confirmation of <hi>Myriads</hi> of <hi>Patients,</hi> confeſſing the ſuddain refreſhment by bleeding, (often before the Chirurgeon getteth to the door) when the Blood is peccant, either in quantity, quality, or motion, may confirm the uſefulneſs, yea, neceſſity of <hi>Phlebotomy.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>If <hi>Empirical</hi> practiſe doth agree with ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal and <hi>Methodical</hi> Art, He who will not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve theſe two faithful Witneſſes, is not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be believed himſelf.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="10" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="82" facs="tcp:115542:31"/>
                     <head>CHAP. X.</head>
                     <argument>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Of Teleſmes.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </argument>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Whether Averruncation of Epidemical Diſeaſes, by Teleſmes, be faiſable and lawful?</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Queſt.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>THat this hath been effected, and that law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, upon the Warrant of <hi>God's Edict,</hi> is <note place="margin">Exam.</note> evident; <hi>in the curing of the biting of Serpents, by erecting a Brazen Serpent in the Wilderneſs:</hi> Which, together with their Sacrifices, the mimick Heathens have tranſlated into Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition: the Aſpect whereof, I confeſs, did cure at a diſtance. Here was no <hi>mummie</hi> of the Wound, nor <hi>Mundane Soul</hi> required; as being tranſcendant, beyond the Effects of Nature: Though the <hi>Rabbins</hi> do contend that the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the <hi>Teleſme</hi> muſt not be contrary to the Diſeaſe; as they imagine <hi>Braſs</hi> to be, againſt the <hi>biting of Serpents.</hi> Yielding ſome Latitude to the Word, I ſhall commit no Soleciſm, if I ſay, <hi>That the Rain-bow hath a Teleſmetical ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nification, for the preſervation of the Univerſe, from Inundation:</hi> which <hi>Rain-bow,</hi> I ſee not, why it ſhould be the firſt, much leſs a miracle, ſeeing it depended upon manifeſt ſecundary cauſes: Morning and Evening every Eye, op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite to the Sun's Beams, will receive a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per <hi>Rain-bow,</hi> when a Horſe pranceth in the Water. What if it were granted never to have
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:115542:31"/>
been ſeen before? Were, therefore, the firſt Diſcoveries of <hi>Load-ſtones, Proſpectives, Gun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powder,</hi> &amp;c. to be canonized for Miracles?</p>
                     <p>That the <hi>Ekronites did make their eight Gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Mice. and five Emrods, and put them in a Coffer by the Ark,</hi> 1 Sam. 6. 5. for averting <hi>Apoteleſmatically</hi> their <hi>Epidemical</hi> Diſeaſes, is clear. As alſo thoſe <hi>blinde</hi> and <hi>lame,</hi> 2 Sam. 5. <note place="margin">Jo. Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory, A. M. on the place.</note> 6, 8. were the <hi>Jebuſites Teleſmes,</hi> erected in their Idol-Temples: And Humane Writers do often concenter in this truth: In which Art <hi>Apollonius Thyaneus,</hi> by the teſtimony of ſeveral Authors, of all the reſt, did obtain the Lawrell: Inſomuch that <hi>Juſtine,</hi> with others, can afford him a laudible <hi>Encomium.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>But, how lawfully this was done, or the like now might be practiſed, is not obvious to my capacity.</p>
                     <p>I am not afraid to exhibite many ſimples, the effects where of I cannot ſo readily reduce to manifeſt cauſes: Elſe were I to abandon, and utterly divorce all <hi>Magnetick, Electrick,</hi> and <hi>Antimonial Medicines;</hi> eſpecially being ignorant, by what faculty, the purging <hi>Simples</hi> do electively attract their adequate humours: yea Light and Fire, the Effects whereof are in view of every vulgar Eye; their proper forms <hi>à priori,</hi> being retired from the acquaintance of moſt judicious men.</p>
                     <p>But that the Forms of theſe ſublunary things, are anſwered with the like Celeſtiall Figurations; and that the <hi>Ideas</hi> of all terre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrial Beings, are, as in a Copy, in the fixed Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:115542:32"/>
by man to be diſtinguiſhed, I cannot be eaſily perſwaded to believe, no more then the <hi>Rabbinical Letters in the Firmament,</hi> or the too occult <hi>Gamahes</hi> of our new Philoſophers: <note place="margin">Gaffarel.</note> Some Phantaſticks, eſpecially if there be a tin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of Melancholy mixed with it, will ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine upon an old Wall, Flame, Graſs, &amp;c more Regular Forms, and better-ſhaped Let ters. But I will lay down ſome grounds.</p>
                     <p n="1">1 The Signs within the Zodiack, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the Tropicks, were made in an arbitrary or fortuitous way: becauſe ſuch a <hi>Sidus,</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther animal or artificial, would beſt contain the moſt eminent Stars of that Conſtellation. For the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> Originally, did decifre them by their <hi>Alphabetical Letters;</hi> the lying <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians</hi> did afterward reduce them into Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures.</p>
                     <p n="2">2 There be many glorious <hi>Sidera,</hi> which can have no reſponſe with things here on Earth; neither are they to be ranked among natural things: as <hi>Lyra, Crater,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                     <p n="3">3 Some are duplicated; as <hi>Corona, Trian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulum, Canis</hi> and that within the ſame Hemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſphere; as <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſa.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="4">4 There ſeemeth a defect; at leaſt, it is hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den from us of <hi>Stars,</hi> adequating the <hi>Vegeta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles</hi> in the ſurface of this our Habitable Earth.</p>
                     <p n="5">
                        <pb n="55" facs="tcp:115542:32"/>
5 There is a groſs miſtake in the placing of them: For Nature, enduring no leaps, procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth by ſteps: When the Sun is ſoaked with the moiſt and cold temper of <hi>Cancer,</hi> then to leap into <hi>Leo,</hi> the hotteſt and dryeſt Sign, is too ſubitaneous an alteration of extream.</p>
                     <p n="6">6 The laſcivious <hi>Aries,</hi> and the fiery <hi>Tau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus,</hi> whoſe Eye with them is <hi>Martial,</hi> are ſo near together, that there would be a fear of the conflagration of the Heavens: a quotannu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all <hi>Phaetontick</hi> combuſtion; but that our <hi>March</hi> Winds, and <hi>April</hi> Showrs do prevent it. They neither agree together, nor aſunder.</p>
                     <p n="7">7 The ſlow proreption of every <hi>Sidus,</hi> out of his proper Sign almoſt unto the ſubſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent, (whether in the eighth or ninth Sphere, it mattereth not) doth overturn the grand Pillar of <hi>Stochelomatical</hi> Art: So that, if I were to <hi>cure the biting of a Scorpion</hi> this way, I ſhould rather take the time, when the <hi>Moon</hi> is in <hi>Sagittarius,</hi> and make the Sign or Figure of a <hi>Centaure,</hi> then a <hi>Scorpion,</hi> which hath crept 28 degrees out of his own Sign.</p>
                     <p>The reaſon of parcelling theſe Signs, to the ſeveral parts of Humane Body, is no leſs ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous: Becauſe <hi>Aries</hi> excelleth in Horns, and <hi>Taurus</hi> in Neck: The one, they make ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>intendant to the <hi>Head:</hi> The other, to the <hi>Throat:</hi> The <hi>Shoulders</hi> being branched into two, muſt have the <hi>Gemini</hi> for their tutelary Angels. Becauſe the <hi>Crabbe</hi> creepeth upon
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:115542:33"/>
his Breaſt, to him is committed the charge of the <hi>Cheſt,</hi> &amp;c. But the ſole reciting of them would endanger a ſmile, from dumpiſh <hi>Demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>critus.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>When the Sun is in</hi> Leo, <hi>becauſe of the fierce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Beast, it is very hot:</hi> and <hi>on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary,</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Object.</note> 
                        <hi>when it paſſeth</hi> Aquarius. <hi>and</hi> Piſces, <hi>their Nature being cold the Sun doth ſymbolize with them: the like of the rest.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Leo</hi> is coldeſt, <hi>Aquarius</hi> and <hi>Piſces</hi> hotteſt, to them which live beyond the Southern Tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pick, <note place="margin">Anſw. 1.</note> and yet the ſame Signs with us. They that dwell between the Arctick and Tropick Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, have, on each ſide, the ſame temper both of Sun and Soil, yet under divers Conſtellati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which never can ariſe mutually one to another.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Cancer,</hi> which coopeth in our Summer Tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pick, is a cold Creature; and <hi>Capricorn,</hi> the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriber <note place="margin">2.</note> of the Winter Tropick, hot.</p>
                     <p>The conjecture taken from <hi>Planets,</hi> is more uncertain; for their Light, the Sun excepted, being borrowed, daily changeth Horns, which the Ancients never underſtood. I doubt much, whether all thoſe Celeſtial Lights were made for the uſe of man; ſince many are, of late, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered; which, without an adventitious <hi>tele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcope</hi> the quickeſt ſight on Earth could never have perceived.</p>
                     <p>So that if any effect of removing Epidemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Diſeaſes by <hi>Teleſmes</hi> be produced, I ſhould rather aſcribe it unto the <hi>Prince of the Air,</hi> (it
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:115542:33"/>
being the fitteſt <hi>medium</hi> to propagate, and ſo to cure all Topical Miſſances) who will ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>villy obey ſuch demands, that he might perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually captivate the Soul, in a falſe perſwaſion of his <hi>Omnipotency. We are not ignorant of his devices, 2 Cor.</hi> 2. 11. It is an old Stratagem, and, An Enemies kindneſs is a dear Bargain.</p>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:115542:34"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:115542:34"/>
                  <p>A STONE TO THE ALTAR OR, Some ſhort <hi>Diſquiſitions,</hi> ON <hi>A few difficult Places</hi> OF SCRIPTURE</p>
                  <p>By <hi>JOHN ROBINSON,</hi> M. D.</p>
                  <p>LONDON: Printed by <hi>J. Streater,</hi> for <hi>Francis Titan</hi> 1658.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="index">
                  <pb facs="tcp:115542:35"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:115542:35"/>
                  <head>The <hi>INDEX.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <list>
                     <item>GEn. 2. 24. Pag. 65</item>
                     <item>Gen. 8. 10, 12. Pag. 67</item>
                     <item>Gen 48. 22. Pag. 68</item>
                     <item>Levit. 13. 13. Pag. 69</item>
                     <item>Levit. 16. Pag. 71</item>
                     <item>Numb. 36. 7. Pag. 72</item>
                     <item>Deut. 21. <hi>ult.</hi> Pag. 73</item>
                     <item>Deut. 25. 3. Pag. 75</item>
                     <item>2 Sam. 6. 3, 4. Pag. 79</item>
                     <item>2 King. 2. 20. Pag. 80</item>
                     <item>Job 3. 3. Pag. 81</item>
                     <item>Pſal. 25. 11. Pag. 82</item>
                     <item>Prov. 24. 16. Pag. 83</item>
                     <item>Eſa. 50. 8. Pag. 84</item>
                     <item>Eſa. 63. 1. Pag. 86</item>
                     <item>Eſa. 66. 7. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Jer. 31. 22. Pag. 87</item>
                     <item>Dan. 12. 3. Pag. 88</item>
                     <item>Math. 3. 14. Pag. 89</item>
                     <item>Math. 8. 6. Pag. 90</item>
                     <item>Math. 9. 22. Pag. 91</item>
                     <item>
                        <pb facs="tcp:115542:36"/>
Math. 27. 37. Pag. 92</item>
                     <item>Math. 27. 44. Pag. 93</item>
                     <item>Joh. 20. 17. Pag. 94</item>
                     <item>1 Cor. 11. 7. Pag. 95</item>
                     <item>1 Tim. 1. 13. Pag. 97</item>
                     <item>Heb. 12. 24. Pag. 98</item>
                     <item>1 Pet. 3. 19. Pag. 100</item>
                     <item>Revel. 12. 11. Pag. 102</item>
                  </list>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:115542:36"/>
                  <head>TO THE <hi>Underſtanding Chriſtian.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>SEeing God hath left Man no better Rule, for the guidance of his Belief and Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience then his <hi>Holy Writ;</hi> and, in the ſame, hath on purpoſe inſerted ſome knot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty places for to make Man more frequent in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination and exerciſe of his Induſtry: for which cauſe the <hi>Jews</hi> had their Oracles delivered unto them without Vowels; (for it is not a bare word but ſenſe, which he intends we ſhould take notice of) and every Chriſtian, within his ſphere, ought to promote his truth. with modeſt reverence unto former mens labours, I thought it not diſadvan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tageous to the Well wiſhers of <hi>Sion,</hi> to offer unto them theſe ſmall Meditations of mine; eſpecially having found very few of them, and thoſe ſhort, in our worthy Predeceſſours Expoſitions.</p>
                  <p>Neither in the building of the <hi>Temple,</hi> were the laudable endeavors of Inferiours, that brought <hi>Stone</hi> or Morter, to be diſcouraged, ſince it was not given to every one, to be a Maſter-Builder, a <hi>Bezaliel,</hi> an <hi>Aholiab:</hi> So neither do I fear any diſguſt, at least, from the beſt ſort of men, becauſe I have, in ſmall meaſure, endeavoured to reach the native ſenſe of theſe enſuing places, wherein I follow no bare Authority of Man, the large nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meroſity
<pb facs="tcp:115542:37"/>
whereof, together with the uncertainty, after purſuit of many tedious Harangues, leaveth their Reader in an unſatisfied Reſolution; the ſpots of their maintained errours, obnubilating the luſtre of their aſſerted truths) but rather by the ſcope of the Text and conſonant places, I ſeek to evince the meaning of the words: By which, if man may have any light, and the <hi>Father of light</hi> have glory; it will be a copious return to him, that wiſheth you all happineſs.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>J. R.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:115542:37"/>
                  <head>A STONE TO THE <hi>ALTAR.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <div type="commentary">
                     <epigraph>
                        <bibl>Gen. 2. 24.</bibl>
                        <q>They ſhall be one Fleſh. <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </q>
                     </epigraph>
                     <p>
                        <hi>INto one Fleſh,</hi> is the Original. Some think that this ſhould have an Aſpect to their Production; becauſe <hi>Eve,</hi> in the <hi>Ribbe,</hi> was an Off-ſet of <hi>Adam:</hi> But to be Fleſh of our Fleſh, and Bone of our Bone, is alſo common to our Progeny; though the manner
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:115542:38"/>
of the latter, by propagation; and the former, by diviſion, be different; yet doth it not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pede an Homogeneouſneſs in the derivation of the matter.</p>
                     <p>Others take <hi>one fleſh</hi> for one <hi>ſpecies,</hi> or kind; as if it had been ſaid: You ſhall not mix mans Fleſh with the Fleſh of Beaſts: But how that can be, as a ground of Marriage, I cannot ſee. Many expound that <hi>one fleſh;</hi> Ye two ſhall ſo joyn, that <hi>one fleſh, i. e.</hi> your Off-ſpring may proceed from you; having reference to their Poſterity: which neither doth fit all Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages; for thoſe that are paſt hope of children ſhould thereby be debarred. Then neither, in regard of the cauſe, not kind, nor effect.</p>
                     <p>The words were not <hi>Adams</hi> but the <hi>Spirits,</hi> by <hi>Moſes,</hi> as appeareth by the citation of them, by our Saviour, <hi>Math.</hi> 9. 5. To ſhew, that it is the neareſt Union, (except that of Soul and Body, which maketh but one per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon) in all the World: They two making properly not a <hi>Plural,</hi> but a <hi>Dual:</hi> to ſpeak accurately, As one maketh no <hi>paucity</hi> ſo no two can amount to a <hi>Plurality: <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>, glued together,</hi> very ſignificantly the <hi>Greeks</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound it <note n="†" place="margin">This is the true <hi>Sarcocolla.</hi>
                        </note>.</p>
                     <p>It might ſeem ſtrange, that <hi>God's</hi> Command ſhould make a Civil Tye ſurpaſs all Natural Obligation, but that I love to acquieſce in <hi>Ipſe dixit.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Two things though, I adde; 1. That whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Parental Relation be Natural or Civil, is queſtionable, 2. There may, nay there ought
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:115542:38"/>
to be a <hi>ſeparation from a Father's houſe;</hi> Pſal. 45. never from a Nuptiall bed. The one for diſtribution of humane ſociety.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="commentary">
                     <epigraph>
                        <bibl>Gen. 8. 10, 12.</bibl>
                        <q>
                           <hi>And</hi> Noah <hi>ſtayed yet other ſeven dayes, and again he ſent forth the dove,</hi> v. 12. <hi>and he ſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed yet other ſeven dayes,</hi> &amp;c.</q>
                     </epigraph>
                     <p>THis man wearied of his priſon, though he had the whole world in a lively Map be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him did often look out for fair weather: rather deſiring to ſet his ſubjects into their Liberty, than to hear their groanes, ariſing from abridgment of their due freedome, and priſtine enlargement.</p>
                     <p>But ſome enquiring the reaſon of the <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth day,</hi> [to omit all <hi>Pythagorean</hi> and <hi>Kab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baliſtical Chimera's,</hi> whoſe ſtudies are to mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie abſtracted, eſpecially the ſeventh, num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber] would inferre from hence, that <hi>Noah kept the Sabbath:</hi> the truth whereof, ſeeing it was inſtituted in Paradiſe, I can readily embrace; but not the reaſon. I think he did it in an <hi>Aſtronomicall reſpect;</hi> he by long-li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved experience, knowing that the <hi>Moon, eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſeventh day, changing its quadra,</hi> was, if not predominant, at leaſt concomitant unto the aeſtuation of the Sea: The good old man meaſuring perhaps too ſtraightly this cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clyſm, within the <hi>zone</hi> and girdle of nature;
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:115542:39"/>
it being, likely, the firſt miracle, [with leave of ſeverer brows] that he had ſeen.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="commentary">
                     <epigraph>
                        <bibl>Gen. 48. 22.</bibl>
                        <q>I give thee a portion above thy brethren, which I took from the hand of the Amorite, with my ſword and bow.</q>
                     </epigraph>
                     <p>To wave the natural reaſon, given by ſome, <hi>why the ſoul ſhould propheſy towards its depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture;</hi> becauſe, its ſtanding, as on tip-toes, at the threſhall of the body, can take a ſurer and further ſurvey, then being cloſe immured; [that the ſeparated ſoul doth underſtand more, then being united to the body; I take it to be not from a quicker apprehenſion; but from more glorious objects.] Some referre this <hi>[which I took]</hi> unto <hi>the ſpoilo gotten from the Sichemites, by the ſons of</hi> Jacob: but that ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth very harſh: For their <hi>Father,</hi> Gen. 34. 30. <hi>reproved them for their perfidious dealing with them;</hi> and <hi>Gen. 49. 6. he curſeth them for it.</hi> Now that goods treacherouſly gotten, ſhould be their portion, is ſomewhat abſurd.</p>
                     <p>It will run more ſmooth, prophetically, <hi>[that I have taken]</hi> for, <hi>[that I ſhall take]</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the trope of the <hi>Father</hi> for the <hi>Sons:</hi> And ſo, by faith, he triumphs before the victory. Such a ſpirit there was in <hi>David,</hi> who blazo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the trophees, before the conqueſt: <hi>Gilead is mine, and Manaſſch is mine,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 60.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="69" facs="tcp:115542:39"/>
But why <hi>Joſeph ſhould have that of the Amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite, taken by ſword and bow, more then the reſt</hi> my conjecture is; he doth, for the preſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of his Brethren in <hi>Egypt,</hi> aſſigne him this ſurplus, above his Brethren; among whom he had, beſides, his portion equally divided by lot, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 47. 13. For to none of his remaining Sons, did he bequeath a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminate reſidence. That he doth confine the <hi>Sea-coaſt unto</hi> Zebulon, <hi>Gen.</hi> 49. 13. is ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a preſage of his nautick profeſſion, then a ſupernumerary grant above his equalls.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="commentary">
                     <epigraph>
                        <bibl>Levit. 13. 13.</bibl>
                        <q>Then the Prieſt ſhall conſider, and behold, if the Leproſie hath covered all his fleſh, he ſhall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce him clean, that hath the plague; it is turned white, he is clean.</q>
                     </epigraph>
                     <p>FOr the clearing of this, becauſe vulgar rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon would conclude the contrary, I muſt premiſe a few words.</p>
                     <p>The <hi>Ceremonies</hi> of the <hi>Jews,</hi> were either <hi>ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picall,</hi> having reference to <hi>Chriſt;</hi> or <hi>Symbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licall,</hi> by which, as <hi>Gods Hieroglyplicks,</hi> they were tutored in ſome morall homages: Or more plainly thus, They were either of Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges, and ſo <hi>Evangelical;</hi> or of duties: Of which latter ſort were, <hi>Not to aſſimilate the m<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves according to the ſuperstitious faſhions, of the</hi> Sabeans <hi>or</hi> Ghaldeans, <hi>their Neighbours.</hi> Of the like nature, was <hi>ſeething the kid in the
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:115542:40"/>
milk of the dam; the cutting of corners in the hair;</hi> which with them were appurtenances unto faſcination.</p>
                     <p>In ſeveral of theſe Laws, the thing it ſelf was no ſin; though there did cleave a legal uncleanneſſe unto it. Sometime it was <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded,</hi> as <hi>laying forth, and burying of the dead;</hi> yea the interring of corpſes, the <hi>Politicians</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Grotius.</note> make a law of nature; being a preſervation of the living. Sometime <hi>naturall,</hi> as <hi>ſickneſſe and iſſues:</hi> Now and then <hi>defective,</hi> as <hi>Eunuchs.</hi> Note, by the way, <hi>God took away</hi> in an advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagous ſubſtitute, in the Goſpel, <hi>their barren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> by <hi>baptizing the Eunuch,</hi> according to his promiſe, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 56. 3.</p>
                     <p>Now for the explaining of this text, Why, <hi>being ſpread over, he ſhould be clean;</hi> two rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons may be given: <hi>Phyſicall,</hi> and <hi>Ceremoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all: Phyſicall</hi> when a diſeaſe is ſpread all over the body, as in that ſoon cured kind of Drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy called <hi>Leucophlegmatia,</hi> Nature will eaſily recover that; becauſe every part hath an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate heat to preſerve it ſelf; and expell that which is noxious: and ſo the <hi>diſcrimen certaminis,</hi> the maine body of the enemy, doth not lay upon one part; except it be in a raw <hi>criſis,</hi> where, after a battle, conquering nature doth ablegate its adverſary, to the vileſt and remoteſt emunctories.</p>
                     <p>The <hi>Ceremoniall</hi> reaſon I take, from the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall Laws, given to the <hi>Jews</hi> forbidding <hi>mixture; either of themſelves with others;</hi> or <hi>of things of ſeverall kinds;</hi> as of <hi>making linſey-wolſey;
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:115542:40"/>
plowing with an oxe and an aſſe; ſowing of meſling,</hi> &amp;c. [into which primitive inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the <hi>Rabbins</hi> have ſhuffled burdenſome and ridiculous devices, of their own] where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as either of theſe, without any <hi>teſellation</hi> or checker-work, ſingle, were lawfull. So this Symbolizing with the former, <hi>if it were all over of one colour,</hi> viz. <hi>white,</hi> becauſe void of heterogeneous mixture, <hi>it was pronounced clean.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>If the Allegory were not ſtrained, the <hi>over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpread Leproſy,</hi> an Embleme of our ſins; and the <hi>whiteneſſe</hi> of righteouſneſſe; might have an aſpect unto <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="commentary">
                     <epigraph>
                        <bibl>Levit. 16.</bibl>
                        <q>How could the Scape-goat be a type of Chriſts Reſurrection, as generally it is expounded, ſince <note place="margin">Queſt.</note> it never dyed?</q>
                     </epigraph>
                     <p>BEcauſe its fellow, which was choſen by <note place="margin">Anſw.</note> lot, did die; And for that Reſurrection was not competent unto beaſts, that one offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring was ſown up and patcht of two individu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alls; whereof one died, and the other eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped: and being one continued act, did, <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junctim, reſemble the death and reſurrection of Christ.</hi> The uncapableneſſe of the Subject in one, diſtributed this type into two: and becauſe <hi>no remiſſion of ſin without blood,</hi> the latter died in the former; and the former re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vived in the latter: So the eſcape of one of
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:115542:41"/>
the repreſented, was an adumbration of the <hi>Reſurrection;</hi> ſince it was reprieved from death, by the immediate oracle of <hi>God</hi> in the <hi>lot.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="commentary">
                     <epigraph>
                        <bibl>Numb. 36. 7.</bibl>
                        <q>None were to marry out of their own Family.</q>
                     </epigraph>
                     <p>TWo ſorts of perſons were exempted; Firſt, the <hi>Levites;</hi> and that upon good ground: becauſe <hi>they had no inheritance among their bretheren.</hi> And ſecondly, the <hi>Royall fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily</hi> was not obliged thereunto: their <hi>porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> being aſſigned them out of the <hi>Kings Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chequer:</hi> I And this well conſidered, anſwereth many objections; and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out this Latitude, ſeverall difficulties, and <hi>Remora's</hi> will ariſe in the <hi>Old Teſtament,</hi> ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting, as it were, a ſuſpicion of levity, by a tranſgreſſion of this precept, among the moſt eminent of the <hi>Jews.</hi> But <hi>the poor,</hi> though they had paſſed away their inheritance, <hi>were not exempted from this law;</hi> becauſe either their <hi>near kinſman might redeem it,</hi> or <hi>at the year of Jubile, it was restored gratis.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The accompliſhing of the preſage of the linage of the <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> was a Cardinall cauſe of this edict. As far as it is grounded upon equity, it bindeth us, analogically; though not <hi>in eodem puncto.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="commentary">
                     <pb n="73" facs="tcp:115542:41"/>
                     <epigraph>
                        <bibl>Deut. 21. ult.</bibl>
                        <q>He that is hanged on a tree, is accur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of God.</q>
                     </epigraph>
                     <p>BOth former and latter Expoſitors run for the nativity of this back unto <hi>Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe,</hi> to the firſt ſin which was brought forth between the knees of a <hi>tree;</hi> and therefore <hi>hanging on a tree</hi> is become a malediction: But that I think is too far fetcht: for a Gib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet is, and may be made variouſly, of any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſubſtance.</p>
                     <p>This ſentence is not to be taken in a <hi>moral</hi> ſignification, reaching any ſorts of people; but in a <hi>Judicial</hi> ſenſe, proper to the <hi>Jews:</hi> and therefore the reaſons muſt not be common, to all the <hi>Univerſe</hi> of mankind; but drawn from their <hi>Political</hi> conſtitution.</p>
                     <p>This capital puniſhment was no curſe of it ſelf; no more then the lapidation, precipita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſword, or fire was. Two probable rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons may be given. Firſt, that this kind of death, was without effuſion of blood; which <hi>ſtrangulation,</hi> even in beaſts, and that other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe clean-ones, was an <hi>abhorred thing among the Jews</hi> and ſo <hi>Ceremonially accurſed.</hi> Many both godly and wiſe Expoſitors hold this rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to be <hi>moral.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>But 2dly, [as in ſome creatures their own entrails prove the propereſt ſauce: ſo in this place] the reaſon which <hi>Moſes</hi> giveth in the
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:115542:42"/>
text, well pondered will be moſt genuine, <hi>That the Land be not defiled which the Lord thy God giveth thee.</hi> In all <hi>Iſrael, no unclean thing was to be left uncovered.</hi> Ch. 23. 19. In all ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pital puniſhments, there was a removing of the offenders dead body out of ſight; in this there was a continued and publick ſhew of that which nature it ſelf doth ſhrink at. See <hi>Gen. 23. 4. All dead corpſes were Legally un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean:</hi> Their defilement was prevented by <hi>bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying;</hi> which is <hi>over and over commanded in this verſe:</hi> leſt, by <hi>hanging on a tree,</hi> there be a <hi>curſe,</hi> or rather an <hi>execration of God:</hi> then would ſtrangers have exprobrated <hi>God's</hi> peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; Lo there hangeth an <hi>Iſraelite:</hi> So that the ſenſe may be, He that remaineth <hi>hanging on a tree,</hi> is ceremonially an <hi>execration unto the Lord.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>God in the death of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> to ſhew his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure againſt ſin, did, by this <hi>Judicial</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding, point at the <hi>Moral</hi> curſe, due unto us, tranſlated upon his <hi>Son.</hi> An <hi>Evangelical malediction.</hi> His elevation above the earth, prefigured, by <hi>lifting up of the Serpent in the wilderneſs,</hi> was rather an emblem of his ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious and expanſe conſpicuouſneſs, then of eminent deteſtation: The Holy Ghoſt ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to point at this, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. 6.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="commentary">
                     <pb n="75" facs="tcp:115542:42"/>
                     <epigraph>
                        <bibl>Deut. 25. 3.</bibl>
                        <q>Forty ſtripes he may give him, and not exceed.</q>
                     </epigraph>
                     <p>THe <hi>Rabbins</hi> are here as uncertain as vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. Let us ſee, what can be drawn from text or equity.</p>
                     <p>God might have commanded man ſeveral du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, without alledging any cauſe for them; yet in moſt, where nature is ſilent, as in the <hi>Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath;</hi> which not having any dependency upon the Law of Nature, God doth annex more then one reaſon for the obſervation of it: the reſt of the commandements, are bare and naked, becauſe their juſtice may be readd by the Lamp of reaſon. Where God accoſteth a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to his precept, there he doth perſwade ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then compel.</p>
                     <p>Firſt then, that this was a particular Law proper unto the <hi>Jews,</hi> may be evinced from the laſt words of this verſe, <hi>leſt thy brother ſhould ſeem vile unto thee;</hi> ſtrengthned by the example of <hi>Paul, 2 Cor. 11. 24. Forty ſave one stripes did I ſuffer, five times of the Jews.</hi> Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther actively nor paſſively, binding the ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger.</p>
                     <p>That, there ſhould no cruelty be uſed, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong Gods people, is certain: yet doth not anſwer the reaſon of the exact and defined number, The Text ſaith, <hi>lest he be contemned.</hi> Either it may be, as forty years are the full
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:115542:43"/>
ſtrength of man; the third year being the prime of Infancy, of Child-hood the 14th: the 21 of Adoleſcency; of Youth the 30th, and of Virility the fourtieth: ſo the higheſt degree of puniſhment ſhould not exceed four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſtripes: But that, becauſe Natural, is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to all Humane kind.</p>
                     <p>Or, rather alluding to the <hi>fourty years tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel in the Wilderneſs,</hi> leſt now being in <hi>Canaan,</hi> your promiſed Reſt, you uſe him harder, then you were entertained in the contemptible Wilderneſs; and, by the <hi>number of ſtripes,</hi> do renew the memory of his priſtine equal years ſervitude.</p>
                     <p>The <hi>Feast of Tabernacles,</hi> that God inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, was with rejoycing for deliverance.</p>
                     <p>Juſt fourty ſtripes, was too near the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream, and, ſo far, Moral.</p>
                     <p>The <hi>Whip of three Cords,</hi> in <hi>Maimonides,</hi> by whoſe 13 blows, there amounted 39 ſtripes, ſeemeth a Rabbinical Legend.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="commentary">
                     <epigraph>
                        <bibl>Judg. 16. 30.</bibl>
                        <q>The dead that he ſlew at his death, were more then thoſe that he ſlew in his life.</q>
                     </epigraph>
                     <p>I Love not to act over <hi>Origen;</hi> or the <hi>Venetian,</hi> who, beyond the intention of the Holy Ghoſt, do, by force, preſs an Allegorical, and that often not very decent, to bear the genu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine ſenſe of the Scripture.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="77" facs="tcp:115542:43"/>
But where there are ſo manifeſt Linea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the prefiguration of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> no man can deny a <hi>type.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>In the beginning of this Chapter, <hi>Sampſon was compaſſed about with his enemies; he aroſe at Midnight, carryed away their Gates and Bars, unto the top of the Hill:</hi> Every circumſtance doth quadrate with his and our <hi>Saviour.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The Queſtion will be, <hi>Whether his death, by</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Queſt.</note> 
                        <hi>conquering more at it then in his life time, may not as aptly reſemble the death of Chriſt?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Some make a ſtand here; becauſe an evil <note place="margin">Anſw.</note> act (ſay they) as is ſelf-aſſaſſine, cannot be any type of good.</p>
                     <p>But I queſtion, whether the act were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnable; that is, either whether this fact were not rather a laying down of his life, then a deſtroying of it; or, this being granted whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>rebus ſic ſtantibus,</hi> it were not lawful.</p>
                     <p>The general Reaſons are theſe: He, before his death, <hi>prayed the Lord to renew his ſtrength:</hi> This was accepted and anſwered: yea, He is regiſtred, by the Teſt of God's Approbation, <hi>to die in Faith,</hi> Heb. 11. 32, 39.</p>
                     <p>But more particularly, to juſtifie his end; We muſt have Recourſe unto the Cuſtome, (which in time became a Law) of the <hi>Zelotes</hi> among the <hi>Jewes;</hi> where a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate man, kindled by Zeal, for Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, or Adultery, if it were publick, (in the
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:115542:44"/>
ſight of ten ſay the ancient <hi>Maſters]</hi> might beat or ſlay the Offender, taken in the Fact.</p>
                     <p>The firſt Example we have in <hi>Phineas,</hi> who <hi>appeaſed the wrath of Gods,</hi> Pſal. 106. 31. <hi>by kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Zimri and Cozbi.</hi> Upon the ſame ground of zeal, <hi>Christ</hi> was ſuffered to <hi>purge the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple:</hi> Neither did the <hi>Jews</hi> ſo much queſtion this, though it be generally ſo interpreted; as the <hi>Miracle in the Fig-tree, and his Teaching.</hi> See <hi>Mark</hi> 11. 27. As <hi>He walked in the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> and <hi>Luc.</hi> 22. 1. As <hi>He taught the People,</hi> &amp;c. Of this Rank was <hi>Simon the Zelote,</hi> Luc. 6. 15. not the <hi>Cananite,</hi> as our Tranſlation hath it, <hi>Math. 10. 4. Mark</hi> 3. 18. being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>.</note> by the affinity of the Word <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifying a <hi>Zelote,</hi> as our, far and near honoured, Mr. <hi>Selden</hi> obſerveth.</p>
                     <p>Now <hi>Sampſon,</hi> being no mans ſubject, might, without injuſtice, in open Blaſpheny, take vengeance of the Offenders: without a Warrant from the Magiſtrate: For he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, by right, was <hi>Judge of Iſrael:</hi> and had power, as of others, ſo of himſelf, in this caſe. Neither was he a ſubject of the <hi>Philiſtines,</hi> his life depending on the Will of the <hi>Conquerours.</hi> Whoſoevers body is bound in chains, is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged from all civil obligation: and thus he may be acquitted from the crime of murder, or ſui-cide. The <hi>Antitype, Joh.</hi> 10. 18. is very ſignificant, <hi>No man taketh my life from me, but I lay it down of my ſelf.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="commentary">
                     <pb n="79" facs="tcp:115542:44"/>
                     <epigraph>
                        <bibl>2 Sam. 6. 3, 4.</bibl>
                        <q>
                           <hi>And they brought the Ark of God out of the houſe of</hi> Abinadab, <hi>that was in</hi> Gibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah.</q>
                     </epigraph>
                     <p>THE ordinary Tranſlations have it, as if <hi>Gibeah</hi> had been a City; and <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, were a <hi>proper name,</hi> which cannot conveniently here have a place: But <hi>appellatively,</hi> it ſignifieth a <hi>Hill:</hi> and ſo it is uſed, <hi>Jerem. 2. 20. 1 Sam.</hi> 10. 5. Sometime, indeed, it ſignifieth a City of <hi>Benjamin;</hi> and ſo is the right Interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Judg. 19. 16. 1 Sam. 22. 6. 7. Hoſ.</hi> 5. 8. But at this time the <hi>Ark</hi> was in a City, after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward called <hi>Kiriath-jeharim,</hi> in the Tribe of <hi>Judah, Joſ. 15. 60. 1 Sam.</hi> 7. 2. Beſides <hi>Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nadab</hi> was of the Tribe of <hi>Judah,</hi> and dwelt there not in <hi>Benjamin.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>It is not unuſual in cognomination, to turn a part of the Commons into a private Fee-Simple: but the frequent peculation of Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellatives in the ſame place, is a haſtening un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a <hi>generical ataxy.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="commentary">
                     <pb n="80" facs="tcp:115542:45"/>
                     <epigraph>
                        <bibl>2 King. 2. 20.</bibl>
                        <q>Bring me a new Cruſe, and put Salt therein,</q>
                     </epigraph>
                     <p>GOD, in working of Miracles, as being a free Agent, doth often vary and change the manner and diſpenſation of them: Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times He uſeth uatural and proper cauſes, <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending the quantity;</hi> as <hi>feeding many thouſands with a Lads burden, a few loaves, and ſmall fiſhes:</hi> or, <hi>intending the quality;</hi> as the <hi>plaister of figs upon</hi> Hezekiah'<hi>s ſore:</hi> Many times he worketh without ſecundary cauſes; as in the <hi>Creation, raiſing of the dead,</hi> (in raiſing of the <hi>Shunamite's ſon, 2 King.</hi> 4. there were ſome natural means, which that inviſible finger of the Lord did work by) <hi>calming of the ſea,</hi> &amp;c. Now and then the Miracle was contrary to the means; as in the <hi>Sacrifice of Eliah, 1 King.</hi> 18. where, <hi>to make the wood burn, water was three times poured on it:</hi> So generally Expoſitors do paraphraſe upon the <hi>clay laid on the blind mans eyes.</hi> But that is very queſtionable; for, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the nitre which is in the Earth and Spit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, the Angularity of Sand is a regular <hi>Seif,</hi> or methodical <hi>Collyrie,</hi> (not to extenuate the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle) fot the waſting and leſſening of the Scaly Films, the cauſe of blindneſs.</p>
                     <p>The queſtion will be concerning this place. Some utterly condemn <hi>Salt,</hi> as a cauſe of bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renneſs; and ſo tropically expound <hi>Jud.</hi> 9. 45.
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:115542:45"/>
where <hi>Abimelech having deſtroyed Shechem, did be ſprinkle it with Salt.</hi> Others commend it for the beſt enrichment of ground, advancing fertility; and that common Salt, as this was, doth, by ſymbolization, eaſily turn into nitre.</p>
                     <p>I think it will bear a double conſtruction: either as ſome ſmall ſecondary cauſe of eme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lioration of the <hi>ground and water,</hi> [the extent was, I am ſure, beyond the power and limits of Nature.] or, as the Text intimateth, for the <hi>continuation and perpetuity</hi> of the effect: For <hi>Salt,</hi> in Scripture-Language, is a Metaphor of <hi>duration;</hi> and ſo a <hi>Covenant of Salt, Numb.</hi> 18. 19. the Holy Ghoſt expoundeth it an <hi>Everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting Covenant.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="commentary">
                     <epigraph>
                        <bibl>JOB. 3. 3.</bibl>
                     </epigraph>
                     <p>SOme, both ancient and modern, have drawn this Book, beginning from this Verſe, unto the ſixt of the laſt Chapter, into queſtion, denying it to be a Hiſtory, but rather a <hi>Diſcourſe and Treatiſe, concerning a Morall Queſtion; Why the Wicked of this world proſper, and the godly are afflicted.</hi> Their Reaſon is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe all that Diſcourſe is, in the Original, in <hi>Hexameter</hi> Verſe, which is no ſtyle of ſadneſs: the edge of which Argument is too dull, to pierce my yieldinger apprehenſion: for we find profane <hi>Authors</hi> in the ſame ſtyle, which bemoan their Tragical misfortunes: <hi>Ovid</hi> writes five Books <hi>de Triſtibus;</hi> the better half
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:115542:46"/>
are in that Meter: <hi>Virgil,</hi> in the ſame ſtrain, ſingeth very ſad lines. But I rather encline to believe, that it was a reall Diſcourſe, or <hi>interlocution, between God out of the Whirle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>winde (Chap. 38. 1.) Job, and his friends.</hi> Firſt, in Proſe; after by himſelf, or ſome godly man, run into Meter; either for the help of Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, as all Poetry is, or for the uſe of the Church, in ſinging of them publickly; which, without a Harmony of numerical ſyllables, will make a confuſed Diſcord.</p>
                     <p>By the ſame reaſon, they may reject ſeveral of the <hi>Pſalms of David,</hi> denying them to be Prayers; which, without contradiction, at firſt being powred out in Proſe, afterward, for the forenamed Reaſons, were, by himſelf, or ſome other <hi>Maſter-Muſitian,</hi> meaſured into Verſe.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="commentary">
                     <epigraph>
                        <bibl>Pſal. 25. 11.</bibl>
                        <q>Thou wilt pardon my ſinne, becauſe it is great.</q>
                     </epigraph>
                     <p>THE pittiful miſtake my Eares and Eyes have been Witneſs of, and that in learned men, of the word <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, I paſs over: they ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it a cauſality, <hi>[for]</hi> Whereas indeed it ſhould be an adverſative <hi>[although]</hi> or <hi>notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding:</hi> and ſo it cannot but be readd, <hi>Hab. 3. 17. Although the Fig-tree ſhould not bloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome.</hi> The ſame miſtake is in the <hi>Greek <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>, Act. 1. 17. For he was numbred with us;</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:115542:46"/>
of <hi>although.</hi> If it might have the power of a cauſe, yet the adverſative ought, as moſt proper, to be taken, in the firſt place.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="commentary">
                     <epigraph>
                        <bibl>Prov. 24. 16.</bibl>
                        <q>
                           <hi>The juſt man falleth ſeven times, [in a day]</hi> is not in the Text.</q>
                     </epigraph>
                     <p>THE general Comment hereon is; <hi>The juſt ſinneth often,</hi> yet <hi>he riſeth again:</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the word uſed here <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, never, in this whole Book, doth ſignifie to fall into ſinne: Enumeration of places will evince it, <hi>Chap. 11. ver.</hi> 5, 14. &amp; 13. 17. &amp; 17. 20. &amp; 26. 27. &amp; 20. 10, 14. 18. In all theſe places it can bear no other ſenſe then of <hi>Affliction.</hi> Now the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt way, to attain the ſcope of an Author, whether Divine or Humane, is, to trace the Age Place, Dialect, or <hi>Genius</hi> he writeth in: And if between the weight of two equal Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, there be an undiſtinguiſhable Equipoiſe, the number of conſonant places muſt caſt the Scales.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="commentary">
                     <pb n="84" facs="tcp:115542:47"/>
                     <epigraph>
                        <bibl>Eſa. 50. 8.</bibl>
                        <q>He is near that juſtifieth me.</q>
                     </epigraph>
                     <p>
                        <hi>CAndace's Eunuch</hi> need no Interpreter for this place: Every Line being a Graphical <hi>Pourtraict</hi> of <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>But how <hi>Chriſt was justified,</hi> is not ſo evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent; Juſtification not being here taken for making one juſt: in which ſenſe it is but twice uſed by the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> Dan. 12. 3. Rev. 22. 11. (though that were true: he being the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs and eternal <hi>Image of his Father,</hi> as a pure River derived from a pure Fountain) but for a <hi>judicial acquittance,</hi> in oppoſition to <hi>condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation,</hi> ver. 9. And becauſe <hi>Juſtification is by Faith,</hi> its Nature in Chriſt is worth our diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition.</p>
                     <p>None will ſay, that <hi>Chriſt was juſtified by Faith,</hi> but by Works: He could not be both the Object and Subject: I ſpeak now of <hi>Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelical,</hi> not <hi>Legal</hi> Faith: which latter is, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that <hi>God is true, wiſe, keeping promiſe;</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſered, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. 6. For this <hi>Chriſt</hi> had, and ſo had the <hi>Angels,</hi> and <hi>Adam</hi> in innocency, onely differing in mutability. This kind of <hi>Faith</hi> will not ceaſe in Heaven, but there will be a full recumbency of the Soul, upon the Divine Goodneſs, for its perpetuation unto Eternity. The Son did believe, that the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther would perform his Eternal Pact with
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:115542:47"/>
him, <hi>to give him the utmoſt ends of the Earth, as the fruit of his travel:</hi> And <hi>becauſe it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came him to fulfill all Righteouſneſs,</hi> Math. 3. 15. he did ſubmit to the Sacraments as they were good Works; whereto he was bound, by vertue of the ſecond Commandement, but not as they were Relative and Organicall Signs.</p>
                     <p>In a word, <hi>Chriſt</hi> the Head did believe <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gally,</hi> that all his members ſhould believe <hi>Evangelically:</hi> The former is a mark of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection; the latter, of defection.</p>
                     <p>Neither doth <hi>Juſtification,</hi> as ſome will urge, preſuppoſe always guilt; but ſometime a Declaration of Innocency. There was, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, a Debt and Bond, which the Law did challenge againſt Chriſt, but no Forfeiture; for, that, He had diſcharged unto the full.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="commentary">
                     <pb n="86" facs="tcp:115542:48"/>
                     <epigraph>
                        <bibl>Eſa. 63. 1.</bibl>
                        <q>
                           <hi>Who is he that commeth from</hi> Edom, <hi>with died garments from</hi> Bozrah?</q>
                     </epigraph>
                     <p>THis litterally is not meant of the <hi>ſufferings of Chriſt</hi> as many think; but the <hi>redneſſe of his blood</hi> is rather of his <hi>enemies</hi> than his <hi>own. Bozrah</hi> and <hi>Edom</hi> did belong to the adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of the Church: He ſpeaketh of his anger and fury: v. 3. in the day of vengeance, <hi>v.</hi> 4. So I gather that the <hi>red wine of the preſs,</hi> as alſo that, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19. 15. is not of his <hi>paſſion</hi> but of his <hi>victory:</hi> Though the former were the way to the latter; and they as the effect upon the cauſe, ſucceeded one another; yet, in conception of reaſon, can and ought to be diſtinguiſhed.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="commentary">
                     <epigraph>
                        <bibl>Eſa. 66. 7.</bibl>
                        <q>Before ſhe travailed, ſhe brought forth; before her pain came, ſhe was delivered of a man-childe.</q>
                     </epigraph>
                     <p>NOt onely Papiſts, to maintain the <hi>virgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity</hi> of our <hi>Saviour's mother, in, ante, &amp; post partum;</hi> but ſome of our Orthodox Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitors, hold this Text to deſcribe <hi>Chriſts birth:</hi> But, in my judgment, farre wide: For, neither in the antecedent, or conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent, is there any ſhaddow pointing toward
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:115542:48"/>
the <hi>Virgin Mary.</hi> Yea, v. 10. <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> is mentioned, and, <hi>v. 8. Sion is</hi> ſaid to <hi>travel.</hi> Beſides, here the <hi>Earth is</hi> deſcribed to <hi>bring forth,</hi> and that <hi>many Children:</hi> So that neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily it muſt be underſtood of the ſuddain and unexpected fruitfulneſſe of the <hi>Church.</hi> The ſame expoſition doth ſute the like words, <hi>Mich. 5. 3. Eſa.</hi> 49. 20.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="commentary">
                     <epigraph>
                        <bibl>Jer. 31. 22.</bibl>
                        <q>A Woman ſhall compaſſe a Man.</q>
                     </epigraph>
                     <p>COngeneous unto the former, is this mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake: neither will the Originall, <hi>a ſtrong man,</hi> nor the ſenſe of the ſequell <hi>v.</hi> 32. bear it concerning the <hi>Incarnation</hi> of <hi>Chriſt.</hi> But it is ſpoken of the <hi>Church under the Goſpel;</hi> and of the <hi>New Covenant:</hi> And ſo the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor</hi> to the <hi>Hebrues</hi> expoundeth it at large, <hi>Chap.</hi> 8. 8.</p>
                     <p>Many places, in <hi>holy writ,</hi> deſigne a ſtate, company, or order; which faſtened upon ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularities, and individualls, openeth no ſmall gap unto errors. The ſame muſt be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood of <hi>Antichriſt;</hi> which muſt have its ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination in a profeſſion, not in a perſonality: <hi>He is Antichriſt, that,</hi> [either in word or deed] <hi>denieth the Father and the Son,</hi> 1 John 2. 21.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="commentary">
                     <pb n="88" facs="tcp:115542:49"/>
                     <epigraph>
                        <bibl>Daniel 12. 3.</bibl>
                        <q>They that turn many, ſhall ſhine, as Starrs, for ever.</q>
                     </epigraph>
                     <p>HEnce ſome conclude, that the conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter muſt neceſſarily be ſaved; which notwithſtanding, in the abſoluteneſſe of its truth, I queſtion. <hi>Chriſt</hi> did adde to his word the <hi>gift of miracles,</hi> to beget faith in the hearers; and the <hi>Diſciples returning, did rejoyce that the Devils were ſubjected unto them:</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong theſe, was the <hi>ſon of perdition.</hi> Hereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is grounded <hi>Pauls</hi> watchword, 1 Cor. 9. ult. <hi>Least, while I preach to others, I my ſelf become a caſt-way.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>It were a notable ſhaking to my faith, if the meſſenger, by whom it was conveighed, ſhould turn to hereſie, or wordly vanity. By the power of his <hi>word, God</hi> calleth ſome, though through the mouth of a wicked one, a childe, yea, [I ſcorn the ſuſpicion of coy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage or forgery] a ſtage-player. A weak or leprous hand may ſow good ſeed: the <hi>treaſure</hi> is more to be valued, then the <hi>earthen veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>This then, with other places, which by the <hi>holy Ghoſt</hi> are delivered univerſally, for fear of corruption, muſt be taken with limitation; and ſeaſoned with the ſalt of reſtrained ſenſe; a <hi>communiter,</hi> an <hi>ut plurimùm,</hi> &amp;c. So, Heb. 9. 27. <hi>It is appointed for all men once to die:</hi> This
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:115542:49"/>
cannot be reaching every individuall: for ſome never taſted deaths cup: Others, who had their lives reiterated have twice under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gone it. <hi>At the day of judgment, inſtead of death, there will be a momentaneous change,</hi> 1 Cor. 15. 51.</p>
                     <p>Severall things are ſet down abſolutely, which muſt have a comparative interpretati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Prov. 8. 10. Receive instruction, and not ſilver: and knowledge, rather then gold:</hi> Luk. 14. 26. <hi>Whoſoever commeth unto me, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth not his Father and Mother, cannot be my Diſciple,</hi> Rom. 9. 19. Jacob <hi>have I loved, but</hi> Eſau <hi>have I hated.</hi> Theſe poſitives muſt have their expoſition graduall.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="commentary">
                     <epigraph>
                        <bibl>Mat. 3. 14.</bibl>
                     </epigraph>
                     <p>
                        <hi>IOhn,</hi> in a godly courteſy, <hi>excuſed to baptiſe Chriſt,</hi> ſaying; <hi>I have need to be baptiſed of thee, and comeſt thou to me?</hi> compared with <hi>Math. 11. v. 4. Art thou He, that ſhould come, or do we look for another?</hi> ſeemeth, as if <hi>John</hi> at firſt knew him to be the <hi>Saviour of the World;</hi> and afterward doubted of him: which would have been but a ſlow progreſſe in ſuch a ones faith, when he had heard and ſeen ſo much of him, and from him.</p>
                     <p>But the probableſt reconcilement, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, is, that <hi>he ſent his Diſciples,</hi> rather to confirme their faith, then to informe his judgment: In him it was rather a work of
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:115542:50"/>
charity, then of doubt: yet I think his know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge was confuſed and overclouded, till <hi>he ſaw the ſpirit deſcend on him,</hi> Joh. 1. 33.</p>
                     <p>It is very unlikely, that upon the tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a priſon, his faith ſhould be ſhaken, who was <hi>more then a Prophet, 11. 9. The meſſenger to prepare the way,</hi> v. 10. <hi>The greateſt of them that are born of women,</hi> v. 11. <hi>The</hi> Elias <hi>to come,</hi> v. 14. Theſe <hi>encomiums</hi> would have been very unſeaſonable, at ſuch a time, by him, who did all things in ſeaſon: when his affiance was a ſtaggering, and his confidence a wavering.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="commentary">
                     <epigraph>
                        <bibl>Mat. 8. 6.</bibl>
                        <q>My ſervant lyeth at home, ſick of the palſy, grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouſly tormented.</q>
                     </epigraph>
                     <p>WHat if a Medicall notion ſhould correct his Torments? For a palſy is a reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the ſinewes, without any pain; a depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, no depravation of ſenſe, might it not better be rendred for a <hi>triall</hi> of his faith, and <hi>exploration</hi> of his patience? Since the word in its Originall <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, doth denote a <hi>touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone,</hi> by which ſilver and gold are brought to their due <hi>examen.</hi> The ſame word is predi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated of things void of ſenſe, and feeling: <hi>Mat.</hi> 14. 24.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="commentary">
                     <pb n="91" facs="tcp:115542:50"/>
                     <epigraph>
                        <bibl>Mat. 9. 22.</bibl>
                        <q>Thy faith hath made thee whole.</q>
                     </epigraph>
                     <p>BY this, and other parallel places, ſome conclude a generall notion: <hi>That Chriſt or his Diſciples did never work miracles, but upon believing perſons;</hi> Faith being fore-ſeen either in themſelves, or in their friends. But this will not hold touch: For what faith there could be in the <hi>dead bodies of the Saints,</hi> or in their ſouls, <hi>that were raiſed from the grace;</hi> Mat. 27. 52. I cannot underſtand. The <hi>laſt miracles Chriſt wrought</hi> in his life time, faith was far to ſeek in the ſubject, <hi>Malchus, Joh.</hi> 18. 10. or in his <hi>kinsman,</hi> v. 26. See, <hi>Acts</hi> 28. 8. In ſeverall there was a fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going belief; not all.</p>
                     <p>That <hi>Chriſt ſaith, Thy faith hath made thee whole,</hi> we muſt underſtand, as we are ſaid to <hi>be justified by works, Iam. 2. 21. i. e.</hi> declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively, not inſtrumentally: <hi>Be it unto thee, according to thy faith, v.</hi> 29. is not, for, or by thy faith: Elſe the luſtre of miracles would have been divided. Saving faith was the end, not the meanes of miracles; not the ſeed, but the fruit.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="commentary">
                     <pb n="92" facs="tcp:115542:51"/>
                     <epigraph>
                        <bibl>Mat. 27. 37.</bibl>
                        <q>This is the King of the <hi>Jews.</hi>
                        </q>
                     </epigraph>
                     <p>IN the whole Volume of the <hi>N. T.</hi> nothing is more harmoniouſly recorded, by the <hi>four Evangeliſts;</hi> then the <hi>ſuper ſcription of the Croſſe of Christ:</hi> and yet not one of them lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terally agreeing with another: Some make a ſtrange paraphraſe upon it. My thoughts are, that the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> ſetteth down nothing <hi>a la vole,</hi> at random: but there is a reaſon of every <hi>iota</hi> in that incorruptible Syſtem: And he, fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeing that the Antichriſtian brood would idolize that title, <hi>[I. N. R. I.]</hi> hath on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe varied the expreſſion in the Elements, holding all to the ſame ſenſe: that ſo there might be no ground left, for the canonization of that deviſed <hi>tetragram.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The ſame prevention did <hi>God</hi> of old uſe with the <hi>Jews,</hi> in the <hi>ſecret burying of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of</hi> Moſes; which, if that people, prone to idolatry, had diſcovered; would have turned his tomb into ſuperſtition.</p>
                     <p>The like I conceive of the <hi>birth day of our Saviour.</hi> All the records we have, is, <hi>In the dayes of</hi> Herod: Whereas other acts, of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferior concernment, have the <hi>year of the reign of the King, the month and day</hi> regiſtred unto poſterity. This, me-thinketh, might in ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber-minded men, take off the edge, of that eager purſuit, in the celebration of the <hi>Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:115542:51"/>
of our Redeemer:</hi> Though the Grandees in Mathematicks, would have the conjunction of the eightht and ninth ſphere to have been that day, <hi>A. M.</hi> 3967; in ♈; yet, that this account doth differ, one, two, three, four, or more years, and upward, many grave Authors have probably concluded. Better is a modeſt ſitting down under a dutifull ignorance, than the extolling of an uncertain errour.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="commentary">
                     <epigraph>
                        <bibl>Mat. 27. 44.</bibl>
                        <q>The Theeves alſo, that were crucified with Him, caſt the ſame things in his teeth.</q>
                     </epigraph>
                     <p>IT is certain, by the harmony of the <hi>Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts,</hi> that one of theſe Sufferers was a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert; and, having faith in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> did rebuke his fellow. It is obvious for the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> to put a plurall for a ſingular, or the whole for a part: and <hi>vice verſà.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>In this there is ſomething more. The de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomination is from the moſt eminent: For this was a notorious valliane. His unbelief did overtop the remorſe of the believer; not in worth, but in degree.</p>
                     <p>Practically it denoteth the contagion of ſin: that a guiltleſſe perſon, in company, ſhould be branded, with the infamy of the malefactor. See, <hi>Joſh.</hi> 7. 11. <hi>Mat.</hi> 26. 8. Here it is a hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs to keep aloof.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="commentary">
                     <pb n="94" facs="tcp:115542:52"/>
                     <epigraph>
                        <bibl>Joh. 20. 17.</bibl>
                        <q>Ieſus ſaith unto her, Touch me not; for I am not yet aſcended to my Father.</q>
                     </epigraph>
                     <p>THeſe words do not import a naturall or moral abſurdity, of the touching of Chriſt. Not <hi>naturall;</hi> For, by his <hi>tangible quality,</hi> he proveth himſelf to be <hi>no ſpirit;</hi> Luke 24. 39. and layeth it in, againſt ſuſpicion of impoſture or deluſion. Nor <hi>morall,</hi> For <hi>he biddeth his diſciples handle and ſee him,</hi> both in a verſe; one ſenſe being as lawfull as the other; <hi>verſ.</hi> 27. <hi>He biddeth</hi> Thomas <hi>reach his finger, and his hand, and touching him thruſt it into his ſide.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>But knowing the ſtrength of <hi>Maries faith,</hi> he would have her live higher then ſenſe: On the other ſide, he did condeſcend to meet with the weakneſſe of <hi>Thomas's belief,</hi> and make his outward feeling, ſubſervient to the ſtrengthn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his inward faith.</p>
                     <p>As leight meat in a robuſt ſtomack, or ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger viands in a feeble body; both are ſubject to corruption: So doth our wiſe and indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent <hi>Houſhoulder,</hi> bring forth ſuitable diſhes of diſpenſations, according to every ones ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall diſgeſtion.</p>
                     <p>The hardeſt knot remaineth yet undiſſolved, <hi>viz.</hi> the coherence of the words; <hi>Why his not yet being aſcended, could be a reaſon of his inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, of her touching him?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="95" facs="tcp:115542:52"/>
My conjecture is, becauſe at heavens door, faith leaveth us; or rather is ſwallowed up, by the real fruition of that beatitude, which we in this life did but hope for. He bid her delay the higheſt degree of perfection, till they ſhould meet in heaven. It was enough here, that ſhe, by her worſhipping and <hi>Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boni-ing</hi> of him, did own his Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
                     <p>Though, to live by faith, doth argue more fortitude; yet to live by ſenſe, is more cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain and more happy: The former moſt fit for a <hi>Souldier Militant:</hi> the latter proper to a <hi>triumphant Victor.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Whereas it is ſaid, <hi>Faith is of things nor ſeen,</hi> ſight is not ſynecdochically taken for any ſenſe: It was a ſtrong evidence of her faith to believe not feeling; And thus ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded, it may be, unto her particular, a ſufficient reaſon of her interdiction. But from hence to derive a ſtanding rule, that <hi>Our Saviour's</hi> raiſed body was either <hi>Phyſical<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> or <hi>morally</hi> intangible; ſheweth a defect of naturall <hi>Logick.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="commentary">
                     <epigraph>
                        <bibl>1 Cor. 11. 7.</bibl>
                        <q>For a man indeed ought not to cover his head.</q>
                     </epigraph>
                     <p>THe ſenſeof this place, to us, is contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the Letter; which ſeemeth harſh to them, who being ſlaves to ſyllables,
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:115542:53"/>
do not conſider, the ſcope and place, where this was written. For the intention of <hi>Paul</hi> was, to <hi>preferre the man above the woman;</hi> the <hi>ſubjection of woman</hi> being ſignified by their <hi>covering;</hi> and that <hi>naturall,</hi> v. 15, [by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall muſt be meant, the cuſtome of the place, not an internall cauſe; for that is alſo common to a man: I queſtion not, but moſt males, would, <hi>Abſolon-like,</hi> if ſciffers were abandoned, vye with many women for length of hair,] as it was a token of <hi>ſuperiority,</hi> to be <hi>uncovered;</hi> which cuſtome pleaſeth ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall <hi>Nations,</hi> unto this day: In the <hi>Eaſtern</hi> Countries, a ſervant is not permitted, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter bare-headed into the preſence of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter: And the <hi>French Potestants</hi> do, upon the ſame ground, juſtifie their preaching, having their heads covered.</p>
                     <p>So ſome of <hi>Hipocrates Aphoriſms,</hi> though with them unfallible oracles, tranſplanted into our nations, by loſing their luſtre, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract a ſuſpectedneſſe: and, without ſubſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing to a <hi>Protagorean Sceptiſm,</hi> That which is true in one place, may be falſe in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="commentary">
                     <pb n="97" facs="tcp:115542:53"/>
                     <epigraph>
                        <bibl>1 Tim. 1. 8.</bibl>
                        <q>I was before a blaſphemer, and a perſecutor, and injurious; but I obtained mercy, becauſe I did it ignorantly, in unbelief.</q>
                     </epigraph>
                     <p>FRom hence moſt <hi>Divines</hi> conclude, <hi>Paul</hi> to have been an unbeliever; before <hi>Christ</hi> appeared unto him: yet this may be queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned. For he was <hi>zealous for the Jewiſh Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,</hi> not yet fully buried; <hi>brought up at the feet of Gamaliel;</hi> and according to the rule of charity (as we are, if judgment will permit, bound to conſtrue all things, in the moſt fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable ſenſe) he did truſt in the <hi>ſeed of the woman, Shiloh,</hi> the <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> the <hi>individuum va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gum;</hi> though, through ignorance, he wot it not to be the <hi>Son of Mary.</hi> Elſe I know not how to conſtrue, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 3. And, <hi>Acts 23. 1. I thank God whom I ſerve from my forefathers, with a good conſcience.</hi> I doubt not but the <hi>Eunuch, Acts</hi> 8. before <hi>Jeſus</hi> was preached unto him by <hi>Philip,</hi> was a believer. <hi>Apollo</hi> no leſſe; <hi>Acts</hi> 18. Converſion after conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, you find in as eminent an <hi>Apoſtle, Luk.</hi> 22. 32. <hi>Mat.</hi> 18. 3. I know that the habits of all graces are infuſed together; yet the emanation of them by degrees, in <hi>Scripture<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>idiom</hi> is a new converſion; or converſion re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed, as well in the extenſe, as in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſe.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="98" facs="tcp:115542:54"/>
Finally, for in-meaſure, they were his own aggravating depreſſing words, to extoll Free-Grace the higher.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="commentary">
                     <epigraph>
                        <bibl>Heb. 12. 24.</bibl>
                        <q>The Blood of ſprinckling, ſpeaking better things then that of <hi>Abel.</hi>
                        </q>
                     </epigraph>
                     <p>OUr general Tranſlation is, <hi>then the Blood of</hi> Abel: I ſhould rather read it, <hi>then Abel,</hi> 
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>: but I find the Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals to differ.</p>
                     <p>The Queſtion is concerning the ſenſe, which will carry it probably, againſt the ſtream of former Commentators; better for the <hi>active</hi> effuſion of the Blood of Sacrifice, then for the <hi>paſſive</hi> blood of Martyrdom, which he ſuffered.</p>
                     <p>For the ſcope of the whole Chapter, yea Book, is, to compare the <hi>Priesthood</hi> of old, and their <hi>Sacrifices,</hi> with that of <hi>Chriſts,</hi> ſhewing the tranſcendency of the latter beyond the former. Now, to bring in the Blood of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrdom, and compare it with the Blood of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices, is an infringing of the Rule of Reaſon: <hi>Comparata debent eſſe ſub eodem, quantum fieri poteſt proximo, genere.</hi> It's more rational to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the firſt acceptable Sacrifice, ſet down by <hi>Moſes,</hi> with the laſt of <hi>Chriſts:</hi> Or rather the Type, <hi>Abel's offering the firſt-fruit of his Flock,</hi> with the Antitype, <hi>Chriſt's</hi> offering the laſt fruit of his obedience.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="99" facs="tcp:115542:54"/>
It hath a reference unto <hi>Gen.</hi> 4. 10. <hi>Thy Brother's blood cryeth.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>That word <hi>cryeth</hi> 
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, ſignifieth ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a preſent miſery, or denuntiation of fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Judgment: But <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, <hi>[ſpeaketh]</hi> is of a ſoft and ſtill nature. As in our, ſo in al-Languages, there is a palpable difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Vociferation, and Speaking. I adde <hi>Chap.</hi> 11. <hi>ver.</hi> 14. of this Book, <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, where the ſame word is uſed, may better have reference unto <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, then unto <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>; becauſe Relatives reſpect ordinarily, the immediate antecedent: So that the ſenſe ſhould be; and <hi>by that, i. e.</hi> his <hi>Sacrifice,</hi> He, <hi>being dead, yet ſpeaketh;</hi> which concenteth with the Expoſition of the former Text.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="commentary">
                     <epigraph>
                        <bibl>1 Pet. 3. 19.</bibl>
                        <q>By which alſo he went, and preached to Spirits in Priſon.</q>
                     </epigraph>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, <hi>Being ſent,</hi> which agreeth beſt, both with word and ſenſe: I ſee not how this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth, <hi>Chriſt's deſcent into Hell,</hi> any ways: nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Soul nor Body; but onely, that <hi>he was preached by his Spirit,</hi> by which <hi>He was quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned from the Dead,</hi> ver. 18. whereunto this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lative <hi>[which]</hi> doth look; unto the <hi>Generation of Noah that are now in Priſon.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Concerning that Article, <hi>Deſcended into Hell,</hi> though great Volumes have been writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten about it: yet, with me, the uncertainty of
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:115542:55"/>
the Author, (not the <hi>Amanuenſis,</hi> elſe I muſt queſtion the <hi>Authority</hi> of the <hi>Acts of the Apostles,</hi> of the <hi>Epistle to the Hebrews<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </hi> and in the <hi>Old Teſtament</hi> more) of the <hi>Symbole,</hi> doth juſtly ſlack the eager enquiry into its truth. Onely we find it firſt in the <hi>Syriack</hi> Tongue; and many of the <hi>Eaſtern</hi> Churche, either by negligence loſt this Article, or elſe on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe left it out: which latter, becauſe of its Senſes ambiguity, I am prone to embrace. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verally it is expounded, and few agree, which I will not mention. What I have beaten out upon the Anvile of mine own Conceptions, you ſhall have.</p>
                     <p>Firſt, that, in a publick <hi>Epitome</hi> of our Faith, ſhould be neither Tautology, nor defect, not a prepoſterous order; I think none will deny: Of each, a word.</p>
                     <p>If for <hi>Hell</hi> you take the <hi>Grave,</hi> as it is fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent with the Originals, then is it a vain re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petition; his <hi>Burying</hi> before included ſo much.</p>
                     <p>If you will have it the <hi>Paſſion of Hell fire, i. e.</hi> the wrath of his <hi>Father,</hi> for all the ſins of the world, it muſt precede his Death: here would be an abſurd prepoſterouſneſs: For no paſſion after the <hi>conſummatum est.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>If for local or vertual deſcent, it is either a part of his exaltation, or humiliation: Not the latter; for it is not by us imitable, as all his ſufferings, (Miracles excepted) ſince his Incarnation, ſtand as well for our Enſamples, at leaſt habitually, as for our comfort: But in
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:115542:55"/>
this, none, I hope, mean to tread in his ſteps. If, as a part of his exaltation; it muſt be, either in his Body, or in his Soul, or according to his Deity. Not according to the laſt; for that was Omnipreſent: Neither according to the firſt; for then could he not be <hi>in the grave, three dayes and three nights:</hi> nor in his Soul; for <hi>that he recommended into his Fathers hands,</hi> concording with his Promiſe, made to the Thief, <hi>This day thou ſhalt be with me in Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>What ſome imagine, that this ſhould be an <hi>Exegetick</hi> Explanation of the fore-going <hi>Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial,</hi> is inconſiſtent with ſound reaſon: ſince every Expoſition ought by right, to be clearer then the precedent ſubject.</p>
                     <p>The whole Earth, indeed, in regard as well of its dignity, as diſtance, may, in reſpect of Heaven, be called <hi>Hell,</hi> or <hi>Inferi:</hi> from whence deſcending, to re-aſſume his Body, this Article, if it had any fore going Type, or Promiſe, might be expounded.</p>
                     <p>It is the dulleſt and ſordidſt piece of <hi>Pedan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try,</hi> to an ingenuous Spirit, to believe, with the Catholicks, what the Church believeth, and to be ignorant of the thing believed.</p>
                     <p>It remaineth then, to know what to hold to, (if I give ſomething more then humane credit to this Article) that his <hi>three dayes and nights resting in the Grave;</hi> oppoſite whereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to is <hi>his ſitting at the right hand of his Father,</hi> which <hi>Prophets</hi> fore-told, and he himſelf had gloried in, <hi>Joh.</hi> 2. 19. <hi>Deſtroy this Temple, and
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:115542:56"/>
in three dayes I will raiſe it up again:</hi> his fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runner being <hi>Jonas in the Whales belly,</hi> is not mentioned in the Symbole; except you have it here: And all that while, being in the Bonds of Satan, was a furder humiliation, than to go to Priſon, and preſently be let out again. Thus, with much ado, it will make a proper Article in its due rank; and ſo I can make ſhift to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, that <hi>Chriſt deſcended into Hell.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>A ſtep or two out of the Road, concerning the <hi>Syſteme of the Apostles Creed,</hi> where I obſerve ſome things inſerted, not abſolutely neceſſary to the ſubſtance of our Belief; <hi>as his ſuffering under</hi> Pontius Pilate, <hi>the Catholick Church,</hi> there being thouſands now in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, paſt all Believing, which were here alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether ignorant of theſe points. Some things muſt be taken warily, with a great caution, as that the <hi>Father</hi> was the <hi>Creatour of Heaven and Earth;</hi> whereas it is aſcribed alſo unto the Son, <hi>Joh.</hi> 1. 3. <hi>Col.</hi> 1. 16. and to the Spirit, <hi>Iob</hi> 33. 4. according to the true and common rule in Divinity, That all the Works, <hi>ad extra,</hi> are indiviſible.</p>
                     <p>But a greater over-ſight there is, in the omiſſion of two principal Heads, the <hi>Baſis</hi> of all our comfort.</p>
                     <p n="1">1 No mention there is of his <hi>actual obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> by which he purchaſed Eternal Bliſs for us: as by His Paſſion, He freed us from the wrath of His <hi>Father.</hi> For they are in an error, who deny any fruit to redound to us, by the perfection of His Works: becauſe, ſay they,
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:115542:56"/>
He being made <hi>Man,</hi> was, by it, <hi>ſubject to the Law;</hi> forgetting that He put on Humanity, for our, not His own ſake. <hi>Et quicquid eſt cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa cauſae,</hi> &amp;c. If for us He became Man, He did alſo for us fulfill the Law.</p>
                     <p n="2">2 His <hi>Interceſſion,</hi> by which our Perſons and Prayers are made acceptable to Him, that ſitteth on the Throne, is altogether for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten. Without the apprehenſion of either of theſe, a Soul ſhall find but ſmall ſolace in the higheſt pitch of his own performances, and ſlow Returns of his humbleſt Addreſſes.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="commentary">
                     <epigraph>
                        <bibl>Rev. 12. 11.</bibl>
                        <q>The Woman having the Moon under her feet.</q>
                     </epigraph>
                     <p>THis is generally expounded of the <hi>Church</hi> trampling upon ſublunary and unconſtant things. Later Writers take it for the <hi>Church under the Goſpel,</hi> which is promoted a form higher, than the School of the <hi>Law,</hi> that is, then the <hi>Jewiſh Ceremonies,</hi> and <hi>Festivals,</hi> which were commonly regulated by the courſe of the <hi>Moon.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>None of theſe Expoſitions are Heterodox, or ſtrangers from the Text, but may have their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundary place, ſtill reſerving the moſt honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Seat, for the principal firſt-born ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
                     <p>The moſt genuine ſenſe to me, is, (if a ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Fore-head may have a place, among more
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:115542:57"/>
compoſed Brows) to ſynchronize with the Hiſtory of that time wherein <hi>John</hi> lived, to ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie the <hi>Churches treading down all Idolatry,</hi> which was generally all <hi>Aſia</hi> over, to <hi>Diana</hi> of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> whoſe Embleme among the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then the <hi>Moon Creſcent</hi> was, and is given in the Arms, unto this day, of the moſt puiſſant <hi>Idolater</hi> of the whole Earth; An encouraging <hi>Omen</hi> for all Chriſtians, to wage War with the <hi>Grand Turk.</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Aquilae augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>Though they had other ſeveral Gods, yet this, exceeding in Univerſality and Magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence, is, Synecdochically, put for all the reſt.</p>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:115542:57" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>A Calm Ventilation, OF <hi>Pſeudodoxia Epidemica;</hi> OR, Doctrine of Vulgar Errours, Set forth by the hand of the moſt ſedulous <hi>THOMAS BROWN,</hi> Dr. in Phyſick, <hi>By the ſtill</hi> GALE OF <hi>JOHN ROBINSON,</hi> His Fellow-Citizen and Collegian.</p>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Pro captu Lectoris, habent ſua fata libelli.</hi>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. Streater,</hi> for <hi>Francis Titon,</hi> at the three Daggers in <hi>Fleet-ſtreet,</hi> 1658.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="table_of_contents">
                  <pb facs="tcp:115542:58"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:115542:58"/>
                  <head>The Contents.</head>
                  <list>
                     <head>
                        <hi>BOOK</hi> 1.</head>
                     <item>
                        <hi>CHap.</hi> 1. In the firſt Fall, whether the ſtronger were deceived by the weaker? 113</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Chap.</hi> 2. Whether <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve</hi> were the greateſt ſinners? 114</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Ibid.</hi> Whether Satan tempting, knew Chriſt's Deity? <hi>Ib.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Ibid.</hi> Whether the Devil's Deſpair be ſin? <hi>Ib.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Chap.</hi> 3. Errour defined. 115</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Ibid.</hi> Whether all things be known by their cauſes? <hi>Ib.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Ibid.</hi> Whether the <hi>Egyptian</hi> Ear-rings were ſtoln? 116</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Chap.</hi> 4. Of <hi>Pythagoras</hi>'s Bean. 117</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Chap.</hi> 6. Whether whole Nations be indiſpoſed to Learning? <hi>Ib.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>BOOK II.</head>
                     <item>
                        <hi>CHap.</hi> 1. Of warmth of Springs. 120</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Ibid.</hi> Of freezing of Eggs. <hi>Ib.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <pb facs="tcp:115542:59"/>
Of the Spirit of cold. <hi>Ib.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Whether ſparks be the accenſion of Air? 121</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Chap.</hi> 2. Of the variation of the Needle by ſubmarine Earth. <hi>Ib.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Of its reſt in the midſt of Water. <hi>Ib.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Chap.</hi> 3. Of the Terreſtrial Pole. 122</item>
                     <item>Of the Wound-Salve. <hi>Ib.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Of revealing of Secrets. <hi>Ib.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Chap.</hi> 4. Of Electricks. 123</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Chap.</hi> 5. Of <hi>Daniel,</hi> and the Dragon. 124</item>
                     <item>Of boiled Gold. 125</item>
                     <item>Of Coral. <hi>Ib.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Chap.</hi> 6. Of Generation by Putrefaction. 126</item>
                     <item>Of Cloves. <hi>Ib.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Chap.</hi> 7. Of Cats. 127</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>BOOK 3.</head>
                     <item>
                        <hi>CHap.</hi> 1. Of Elephants. 128</item>
                     <item>Of the ſite of <hi>Muſculs,</hi> 129</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Chap.</hi> 2. Of Horſes dunging. <hi>Ib.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Chap.</hi> 9. Whether propagation be from every part? <hi>Ib.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Chap.</hi> 12. Of the Soul of <hi>Adam</hi>'s Rib. <hi>Ib.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Chap.</hi> 13. Of Frogs. 130</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Chap.</hi> 16. Of Vipers. <hi>Ib.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Chap.</hi> 17. Of Silk-Worms. <hi>Ib.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Chap.</hi> 18. Of Moles. <hi>Ib.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Chap.</hi> 21. Of the uſe of Noſtrils. 131</item>
                     <item>Of Aliments taſte. <hi>Ib.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Chap.</hi> 22. Of Chilification. 132</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Chap.</hi> 23. Of Unicorn. <hi>Ib.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <pb facs="tcp:115542:59"/>
                        <hi>Chap.</hi> 24. Whether Terreſtrial Creatures were firſt named? 133</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Chap.</hi> 26. Of the Glo-Worm. <hi>Id.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Of the Pigmire. <hi>Ib.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Of ſinging of Birds. 134</item>
                     <item>Of the Spider and Toad. <hi>Ib.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Chap.</hi> 27. Of the yellowneſs of the Stomach. 235</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>BOOK IV.</head>
                     <item>
                        <hi>CHap.</hi> 1. Whether Man alone ſit? 136</item>
                     <item>Of the Generation of Males. <hi>Ib.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Chap.</hi> 6. Of Fat floating. 137</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Chap.</hi> 7. Of the weight of a Blown-Blather. <hi>Ib.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Chap.</hi> 10. Of the cauſe of the Pox. 138</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Chap.</hi> 12. Of time. <hi>Ib.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Chap.</hi> 13. Of the Dogg-ſtars riſing. 139</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>BOOK V.</head>
                     <item>
                        <hi>CHap.</hi> 4. Whether any thing in Paradiſe were hurtful? 140</item>
                     <item>Whether <hi>Eve</hi> could kill her Husband? <hi>Ib.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Chap.</hi> 5. Of <hi>Adam</hi>'s Navel. 141</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Chap.</hi> 6. Of the Jews Ceremonies. 142</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Chap.</hi> 14. Of <hi>Jephthe.</hi> 143</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Chap.</hi> 19. Of Long-tail'd Bears. <hi>Ib.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Chap.</hi> 21. Of ſitting croſs-leg'd. <hi>Ib.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Chap.</hi> 22. Of Palmeſtry. 144</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <pb facs="tcp:115542:60"/>
                     <head>BOOK VI.</head>
                     <item>
                        <hi>CHap.</hi> 2. The World created in Autumn. 145</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Chap.</hi> 5. Of the motion of the Sun in the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quator. <hi>Ib.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Chap.</hi> 7. In Paradiſe were the principles of all things. 146</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Ibid.</hi> Of the advantage of the Eaſt. <hi>Ib.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Chap.</hi> 10. Of the <hi>Mores</hi> blackneſs. 147</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Ibid.</hi> Of Sight. <hi>Ib.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Chap.</hi> 11. Of cold fire. <hi>Ib.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>BOOK VII.</head>
                     <item>
                        <hi>CHap.</hi> 1. Of the forbidden Fruit. 148</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Ibid.</hi> Of the word <hi>Pomum. Ib.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Chap.</hi> 4. Of the Rain-bow. 149</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Chap.</hi> 5. The Printers faults. <hi>Ib.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Chap.</hi> 7. The ancient Hyſſop. <hi>Ib.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Chap.</hi> 13. Whether the Moon be the cauſe of flowing and ebbing. <hi>Ib.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Chap.</hi> 17. Of Poiſons. 150</item>
                  </list>
               </div>
               <div type="preface">
                  <pb facs="tcp:115542:60"/>
                  <head>Preface.</head>
                  <p>THE enchaining of Knowledge, within the Fetters of Humane Authority, ſurpaſſeth the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Thraldom. Set the underſtanding free and diſ-ingaged from the uſurpation and ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny of precedent opinion, it will ſore into a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rene height. Nay, as further diſquiſition and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience of man doth promote clearneſs of mind; ſo is it no ſhame, upon ſecond review, to lay <hi>Batte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> to ones own former weakneſs; and, upon the <hi>demantling</hi> of it, to caſt up a ſtronger <hi>Breaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>work;</hi> ſtill allowing the full weight of reverence unto Antiquity if it be right.</p>
                  <p>This candor I have found in my honoured <hi>Friend</hi> and <hi>Author;</hi> who, in his maturer years, is willing to rectifie, what himſelf, and others, in their younger days, were falſly ſeaſoned withall. It is the freedom, beſides, of a <hi>Philoſopher,</hi> to cite any thing doubtful and ſuſpicious to the Aſſizes of <hi>Rational Inquiſition.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>There need but little care concerning the choice of a Language: For I am ſure, whoſe art cannot afford him more Tongues, then Nature doth Eyes, he will never attain, to the full under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing of <hi>his elaborated exercitations:</hi> which, I confeſs, require a more ſubtile <hi>Reader</hi> and <hi>Judge,</hi> then my ſelf; my cold Brain would Snail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like be contented to cozen the Winter with a three
<pb facs="tcp:115542:61"/>
Moneths ſleep. But zeal unto truth the ſpark of labour, hath almoſt awakened me from my won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted drow ſineſs: not that I deſire to reciprocate the Saw of Contention.</p>
                  <p>Here I do but more regularly examine, what we have in private, without infringing the limits of Amity more looſely diſcuſſed: We both being loyal Subjects to Truth, agreeing on that third, cannot diſagree from our ſelves, nor from any that ſubſcribeth with me, to be</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Her faithful Follower, John Robinſon.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div n="1" type="book">
                  <pb n="113" facs="tcp:115542:61"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>BOOK.</hi> I.</head>
                  <p>CHap. 1. <hi>In the firſt fall the ſtrongeſt was not deceived by the weakeſt:</hi> For <hi>Satan in the Serpent,</hi> as being created a Sphere higher then man, was the ſtronger: We muſt not think that the edg of his intellect was dulled by ſin: this line not being defective in length, but ſtraight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: Neither are a regenerate man's thoughts ſubtiler, but ſublimer. The experience of <hi>Eves ſenſe, v. z.</hi> not dying immediatly, did give the foil to her <hi>husbands faith.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Ib. <hi>Whether were</hi> Adam <hi>and</hi> Eve <hi>the greateſt ſinners in the world?</hi> If the <hi>world</hi> be taken for the whole <hi>Univerſe,</hi> it comprehendeth the <hi>Angels,</hi> which ſinned from inward principles, and that irrecoverably: Neither of which is quadrating with the fall of man. But take the world ſtricter, for Mankind; certainly they eſcaped the experience of the fruit of ſin, which is its aggravation; nor were warned by the examples of others. Neither ſinned they againſt Evangelical mercie; nor that pardon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs ſin, the remiſſion whereof we may not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>precate. Their ſin, indeed, was, by contagion, the greateſt, <hi>extenſivè,</hi> as being the ſource of all; not in their perſons, <hi>intenſivè.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="114" facs="tcp:115542:62"/>
Ch. 2. <hi>That Satan knew the Deity of Chriſt at his temptation,</hi> I would rather incline to believe: he having ſeen the compleating of all the prophecies: not being ignorant, at <hi>his conception of the congratulation of his Mother:</hi> at <hi>the birth of the hymn of Angels, and the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of ſhepherds; and at his baptiſm ſeeing the Dove and hearing the witneſs, both of heaven and earth, God and John.</hi> Add unto theſe, their number and nimbleneſs of communication; he himſelf is afterward brought in, to give a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile or extorted teſtimony of his <hi>Deity. Luke</hi> 4. 41. Either when the weaker was overcome by the ſtronger: or, that with more eaſe he might delude, when he ſhould be called, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooth, a <hi>Chriſtian.</hi> Neither is it ſafe to exte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuate his ſin, or to be his <hi>Advocate</hi> in pleading his ignorance.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ib.</hi> I think it <hi>a ſin in Devils to deſpair:</hi> the like I hold of <hi>reprobates;</hi> I mean of the ſame <hi>Oeconomy.</hi> If you object, they have no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement or overture to hope; I anſwer, they had a commandement: The former, to truſt Gods mercy, in the confirmation of their eſtate. The other, have had, if not Evangelical faith, at leaſt the <hi>Law of Nature,</hi> which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ill imployed, God juſtly denyeth them hope of grace, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. 21. Beſides, as their a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilities, are uncapable, ſo is their will averſe: the continuation whereof doth juſtly eternize their exile. Neither can I condemn their opinion, who make the linked chain of their continued crimes the reaſon of the perpetua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:115542:62"/>
of the wrath of their <hi>Judge.</hi> For if after the day of Judgment, the Mediatorſhip of <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſhall ceaſe, (as the Schools teach) and the perputuation of bliſs is <hi>Angel-like,</hi> by a congruity of holyneſs; then, by analogy, the duration of puniſhment, doth anſwer their everlaſting unbelief. Nor muſt we think that obdurate ſouls, in that fire, are melted into remorſe, or ſoftned into repentance.</p>
                  <p>Ch. 3. <hi>Error is defined a firm aſſent unto fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity.</hi> The underſtanding often ſuſpendeth its judgment, concerning the truth of an aſſerti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: And ſo the <hi>Author</hi> himſelf, with moſt wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer men, doth acquieſce frequently in a <hi>ſcepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal</hi> likelihood and probability. Sometime there is an inclination rather unto this ſide, than the other; which is an <hi>Opinion.</hi> In all theſe there may be one or more falſities. A determination is not alwaies requiſite, to the compleating of an errour. Beſides, there is one falſhood in notion, another in the ſpeech: this is an incongruity to the heart; that to the thing. All lies are Errours; yet ſome without the ſuffrage of the mind. Finally, Oblivion it ſelf is a lie, for either it is of things paſt, or to come: the forgetting either <note place="margin">Ab oblivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muntur im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſibilia, illicita, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinentia.</note> of them, is a denying either of what hath been or ſhould be, and yet without any <hi>firm con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Ib. <hi>That nothing is truly known but by its cauſes,</hi> though <hi>Ariſtotle's</hi> ſeemeth too general an enuntiation. In tranſnatural things, the
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:115542:63"/>
                     <hi>Trinity, Election, Reſurrection, &amp;c.</hi> We muſt truſt to bare authority; without ſearching cauſes. Properly, I belive no more then I know: See <hi>Job</hi> 19. 25. Yea, in Phyſical <note place="margin">Ne credas quod neſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as.</note> things, cannot comprehend the formal cauſes, why fire burneth; the Load-ſtone or <hi>Carabe</hi> attracteth: It is well we know them <hi>à poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riore.</hi> To <hi>reduce the difference of individuals to a manifeſt cauſe were a fruitleſs labour.</hi> See <hi>chap.</hi> 10. of this his <hi>Book.</hi> To ſpeak truly, as ſenſe is dazled at the exceſs of objects, or puzled at the exiguity of particular moats: ſo the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding cannot attain to the higheſt cauſe, becauſe of It's tranſcendency; Nor the low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt atomes of individuality, becauſe of its re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuity. To be contented with the ignorance of ſome things, is a part of modeſt wiſdom. <note place="margin">Scaliger,</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ib.</hi> It is too uncharitable a thought, <hi>that the ear-rings of the Egyptians were ſtoln.</hi> For by <hi>Gods Expreſs</hi> they were borrowed; in which ſole reaſon, moſt acquieſce: But to flee to an exorbitant precept, when firm and ſolid ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments may be drawn from a ſtanding rule, is a mark of a weak and ſhallow judgment. Upon demand, they were ready to reſtore them again: But when they were purſued for their lives, what ſhould they have done with them? In a diſtinct order to return every one their own, they had no poſſibility: to throw them down promiſcuouſly, would not have been ſatisfactory to the particular borrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="117" facs="tcp:115542:63"/>
Moreover, in equity there was as much due unto them in arrearage, for their <hi>ſaper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerary brick:</hi> in the <hi>Chancery of Alexander the Great:</hi> Since this <hi>Pharaoh</hi> would not ſtand to the pact, made with <hi>Joſeph</hi> for his <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers family.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Withour making God acceſſary to it, I ſee not how it can be regiſtred among the great benefits beſtowed upon them, <hi>Pſa,</hi> 105. 37. <hi>He brought them forth with ſilver and gold,</hi> foretold <hi>Gen.</hi> 15. 14. which, without angaria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or a preſs, cannot but have reference to theſe <hi>medals:</hi> And to liſt their felonious riches, within the Catalogue of God's mercies, in my ears, ſoundeth harſh.</p>
                  <p>Ch. 4. <hi>Pythagoras's bean</hi> may elegantly <hi>prohibit Venery:</hi> Since in it, at the ſeveral ends, there are the manifeſt ſignatures of the Genitals in both Sexes. Our Maſters teach us, that all <hi>leguminaes</hi> or pulſe, as alſo bulbous roots, do, by their flatulency, blow up this ſpark of <hi>Venus.</hi> Neither do I, hereby, aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don its uſe, in <hi>Political ſuffrages.</hi> Nor was <hi>Pythagoras's Genius</hi> altogether a ſtranger to theſe abſtruſe Characters.</p>
                  <p>Ch. 6. <hi>If there be ſome whole Nations indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoſed unto learning</hi> it dependeth either upon a Celeſtial or Tereſtial Cauſe: Not Celeſtial, for every thouſand years, the Longitude chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth its ſituation, above five degrees; which, in this caſe, is of ſome moment: ſo that the Land, which in the Creation, lay under the middle of <hi>Aries</hi> is now ruled by the influence, to phraſe it with them of <hi>Taurus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="118" facs="tcp:115542:64"/>
But, what will the <hi>Astrologers</hi> ſay, to ſee ſo continued a malignity of Aſpects; that none ſhould have ☿ or ♃ <hi>Aſcendent</hi> in their <hi>Nativi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty?</hi> Never a <hi>Promiſſor</hi> or <hi>Significator</hi> ſtrong or ſure enough for to cauſe a benevolent inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion?</p>
                  <p>If terreſtrial, it is either external or inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal: not the former, as <hi>air, water, diet, &amp;c.</hi> for often Nature, alwaies Art, can correct thoſe: by which Moors and Boggs are turned into fragrant Meadows. If internal, either the unaptneſs is of the Souls part, or of the Bodies. Not the ſouls, for all mens Souls are alwaies alike; though their emaning beams be either brighter or duller, according to the clearneſs or dimneſs of the Lanthorn of the organized body. If on the body's ſide, that might have a medical hand: yea many times in individuals, one diſeaſe, by accident, becometh the cure of another: And I ſee not but one <hi>Epidemical</hi> diſtemper might remedy an <hi>Endemical</hi> malady. The <hi>Plague</hi> of the <hi>Ek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronites</hi> is a preſervation and cure of a <hi>maniack paſſion:</hi> ſemblable to which are many occur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences <note place="margin">Barclay,</note> in quotidian practiſe.</p>
                  <p>Further, it is obſerved by rational <hi>Hiſtori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> that, after revolutions of a few Centuries, learning taketh its tranſmigration: ſo that thoſe people, which about <hi>Chriſt's time,</hi> were, for humane letters, the only <hi>mirror</hi> of the world, did, not long after, and now are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the moſt <hi>Boetiſh</hi> of the whole earth; <hi>et vice versa.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="119" facs="tcp:115542:64"/>
The like doom is befaln unto Chriſtianity: <hi>Canaan</hi> and <hi>Jury</hi> is degenerated into <hi>Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſm;</hi> The <hi>ſeven Churches of Aſia</hi> unto <hi>Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſm:</hi> We, the untamed <hi>Weſt,</hi> are grown up more then into civility.</p>
                  <p>As for the <hi>Genius</hi> of <hi>man,</hi> I take it not to be <hi>connate;</hi> but a reteined propenſion to obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved and approved paſſages, an inclinable and ready way to a habit. The <hi>Demones of Plato,</hi> appropriated to every Countrey, are incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting with the profeſſion of <hi>Goſpel-light.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="book">
                  <pb n="120" facs="tcp:115542:65"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>BOOK</hi> II.</head>
                  <p>CHap. 1. <hi>That many ſprings do not freez,</hi> their motion may be one cauſe: which is ſwifter, at their narrow eruption, then at their enlarged diffuſion. A violent motion of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, is a preſervative againſt glaciation; yet doth not altogether prohibit it: Drops ſquee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed from the clouds, in their ſwifteſt fall, are precipitated into frozen hail-ſtones. Moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, many ſprings have a ſenſible warmth, at their firſt ebullition, whoſe refrigeratedſtreams are ſubject to the chains of congelation.</p>
                  <p>Ib. <hi>Eggs will freeze in the albuginous parts.</hi> That point in the <hi>Chalaza,</hi> the ſpark of viviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, I wiſh it might freez; it would rid my trees from Caterpillers, which continue their noxious <hi>ſpecies,</hi> by their hybernating <hi>Eggs.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Ib. <hi>Salt peter doth excite the ſpirit of cold.</hi> So doth Sugar decayed Muſtard: which for affinity of elements in the letter, and aliment in the platter, I merrily uſe to call in Latine <hi>Sal-charum.</hi> This ſpirit is manifeſt in ſnow; where, if, by the clemency of the air, it be lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurely diſſolved, the ſpirit fixed will preſerve it from putrefaction: whereas, if by fire, you ſuddenly put it to flight, a ſtrange heir, making an unlawful entry, doth, with a debauchment of its new inheritance, haſten its corruption.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="121" facs="tcp:115542:65"/>
Ib. If <hi>Scintillations are not the accenſions of the aire, upon the colliſion of two hard bodies,</hi> what inflammable effluence is there in ſand, or a wet grind-ſtone? yea, I have ſeen a horſe in the rain, ſtrike fire on the flint. Chalk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coale blown maketh a flame, yet no more ſmoak then in kindled iron or ſtone.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Chap.</hi> 2. What <hi>Kircherus</hi> obſerveth, that <hi>the ſubmarine earth doth cauſe the variation of the needle,</hi> is not to be ſwallowed without chewing: For the Load-ſtone doth not ſo free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſend forth its <hi>effluviums,</hi> through heteroge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neall <hi>mediums,</hi> eſpecially an Iron plate; this experiment will illuſtrate it.</p>
                  <p>Put a needle into a beer-glaſſe, half full of water: hold a vigorous load-ſtone at the edge of the glaſſe; the drowſy needle lyeth <hi>dor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant:</hi> Fill the glaſſe up to the brimme; which touch with the ſtone; the awakened needle, with joy, leapeth towards its allicient: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, that the heavier the <hi>medium</hi> is, the drowned body is the lighter; as in the weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of anchor, or drawing up of a bucket, every inferiour hand can witneſſe, [in quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilver it is moſt evident] the <hi>effluvium</hi> of the load-ſtone, if it be not contiguous with the water, doth upon its <hi>ſuperficies,</hi> ſuffer a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flexion; and by that meanes is debilitated. The ſureſt way were, to lay a needle upon the ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face of the Sea it ſelf.</p>
                  <p>Ib. <hi>A needle run through corck, may ſwim in the midſt of the water, and not ſinck.</hi> It <hi>he</hi> ſpeak of liquours heterogeneall, it is a thing
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:115542:66"/>
ſo vulgar, that it falleth below the worth of his diſquiſition, who breatheth nothing but excellencies. If it be underſtood of homo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generall liquours, that, by its gravity, it ſhould be permanent in the midſt, the rule of moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on proveth it falſe; for the ſelf ſame weight, that brought it to the midſt, will depreſſe it to the bottome; <hi>ſi catera ſint pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>One thing may be tryed, by the brain ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then the hand. If you have a body equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>librous with the water, it may be thruſt, but will never ſinck into the middle: But to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt this, becauſe the upholding ſubſtance, whether wood or Cork, inebriated with the <note place="margin">Dal detto al fatto, vi è un gran tratto.</note> liquour, loſeth the memory of its propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, I have no minde to try.</p>
                  <p>Chap. 3. <hi>From the non-variation of the needle, in the Ile of</hi> Elba, <hi>in the Tuſcan-Sea,</hi> is no <hi>firm argument againſt the terreſtriall pole.</hi> For all magnetick bodies, have their attraction and variations more ſtrenuous about the pole; then towards their <hi>Aequator;</hi> whereunto this place is inclining.</p>
                  <p>Ib. The <hi>Sympatheticall Vnguent</hi> may beſt be refuted, by daring, [neither is there great for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude or patience required hereunto] to fire and quench the inſtrument wounding, or any thing folded therein. For theſe ſublime <hi>Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgeons</hi> do give out, that a cloath or ſtick dipt in the wound or ulcer, and that refreſhed by their <hi>panacean Balſam,</hi> will ſolace and heal the part affected; if kept from extremity
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:115542:66"/>
of weather: otherwiſe it proveth painfull and noxious. Let the ſame jury of experience try the <hi>calcined,</hi> and, in praiſe, <hi>ſublimed vitriol.</hi> If kept from extremity of weather; otherwiſe it proveth prejudiciall and noxious: let it either help or hurt, or be an Idol, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 41. 23.</p>
                  <p>Ib. <hi>To diſcover to another in a ſeverall room my intention,</hi> may eaſier and ſurer be done, with the hand alone; then to rely upon the uncertainty of the dubious <hi>load-ſtone. Fruſtra fit per plura,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Chap. 4. Neither <hi>Cabaeus gyration of atomes,</hi> nor Sr. <hi>Kellem Digby's ſyrop-like con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction into a rope,</hi> can handſomely ſtand be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the leaſt gale of winde, in <hi>Electrick bodies, drawing up feſtuceous fragments:</hi> For, by a ſmall breath, both their ways are overturned: Neither would the body attracted riſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendicularly; but, by an oblique angle, miſſe the middle of the <hi>Electrum:</hi> The <hi>contact us</hi> being leſſe virtuall, and more groſſe, then that of the load-ſtone.</p>
                  <p>Three things I obſerve, 1. That theſe bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes are attractive, though but weakly, not being excited by heat: which hath alſo not eſcaped the induſtry of our <hi>Author.</hi> 2. That, upon a ſuddain approach of the warmed <hi>Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrick,</hi> the ſtramineous bodies will, at firſt, a little recede. 3. That, where the rever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beration of the <hi>effluvium</hi> is ſtronger, [as it is on a looking-glaſſe, beyond on carminated wooll; becauſe of its polilſhed <hi>ſuperficies,</hi> the
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:115542:67"/>
points are more compact, and at equaller diſtance; It's concavity doth alſo promote the attraction, as it's convexity, though reſting on fewer points, doth retard it] there is the love hotter; which giveth a hint to a true cauſe. But the reaſon, and ſuperſtructure thereon, is not for this place.</p>
                  <p>Chap. 5. To ſhore up the eſteem of the <hi>Apocrypha,</hi> like an old houſe, it calleth for many ſupporting props: If <hi>Daniel</hi> had the <hi>Dragon</hi> at that command, to <hi>put his im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mune hand into his throat;</hi> he, upon delibera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as this exploit was, had, (bearing <hi>ſword</hi> or <hi>ſtaffe,)</hi> twenty opportunities of victory, both ſurer and readier then this. The ſame <hi>Canon,</hi> that bindeth <hi>Phyſicians</hi> in the cure of a diſeaſe, that it be <hi>citò</hi> and <hi>tutò;</hi> the ſame rule will every circumſpect man take, in the conquering of his adverſary. Neither is it likely, that <hi>Daniel,</hi> the wiſeſt of Sages, was ignorant of that Rule in reaſon, <hi>Entiae citra ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitatem non multiplicanda.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But let us examine the <hi>toxicum: Hair, pitch,</hi> and <hi>fat.</hi> That <hi>hair,</hi> is not poiſon, though taken in a great quantity, is proved, by the excrements of voracious doggs, which is ſeen to be very pilous; by their ſwallowing <hi>hair</hi> with the hide. If any one object the the heat of their ſtomack, by which hard bones are ground into powder; the fleece comming away whole, and indigeſted, doth enervate that. <hi>Pitch</hi> after it hath layd a while in the ſtomack, is turned into a <hi>chilus,</hi> where it
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:115542:67"/>
depoſeth its viſcoſity: as we ſee in <hi>Terpentine</hi> rejected. <hi>Fat things,</hi> are ſo far from cauſing adheſion, that, by me, they are counted the Soveraigneſt <hi>Alexiteriums,</hi> beſides the diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution of the <hi>pitch,</hi> becauſe of the lubrifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
                  <p>Ib. <hi>That gold boiled ſhould communicate any vertue to the broath,</hi> no man can gather a ſolid argument, from a poſſibility, unto a reality; where both the <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> and the <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> is wanting. If the effects were as evident, as that of <hi>Stibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um</hi> or <hi>load ſtone,</hi> without abatement of weight; then were it beyond all controverſy. That the quenching of it, doth induce a ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity into the liquor, I willingly admit. But by the ſame reaſon [torrefying the terre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiall moats, which alſo produceth its ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainer glaciacion] will, beſides ſteel or ſtones, bread toſted hard, and dipt in hot, imprint an aſtrictive quality on the drink; whereof I uſe, in caſe of coſtiveneſs, to admoniſh my patient's keepers.</p>
                  <p>Ib. Concerning <hi>Coral, whether it grow while it is petrified,</hi> as doth the <hi>ſilver-tree;</hi> or, whether it be not, in its younger age, an herb, reſembling our <hi>Sampire,</hi> hardened after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in its perfect ſtature, may juſtly be queſtioned. For firſt, in every branch there is a hollowneſſe, which may not be admitted; if it have its accretion by externall lapidificall juices: neither could it ſo decently aſcend in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a methodicall form. Let us look into all ſalts, whether vitriol or allum, whoſe encreaſe
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:115542:68"/>
is by appoſition of forinſecall matter; their ſubſtance is more ſolid; and their form, if with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in their proper <hi>matrix,</hi> leſſe expanſe. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, then would the loweſt and thickeſt part, as being the ancienteſt, exceed in hardneſſe; and not be ſo ſtipulous as we find it.</p>
                  <p>Chap. 6. <hi>That putrefactive generations are correſpondent unto ſeminall productions, in vege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tables,</hi> is clear, by the <hi>Author's</hi> aſſertion, and obvious experience. Calcination I take to ſurpaſſe all putrefaction, and to be the extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſt limits of corruption; yet men, of ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved integrity, do affirme that, hereby, ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration is not extinguiſhed Unto <hi>ſenſitives</hi> it cannot be altogether denied, eſpecially in <hi>Teſtaceous Fiſhes,</hi> and <hi>Eeles;</hi> where the <hi>mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria</hi> of the one, and ſlime of the other, falling into a convenient womb, will produce a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cificall progeny; yea it is common to all Creatures, which for want of diſcrimination in ſexes, are denied copulation. For recre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation and admiration, I adde; In my garden I have an herb, much like, in figure and taſte, to the <hi>Cardamine,</hi> with a ſumptuous double flower; the leaves whereof being chopt ſmall, and committed to the earth, every particle will take ſuddain root. Though here be no putrefaction; yet doth the mincing of it deſtroy its extern herbal form.</p>
                  <p>Ib. <hi>Cloves are</hi> no <hi>rudiments;</hi> but a perfect fruit, which I can ſhew compleately faſtened to the <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>mbella.</hi> It is no kind of Medler, which, after reaping, muſt receive a new fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation.
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:115542:68"/>
By the ſame ſtandard, all our corne ſhould but prove initiated <hi>rudiments:</hi> which like to the <hi>cloves,</hi> for their preſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, have nothing, but their ſuperfluous hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midity, exhaled from them.</p>
                  <p>Chap. 7. Whether for Medicament or aliment, I know not; but ſeverall, beſides me, have ſeen <hi>Catts eat mint and nipt.</hi> It's moſt probable for ſome correctory: as <hi>Bears will lick ants;</hi> inſects, in quantity, too infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour, to allay their voracious appetite. In the time of ſatiating their former hunger, there would riſe up a ſecond, which ſhould prove more eager.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="book">
                  <pb n="128" facs="tcp:115542:69"/>
                  <head>BOOK. III.</head>
                  <p>CHap. 1. <hi>That Elephants have no joynts,</hi> though, by ſome, it be delivered in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall termes; yet was not their <hi>Minerva</hi> ſo dull, to except all; but did intend the <hi>ſuffra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gineous</hi> or <hi>knee joynts</hi> onely: without which there may be a progreſſion in man; as upon ſtilts; by the ſole motion of the hippe: in <hi>quadrupedes,</hi> as in a full gallop. But of the <hi>Elke</hi> conſult with <hi>Caeſar. Alces crura ſine no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis articuliſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> habent: neque quietis cauſa pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbunt;</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Lib. 6.</note> 
                     <hi>neque, ſi quo afflictae caſu conciderint, erigere ſe poſſunt,</hi> &amp;c. Neither can I deny ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely <hi>reſt to ſtanding:</hi> ſince, in that poſture, many fouls, [eſpecially carnivorous or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacious ones, whom nature for fight hath fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with the ſtrongeſt thighs and tallons; A cock doth by the ſame geſture, obtain his victory, that he doth his food by ſtriking backward,] yea horſes do take their ordinary repoſe. I could relate ſtrange things ſeen in man.</p>
                  <p>A favourable conſtruction of the Ancient's tenents, if it can conſiſt without infringing Authority of truth, is more piety; and it ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voreth of reverence, to cover our Father's na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="129" facs="tcp:115542:69"/>
Ib. <hi>How every muſcule hath its free ſite,</hi> may beſt be diſcovered, where all the muſcules are alike affected: and that is, in thoſe that are drowned: which is not a right, but an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clining poſture. Some advantage to an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite <hi>Anatomist.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Chap. 2. <hi>The cauſe of the often dunging in the horſe,</hi> I ſhould rather aſcribe it to the moiſture of his meat, then <hi>to his gall:</hi> ſince, if grooms have any credit, his going to graſſe, doth acquire a frequency in excretion: his ſtanding in, with dry meat, which is more <hi>bilious,</hi> doth contract a rareneſſe. I leave the deciſion to the farriers.</p>
                  <p>Chap. 9. <hi>If propagation be by a reall tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion from every part;</hi> then would thoſe, who have ſupernumerous or mutilated joynts; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce their like. Soon would ariſe whole fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies of deformity: Nay, all <hi>Adams poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity ſhould have been defective in one ribb;</hi> as is granted 7 <hi>Book Chap.</hi> 2.</p>
                  <p>Chap. 12. toward the end. <hi>That God animated the ribbe of</hi> Adam's <hi>apart,</hi> is not ſo evident: but, by traduction, its ſoul might proceed from the ſoul of <hi>Adam.</hi> There is no mention, in Scripture, of inſpiration into the woman: Neither, for perfect propagati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, is there requiſite a diſtinction of ſouls in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſexes. There muſt be a ſoul of the female; but no female ſoul: As one man was generated without a man; ſo one woman without a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man: both, moſt like in ſleep.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="130" facs="tcp:115542:70"/>
Chap. 13. <hi>In frogs,</hi> with ſome few other creatures, I find a riddle: that, <hi>all their life time, they delight in their womb,</hi> which is <hi>the water.</hi> For, after excluſion from the ſpawn, in it are all the joints articulated, and metamorpho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed into another ſhape: from <hi>apodes</hi> to <hi>qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drupedes,</hi> from tailed to bobbed.</p>
                  <p>Chap. 16. <hi>Catterpillers</hi> and <hi>ſilk-worms are left to their own ſhift, without a maternall tui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:</hi> I marvaile, what priviledge the accur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <hi>viper</hi> ſhould have got, to be exempted from the ſame hardſhip; why nature ſhould be a German to this, and to the other, but a Step-mother. Though the one be vivipa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, the other oviparous: yet doth it not amount to a neceſſity of diſcrimination, in one above another, of a parentall foſtering: both being equally able, to ſhift for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and live at their own hands: This therefore can be no <hi>argument against the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's death.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Chap. 17. Others with me, that have brought up <hi>ſilk-worms,</hi> will teſtifie, that <hi>in them;</hi> both of <hi>magnitude,</hi> wherein, ordinarily, the female ſurpaſſeth twice the male; and <hi>ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitalls,</hi> there is a manifeſt diſtinction. Three ſmall pricks, ending like a <hi>pyramis,</hi> in one point, is the tegument of his viriſity.</p>
                  <p>Chap. 18. The cauſe of a <hi>Mole's dimneſſe,</hi> is a thick and hard tunicle covering their eyes: which, if it were thin and tender, would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually be moleſted, and ſoon worn out, by the angularity of ſand: they ſeeking their
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:115542:70"/>
food, by looſning the earth, upward.</p>
                  <p>When they are ſaid <hi>to be blinde,</hi> it is not to be underſtood in their loweſt <hi>ſpecies;</hi> but in the next above it: in the catalogue of of <hi>quadrupedes.</hi> They have skill, though not to uſe, yet to refuſe light.</p>
                  <p>Chap. 21. I doubt <hi>whether ſmelling be the principall end of noſtrills:</hi> Although <hi>Fiſhes</hi> have no lungs, yet their <hi>gifts,</hi> are an analogicall ſubſtitute for <hi>reſpiration.</hi> I ſhould count that the principall function of a part, without which, the creature cannot ſubliſt. What if reſpiration be not preſently aboliſhed, upon the ſtopping or looſning of the <hi>noſtrills?</hi> no more is ſmelling; in both there is a dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nution. The mammillary teats in the brain, are the proper receptacles of odours: the paſſage unto them, is the external cartilage. But of all ſenſes, Smelling would be leaſt miſſed: and deprivation of that ſenſe, is reckoned among the <hi>leves jacturae.</hi> While I was thus ſcribling, I had a patient, who, probably, by the loſſe of his ſmell, did redeem his indangered life. There may be a mercy in a privation: and the <hi>night hath its pleaſure,</hi> ſaith <hi>Seneca, in ſolacing of the blind.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Ib. If <hi>in all aliments there be a ſapidity:</hi> the more ſapid, the more alimentitious: but ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced and ſalted diſhes, are counted among leaſt nouriſhing diets. Again, the more ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentitious, the more ſapid: yet no food in nutriment can hold pace, with the inſipid egge. But all ſenſes delight in a mediocrity.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="132" facs="tcp:115542:71"/>
Chap. 22. <hi>Whether Chilification be not a corroſion, by ſome ſharp ferment,</hi> I queſtion: when I ſee doggs devour hard bones, and, not long after, reject them in a friable <hi>album graecum:</hi> which, if rare, were as wonderfull, as that <hi>an Oſtridge ſhould diſgeſt Iron:</hi> Not unlike to that acid flegme, expelled by vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miting, which, in corroſion, is not inferiour to the ſharpeſt vineger. The ſowre rennets of beaſts come under this notion; which being familiar and pleaſant to domeſticks, within doors; breaking forth, prove troubleſomegueſts to their neighbours: which is proper alſo unto gall.</p>
                  <p>Chap. 23. It were a rationall labour, and would correct, not onely <hi>Vulgar,</hi> but alſo <hi>Medicall</hi> Errours, to ſearch the reaſon, why <hi>Unicorn ſhould cure poiſon.</hi> Some poiſons [I ſpeak not of outward, which are cured by li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatures, attractives, <hi>&amp;c.]</hi> are dulled, by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibition of great quantity of drink, as <hi>livium:</hi> Others, by obtunding or blunting the corro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding teeth of its arſenick; and that is by fat things: many by manifeſt contraryeties, as <hi>Opium</hi> by <hi>Coſtoreum;</hi> the latter, by its heat, conquering the former's coldneſſe, and that within the neareſt <hi>genus</hi> of ill-ſavoured Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines. Others attain an help by ſudorificks, and that in venemous and peſtilentiall aire, intermingled with our ſpirits. Not a few, by hindring its venome, from ſpreading to the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talls; by their ſtipticity and dryneſs, inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepting or exſiccating the <hi>effluvium.</hi> So doth
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:115542:71"/>
                     <hi>Bezoar, Bole, Coraell,</hi> as <hi>Ivory</hi> in the <hi>Jaundiſe;</hi> And this way <hi>Unicorn</hi> or <hi>Harts-horn</hi> may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a tolerable remedy. But whoſoever look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth for an effect proportionable to the heighth of its renown or price; I am more then affraid, he ſhall be fruſtrated of his expectation.</p>
                  <p>Chap. 24. In ſtrict reaſon, <hi>Terreſtriall animalls ſhould have their praenomination, above all Marine creatures.</hi> The former <hi>Adam did name, according to their nature;</hi> to the other [as is confeſſed] men muſt fain an <hi>analogicall denomination.</hi> The one were preſerved in the Arke, to have a name among the living; The other, if they were not, by the confuſed co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ition of freſh and ſalt water, deſtroyed, were mainly damnifyed: For few fiſhes, and thoſe of the delicater kind, will endure, eſpecially ſo long a time, both pure, or commixture of water. But I ſee no abſurdity to ſay, that the Sea, [as at the firſt ſo] after the ſeparation of that grand conflux, might produce <hi>junior</hi> fiſhes, out of its emptied womb. And accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to this <hi>Epoche,</hi> in my <hi>Herauldry,</hi> the creatures of the earth, ſhould have the prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative of the ancienter houſe.</p>
                  <p>Chap. 26. <hi>The contracting of a glo-worm extended, is no argument of life.</hi> For this doth befall moſt dead inſects, moving by annnular fibres. In artificiall things it is very obvious; the experiment may be ſeen in a <hi>quail pipe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Ib. In the <hi>center of the kernell of grain,</hi> as the ſafeſt abditory, is the <hi>ſcource of germina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> which may and doth <hi>eſcape the amputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:115542:72"/>
of the extremes, by a knife;</hi> but <hi>not the terebration of the piſ-mire;</hi> though very ſmall: The latter hindereth it from <hi>ſprouting;</hi> ſo doth not the former. Neither is it a ſhame to learn from beaſts; we owing the invention of moſt mechanick arts, to the inſtinct of unreaſonable creatures.</p>
                  <p>Ib. That <hi>no lati-rostrous animal doth ſing,</hi> is not eaſily gain-ſayed: But <hi>that a flat bill, is an open diſadvantage unto ſinging,</hi> may be doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; ſeeing many modulations are upon flat winde-inſtruments; and man, without a beck, can tune any kinde of voice. The reaſon of circular extreames, in pneumatical pipes, is, that the ſound the eaſier might be prompted into its proper form, a globe. As, from the converſion of a triangle, the product is a cone; ſo, from the circumvolution of a circle, ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the voice's naturall figure, a Sphere. In ſtrict ratiocination, the proper forge of <hi>Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick,</hi> is not the <hi>bill,</hi> but the <hi>throat.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Ib. Though <hi>a ſpider ſhould vanquiſh a toad,</hi> it were, [to ſpeak gently] temerity, <hi>to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe the one, as an anti dote to the other.</hi> Let, by the ſame law, a chicken be an antidote againſt ſpiders. Oile, which killeth all ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getables, will preſerve man againſt the moſt deletory <hi>Granum Nob.</hi> The ſame dangers are not to be looked for, in the dead bodies of venemous animalls; which were feared in their life; as the learned <hi>Author</hi> doth rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onally deliver, §. 12. of this <hi>Chapter.</hi> And if their poiſon ceaſe, I ſhould ſcarce truſt
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:115542:72"/>
their antipoiſon: yet the plague, after many years ſleep in linnen or wollen, will awaken and rage; by the teſtimony of our predeceſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours, backt with our own experience.</p>
                  <p>Chap. 27. The <hi>yellowneſſe of the ſtomack, and gutts in the chicken,</hi> doth not neceſſarily argue <hi>its nouriſhment on the yolke;</hi> though I believe the thing, yet not the reaſon: For the ſame colour is apparent, in all new-born babes; except, with ſome, <hi>Omnia ex ovo,</hi> which, in a Metaphorical and florid ſenſe, may be admitted, with a Rhetoricall ſtrain; but in a Phyſicall demonſtration in ſtrict termes, is hard to be underſtood.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="book">
                  <pb n="136" facs="tcp:115542:73"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>BOOK</hi> IIII.</head>
                  <p>CH. 1. That <hi>ſitting is not proper to Man on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> the ſeveral kinds of Apes, by their untaught Mimicks, and Dogs, by teaching, will draw it into queſtion; If ſitting upon the ground or flat, may come under that denomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation. Man can do no more than theſe beaſts; and will make <hi>a cute Angles, between Back, Thigh, and Leg bone,</hi> [though inverted] as do irrational animals: And beaſts will, upon ſeats, make as <hi>right Angles,</hi> [two lines to an Angle] as doth man.</p>
                  <p>Ch. 5. The uncertainty of <hi>generating males by a ligature, of the left teſticle,</hi> may more ſolid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be refuted, becauſe in congreſs, the males right, is the females left; which left ſide, is not thought the proper place for maſculine conception: ſo that this conceit falleth by its own weight: Neither was this arrow full drawn home to the head. Some probability there might be in thoſe creatures, which ingen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der by infilition.</p>
                  <p>There are three kinds of Being, <hi>Real, Ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal,</hi> and <hi>Modal:</hi> the latter is neither of the former, but more then Rational, yet leſſe then Real. Such is this relative ſite. The want of which accurate diſtinction, bringeth one into a maze of confuſion.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="137" facs="tcp:115542:73"/>
Ch. 6. <hi>That fat bodies do ſoonest float,</hi> there is an errour, <hi>à non causâ ad cauſam.</hi> The true reaſon is, that they have leſſe proportionable weight depreſſing them, then lean bodies. If the whole body were fat, it would never ſinke. Not that <hi>fat is, under water, more prone unto fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation,</hi> which is the cauſe alledged; We beſprinkle our almonds, in beating, with Roſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>water, to preſerve them from reſtineſs. To ſpeak properly, Oyly or fat bodies ſcarce grow rotten, but rancid. Neither doth fat, ſo readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſymbolize with air, as the Schools teach. Let oyl, greaſe, or tallow be boyled unto va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pours, and I will believe: ſuper-infuſed it will preſerve liquours freſh, excluding all allien air: By the ſame reaſon, it defendeth iron from ruſt, and locketh up, faithfully, whatſoever it is intruſted withall. To ſay, it will ſoon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive a flame, is no ſatisfactory argument; for the ſame happeneth unto chalk-coal, which yieldeth no ſmoak, the product of kindled fat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. Beſides, when the <hi>acme</hi> of fermentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is over, except there be, at the very height of it, a fixation, from ſome external cauſe, the ſubject will fall into a more compacted gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity.</p>
                  <p>Ch. 7. There may be a miſtake in <hi>a blown bladder,</hi> about the <hi>weight</hi> of it; if, either the bladder be moiſt, and then, with extenſion, it dryeth: or if it be blown up with the breath of man, which containeth ſome water.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="138" facs="tcp:115542:74"/>
Further, Gold foliated, and feathers expan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, will not weigh ſo much, nor fall ſo ſwift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as the ſame will, being contracted. Smoak rarified doth aſcend; but being condenſated into ſoot, its nature is to deſcend. The com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon road of conception and production of rain, is an ancient and ſufficient teſtimony.</p>
                  <p>Ch. 10. If <hi>the Small-pox have their Original from ſome quality in the Menſtruum, imprinted upon the child in time of geſtation;</hi> It muſt needs follow that this diſeaſe is <hi>endemical</hi> to the whole world; becauſe of the univerſality of its cauſe: The truth whereof is worthy ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination; and unto mine as far as travellers report is to be credited, the aſſertion is ſecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. That others undergo them never, others often, is according to the diſpoſition of the receiver.</p>
                  <p>Ch. 12. <hi>The meaſuring of the motion of bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies doth teach us their duration.</hi> No duration then to the center either of earth or heavens; becauſe deſtitute of motion. If it be replyed, the motion need not to be in the thing but either in the Sun or Earth; neither is that abſolutely true: For a motion of either up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon its own <hi>axis,</hi> if the body be homoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous, which is queſtioned concerning the Sun, will be no rule of meaſure. A <hi>loco-moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> will be requiſite. How far ſhall <hi>Saturn</hi> out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure the <hi>Moon?</hi> A ſtep higher: There may
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:115542:74"/>
be a time of duration without motion, as were the <hi>three firſt days,</hi> before the Creation of Sun or Stars. There was a flux of time in the dayes of <hi>Joſhua,</hi> when the <hi>Sun stood still:</hi> This Philoſophers call <hi>interval time.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ch.</hi> 13. If <hi>ſince the world began Syrius, aroſe in</hi> ♉, <hi>and before its end may have its aſcent in</hi> ♍ by that compute, the world's glaſs ſhould run yet 12000 years: And where are then the laſt times, wherein the Apoſtles lived? <hi>Sed meliora ſpero.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="book">
                  <pb n="140" facs="tcp:115542:75"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>BOOK</hi> V.</head>
                  <p>CH. 4. Might not theſe words have been ſpared, <hi>In Paradiſe there was no creature hurtful?</hi> Since there was none, the Devil ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted, all the world over. It might with better reaſon have been queſtioned, <hi>Whether there were any Medical Plants?</hi> I think, to ſay, any <hi>Therapeutick Medicines</hi> were exiſtent, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a diſeaſe be in nature, is fruſtraneous: But that they had then a <hi>Prophylactick</hi> vertue, to prevent all ſeminaries of maladies, may ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily be underſtood.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Botanicks</hi> comprehend corn, trees, and fruit, within the tome of their <hi>Herbals.</hi> Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſins might be a preſervation againſt rain and darkneſs. As other Phyſical Plants, ſo <hi>Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barb</hi> might ſerve for food to ſome creature. Many things ſtand for ſymmetry and comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Univerſe.</p>
                  <p>But, to ſpeak with the Schools, there were remedies in Innocency, radically and poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially; but not actually, and formally: So was repentance and commiſeration in ſinleſs <hi>Adam.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Ib. <hi>There was a natural ability in Eve,</hi> after
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:115542:75"/>
impregnation with a boy, <hi>without imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting the Creation,</hi> as ſhe had killed the ſoul, ſo <hi>to destroy the body of Adam;</hi> without the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boliſhment of a <hi>Species:</hi> But this would, I confeſs, have uſhered in many moral abſurdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</p>
                  <p>Ch. 5. That <hi>Adam ſhould be created with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Navel, becauſe he was not nouriſhed that way<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> I ſee no neceſſary conſequence. For it is of all ſides granted, that, to the ſame part of the body, do appertain ſeveral offices. Now if, for the <hi>Navel</hi> be taken the out-ſide only, it ſerveth to the <hi>Umbo</hi> of the belly, for a Center in way of ornament; or for an emun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory. Nature many times curing Drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies that way. Of like uſe are Paps to men. If, for the <hi>Navel,</hi> be underſtood the <hi>Vaſa um<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilicalia,</hi> the inward Ligaments; <hi>Adam</hi> could not ſpare them, they ſerving to hold up the Liver and Blather; the exciſion of them brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth ſudden death: which kind of puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is, according to the <hi>Hiſtorians,</hi> in uſe with the <hi>Egyptians.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>A <hi>Skar is a defect in the skin:</hi> But the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward veſſels of the <hi>Navel,</hi> never deſerved the title of humane part: rather an antecretion, for forty weeks nouriſhment in the dark: which, ſince it precedeth mans being, and doth forſake him being born; the <hi>amputation thereof can be no defect.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Laſtly, the commonneſs and univerſality of this part, to all ſorts and ſexes of people,
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:115542:76"/>
doth take away the reproach of deformity, and ſuppreſſe the tongue from a ſhameful up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braid.</p>
                  <p>Ch. 6. <hi>That the Jews did omit the ſtanding or loin-girding, or ſtaff-handling, in eating of the Paſſeover,</hi> and that without ſin, is not likely: they being eſſential ſignificant Ceremonies, inſtituted by <hi>God,</hi> to ſhew their ſuddain de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture out of <hi>Egypt.</hi> The Traditions of the <hi>Rabbins</hi> are not unknown: But their autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, as being repugnant to reaſon or Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, is often ſuſpected. <hi>Chriſt</hi> indeed was <hi>Lord as of the Sabbath,</hi> ſo <hi>of the Ceremonies:</hi> &amp; he, being the body, come, the ſhaddows were ſhortned; eſpecially, he then inſtituting a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of a diſſonant poſture.</p>
                  <p>A Digreſſion by a <hi>Parentheſis,</hi> concerning thoſe, who fear to approach too near to the <hi>Artolatry.</hi> They dare not ſeem to worſhip the bread, by kneeling before it; yet will they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence it with their head bare; which is no geſture befitting familiar accumbency, and fraternal communion. Who can think that the <hi>Jews</hi> did eat the <hi>Paſſeover</hi> uncovered, it keeping no <hi>decorum,</hi> with the reſt of the itine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rary poſtures? They ſay, we ought herein to ſhew all reverence; But, to enterweave hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane devices, and thoſe incongruous, with divine inſtitutions, is more then irreve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="134" facs="tcp:115542:76"/>
Ch. 14. To the rational defence of <hi>Jephthe,</hi> I add one argument, by others alſo omitted, from <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. <hi>All theſe dyed in faith:</hi> and <hi>Jepththe</hi> is inſerted within the Catalogue of believers. That one unqueſtionable teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, is of more validity with me, then many diſputable arguments, of frail humanity: and when, without pondering, we follow the ſteps of dubious guides, we may ſoon aberre from the way of truth.</p>
                  <p>Ch. 19. <hi>Bears with long tailes,</hi> need not be a <hi>Poetical fiction;</hi> nor a <hi>black Swan a mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroſity.</hi> In <hi>Egypt</hi> there are ſheep of incredible tails, weighing 80 li. White <hi>Bears, Hares, Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tridges,</hi> are common to <hi>Greenland.</hi> The race of <hi>Moors,</hi> and that by a regular production, is no <hi>anomalous monſtroſity.</hi> White Thruſhes, are not rare in <hi>England.</hi> It is not the change of accidents; but the commixture of forreign forms, that breedeth a prodigious ſpecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle.</p>
                  <p>Ch. 21. To <hi>ſit croſs-legged,</hi> or <hi>have our fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers pectinated,</hi> doth really induce a numneſs, and retarding the circulation of the blood, doth affect the heart: and, by compreſſion or diſtortion of the ſinews, is an impeachment to motion and ſenſe. That which Ligatures do on ſet purpoſe, theſe poſtures will perform without advice.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="144" facs="tcp:115542:77"/>
Ch. 22. <hi>The line of life, and of Liver,</hi> in Man or Monky, which generally are taken for <hi>Nature's Manuſcripts,</hi> are but the folds of the skin; when the hand or thumb is bent inwardly. Neither proper to any who have their feet alwaies extended. By the ſame rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon we have not thoſe now, which we had in our infancy; but by accidents, diſeaſes, labour, changeable. The variety and numeroſity of theſe <hi>Characters,</hi> and <hi>Lineaments,</hi> are both more legible and certain, in ſpelling out ones profeſſion: A <hi>Book</hi> fit for <hi>Juſtices</hi> to ſtudy, how to diſcover idleneſs.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="book">
                  <pb n="145" facs="tcp:115542:77"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>BOOK</hi> VI.</head>
                  <p>CH. 2. What Land was out of <hi>Paradiſe,</hi> was <hi>Terra Incognita:</hi> But, to the <hi>Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants the world ſeemeth to be created in Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumn:</hi> For the fruit of all trees was ripe, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept we affirm, that, before ſin, <hi>every month had freſh fruit,</hi> glancing unto <hi>Rev.</hi> 22. 2. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 47. 12. Or, that ſome of the fruit was ripe, while other were but in bloſtome. The name of <hi>Thirſt</hi> ſignifying originally <hi>beginning</hi> which fell on <hi>Autumn,</hi> being <hi>October,</hi> doth perſwade the ſame: But the month <hi>Niſan,</hi> which fell on the Spring, became the new year of the <hi>Jews,</hi> not upon any natural ground; but up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the inſtitution of God, in remembrance of their <hi>delivery out of Egypt:</hi> And that <hi>Abraham</hi> did begin the calculation of years, from the <hi>Autumn,</hi> as having received it, by tradition, from the Patriarch <hi>Enoch,</hi> witneſs both <hi>Joſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phus</hi> and <hi>Euſebius.</hi> But man and beaſt drew their firſt breath in their ſpring; becauſe their flouring years did precede their fruit-bearing harveſt.</p>
                  <p>Ch. 5. <hi>If the Sun ſhould move conſtantly, in the Equator, it would be, unto both poles, continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al day;</hi> becauſe of the refraction of the beams,
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:115542:78"/>
through the air, contrary to <hi>chap.</hi> 14. of <hi>this Book.</hi> But thoſe, who have the Poles vertical, do, for above half a year, in every month, new-Moon excepted, enjoy the benefit of both Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minaries, 14 dayes together.</p>
                  <p>Ch. 7. It is moſt conſonant to the order, which God kept in the Creation, and to rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of man, that <hi>the principles of all things were wiſely diſpoſed, in a convenient Matrix, within Paradiſe,</hi> ſeeing there was a <hi>compendium</hi> of the Univerſe: For as unto all creatures <hi>Adam</hi> gave ſuitable names; ſo he muſt have within it, the <hi>epitome</hi> of the whole world: or elſe he could not have known it. To the Proverb,</p>
                  <q>Non omnis fert omnia tellus; <hi>I oppoſe,</hi> Non fuit ſic à principio.</q>
                  <p>Ib. <hi>The emolument of the Eaſt</hi> is not to be deſpiſed, by them, who have any Sea, or Lake adjacent unto them. There is no ſmall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence from the aſcending rayes of the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning; diſperſing the exhaled vapours of the night: Whereas in <hi>Occidental</hi> coaſts, the damps of the Sea enter into the room of the departed Sun: The <hi>Oriental</hi> is famous for its dryneſs; the <hi>Occidental</hi> manſions, are by their moiſture, rafty. Hence is the frequency of evening thunders; which in a morning is a rarity. The like I ſay of rain-bows.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="147" facs="tcp:115542:78"/>
Ch. 10. <hi>All things are ſeen under the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh of colour:</hi> How this conſiſteth with the <hi>fight of Moles,</hi> I ſee not: For <hi>Book</hi> 3. <hi>Chap.</hi> 8. they are <hi>allowed the ſight of light;</hi> and <hi>that of colours is denied them.</hi> Yet to ſpeak with the Schools, colour is light, terminated in the <hi>ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfices</hi> of a ſolid body.</p>
                  <p>Ib. Concerning the <hi>blackneſs of Negroes,</hi> there ſeemeth ſome promotion of it, either from the climate, or ſoil, which being ſcituated between four great Rivers, whoſe banks are often over-flown; the heat having thereby a thicker <hi>medium</hi> to work upon, than upon pure air [hence, after rain, the new beams of the Sun become moſt ſcalding] doth exhale and fix more vapours, eſpecially towards the head; which maketh their skulls, to exceed triple in thickneſs, ours of <hi>Europe:</hi> So that their proud depth doth contemn the force of the ſharpeſt ſword, as ſeveral times, with admiration, I have ſeen.</p>
                  <p>Ch. 11. <hi>If denigration proceed from mortifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation,</hi> it preſuppoſeth a <hi>cold fire:</hi> as in an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme <hi>maraſm</hi> of age, or by froſt, in <hi>Ruſſia</hi> is evident: Of which ſubject, I remember to have read a rational treatiſe in the <hi>Teutonick.</hi> But I love no <hi>Logomachie.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="book">
                  <pb n="148" facs="tcp:115542:79"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>BOOK.</hi> VII.</head>
                  <p>CHap. 1. It is ſaid, <hi>that the forbidden fruit was never produced ſince.</hi> If it be meant that it ſhould be obſcured, and retired into the cloſet of perpetual latency, I ſee no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for it: becauſe man is now diſobliged from that Commandement. <hi>No man might imitate that holy perfume, Exod.</hi> 30. or tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer it into a domeſtick uſe: But that it ſhould over-awe us, hitherto, morally, ſavoureth too much of <hi>Judaiſm.</hi> By the ſame Law, we ſhall be forbidden the ſmell of <hi>Frankincenſe.</hi> yea, <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine</hi> being once inſtituted for a <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament,</hi> muſt not be expoſed to a natural and common prophanation. If the whole <hi>Species</hi> were annihilated, though it were but in one individual, [as that happeneth unto ſome creatures] it mutilateth the Creation, and bringeth a lameneſs into the beauty of the Univerſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ib.</hi> A Peach, though <hi>with a hard kernel,</hi> is named <hi>Pomum</hi> by the learned: And ſo are <hi>jugulandes</hi> and <hi>ſiliqua</hi> by <hi>Pliny.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Ch. 4. The <hi>Galaxia</hi> or <hi>Milk-way,</hi> if it had a natural ſignature, of both rain and fair wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, might be as <hi>comfortable,</hi> I dare ſay,
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:115542:79"/>
more <hi>frequent</hi> then the <hi>Rainbow.</hi> Beſides, the former is not imitable by the induſtry of man; the latter every plebeian hand can at pleaſure command: yea, a Horſe trotting through ſhallow water, if the <hi>Sun</hi> approach near the <hi>Horizon</hi> ſhall unwittingly raiſe the colours in the Bow, as hath been mentioned before. The conſtancy in duration, and ſcitua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, might challenge a preheminency; but it is ſafe, to acquiſce, humbly, in the wiſdom of the <hi>Maker.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Ch. 5. <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Iſhmael,</hi> inſtead of <hi>Iſaac,</hi> So Ch. 15. <hi>Gold will ſwim in quick ſilver, wherein iron and other mettals ſink;</hi> I dare not but lay the ſlip upon the oſcitant <hi>Printer.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ch.</hi> 7. The <hi>Hyſſop upon the Wall, I would rather take for our Parietaria,</hi> or Pellitory, which is uſed for cleanſing and polliſhing of Veſſels and Glaſſes; This for ſite and virtue, will beſt ſuite which the Herb, which the <hi>Prieſt</hi> uſed in ſacrifice, and the <hi>Botanicks</hi> of <hi>Solomon. Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oſcorides</hi> is dubious.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Chap.</hi> 13. If the <hi>Moon, by exciting the ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tro-ſulphurous ſpirits, at the bottom of the Sea, cauſe high-water;</hi> It is either in regard of its vicinity, or by vertue of her body, or her lihgt. The firſt cauſe is vain: For the perio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicall eſtuation would be at the time of the <hi>pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rigaeum.</hi> The body of the <hi>Moon</hi> is unchange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able: Neither can we conferre this effect to its light; becauſe, at new-Moon, the ſpring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tide is not inferiour.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="150" facs="tcp:115542:80"/>
                     <hi>Galileus</hi>'s ſubtile device, concerning the motion of the earth, hath its ſcruple. It is true, that the water will riſe to the ſides of the Veſſel, being ſwiftly moved; but, that the ſame befalleth the <hi>Sea,</hi> arreſted by the ſhoar, is a doubtfull conſequence: becauſe the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the one is naturall, the other violent.</p>
                  <p>In water, as in all liquid things, I acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge a double naturall motion: by the one, in regard of its gravity, it deſcendeth; by the other, becauſe of its tenacity, it runneth into the form of a Globe. Reiterated drops upon a true levell, (if there be any Phyſicall plane) will evince this; which, ſwelling in the midſt, caſt themſelves into a circle. That dolefull deluge, which did compaſſe the whole earth, was a ſad example. The latter propriety is the product of the former.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Chap.</hi> 17. <hi>That God made all things double, one against another, and that poiſon is not without antipoyſon,</hi> I deſire to have my aſſent excuſed. Not to ſpeak of morall things, where one contrary hath ſeverall contraryes, and one vice as adverſe to another, as vertue to them both; I think God made no <hi>Poyſon,</hi> but all things in the world were made for the uſe of man. Their chiefeſt <hi>deleterium</hi> is, either in the quantity, or ſome other circumſtance, as in <hi>Lettice, Lecks, Caſſervi, &amp;c.</hi> whoſe <hi>integra</hi> are aliments; though juices mortiferous. Thoſe things that are pernicious by their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall form, as <hi>beaten Glaſſe, Sponges, &amp;c.</hi>
                     <pb n="151" facs="tcp:115542:80"/>
have not deſerved the brand of poyſon. Thoſe that are really lethiferous, are but <hi>peccatorum ſudores,</hi> excreſcences of ſin, &amp; came in with the thorns. The <hi>Serpent</hi> was deſtructive rather to the ſoul, then the body.</p>
                  <p>Beſides, ſome <hi>Vincetoricks</hi> are generall, and will be contrary to ſeverall kinds. Finally, in divers creatures, one part is alexipharma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call to the other, as is confeſſed in the ſubſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Section, by our <hi>Judicious Author,</hi> to whom be peace.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
